all rise in this case number 555 on the
calendar in the manner of Dolan versus
Leto thank you you're welcome judge
parties have been sworn in you maybe see
the folks that was seen your honor
I heard the yep outside yeah me too
mr. lado yep yes is the answer yes your
honor
stand up on your own two feet if you can
if you had anything to drink today of an
alcoholic nature not at all have you
used any drugs within the last 24 hours
not at all then behave yourself you got
that didn't require an answer we
understand each other can we do your
honor
take your hands out your pocket man this
can either be pleasant or unpleasant for
you it probably won't be really Pleasant
either way but it could be totally
humiliating or only marginally
humiliating the extent of your
humiliation is totally in your court now
we understand each other we do your
honor
perfect I actually think he got it let's
see how old are you mr. Dolan I'm 18
mr. Leto was a supervisor of yours yeah
he was my boss what kind of work I'm a
dishwasher and a cook at infinite park
it's like a little local amusement park
and how old were you when you started to
work there 17 was mr. Leto your
supervisor at that point yes did you
claim that mr. Leto took some money from
you
you want to tell me about that yeah I
worked there for about a month with
Scott
when did you start I started there the
end of June 2010 I was a dishwasher and
one day I was washing dishes and he
pulled me aside into a secondary storage
room and he started complimenting me
about this ridiculous okay
the extent of your humiliation in front
of your family your mother your father
your grandparents your friends this
person that you brought here with you
and ten million people is strictly up to
you do you understand I understand you
understand you
we'll have a chance to speak all right
thank you this is not your time okay I
still have my fingers crossed
okay you were there for about a month
yes you were washing dishes yes he
pulled you into a secondary storage room
just in case you think I wasn't paying
attention and he said he started
complimenting me about my work habits is
that was great employee is very
respectable and that he was sorry you
had to ask me this but he needed $40
well he didn't need 40 he needed money
he asked me for money he tell you why he
needed money he said he was in a spot
right now he was having a little
financial trouble getting started with
everything he started with what he said
he just moved from Las Vegas and this
job is new he doesn't really know many
people out here he's kind of in a tough
spot and he didn't want to have to ask
me for money but he needed to and I said
well sure I'll see what I have on me and
I had $40 so I gave it to him and then
he let me go home early without doing
much work that night okay let's say that
was sometime in July then what sir then
two weeks went by he was pretty kind of
town look here okay he was friendly with
me who's you know real cool laid-back
about two weeks later on August 2nd he
asked me to borrow more money he
contacted me and said what did he say
and where were you when he has to borrow
more money I don't remember where I was
that he was at the golf course the
miniature golf course at work and he
said I need you know another favor to
you if he was at the golf course you
don't remember where you were he texted
me and said hey what's up and I said not
much she said can I have another favor I
need you know some more money did you
happen to save that text yes do you have
it with you yes I'd like to see it
I have every Texas season
what did you need one hundred and sixty
dollars for sir can I see that so I can
know what the conversation is I mean let
me read it to you okay Scott what's up
Joe not much do you want me to come in
early today question mark Scott I'm not
working but I need a favor from you
again only if you can I need to borrow
160 bucks today and I will pay you when
we get paid the $200 I'm at work right
now golfing I would really appreciate a
Joe I'm in a really tight spot that
sounds exactly like what he just said
right now just a second my question to
you is do you know what you needed the
hundred and sixty dollars for well I
don't even know what the conversation is
for I just read it well yeah but I say
what's up or did he say what's up Scott
Scott raise your hand
I'm Scott what's up okay Joe responds
not much do you want me to come in early
today Joe raise your hand
Scott raise your hand I'm not working
but I need a favor from you again and
then it continues as I indicated right
now you understand I understand what
you're reading and what he said yeah yes
so can you tell me what you needed if
you remember the hundred and sixty
dollars for that afternoon I have no
recollection of the conversation okay
let me go to another one please
well this chant hey man Scott raise your
hand I really need your help I'm in a
situation because I just moved into this
place and I spent a lot to get here and
I'm almost caught up financially I owe
you and MasterCard money and would like
to take care of my MasterCard situation
you can say no but I'm about to ask you
can I borrow 450 more bucks and then I
will work out some sort of a payment
schedule if you do this great if not I
will figure out and try something else
Thanks I'm not gonna talk now no I'm
gonna talk now right yeah I mean I could
take a piece of paper and type out all
sorts of text on it and say hey this was
saying what I'm asking you is these were
texts that you never sent so if mr.
Dolan were to have
any texts from you on his phone from
your phone right that would be also
something he created would that be a
contract no no I didn't say contract I
mean what I didn't say anything don't me
ask me I don't answer your questions I
asked you a simple question okay this is
a piece of paper yep
yes your honor sorry learning learning
yes judge judy continues in a moment I
have well be always behind the 8-ball
mr. Leto mm-hmm usually because they're
wiseguys and have more of a big mouth
than they have brains they find
themselves always behind the eight-ball
they're always look at the scams
somebody always looking to scrounge
their rent always looking to live off
somebody else it's usually not because
they're the brightest bulbs in the pack
I don't want you to put yourself in that
category yet now my question to you was
a simple one mr. Leto if mr. Dolan were
to have on his cellular phone which I
see he has with him any text messages
that come from your phone would that be
a surprise to you yeah yes yes now mr.
Dolan's defense because you say that he
borrowed over the course of the time
that you worked there according to you
$1,700 yeah a little bit here a little
bit there
now mr. Leto said he doesn't know what
you're talking about he never took any
money from you so what I would like to
see is if you have any acknowledgement
not these papers that you handed me but
any acknowledgments other than these
papers that were clearly prepared from
something to demonstrate to me any money
that mr. Leto either asks you for or
received okay I have the physical text
messages in my phone from to see them as
well as bank statements that provide
withdrawal information on the date I
don't even need the withdrawals
statement sir well I want to see it the
text messages from mr. Leto every text
message that is in here
that time
would you show this please to the
defendant
so Scot the boss that would be you that
would be what was entered in what's the
phone number I don't know oh I don't
know either so Scot the boss I can put
any address name in 2010 what date is on
there mr. dhowan they go through August
through October of 2010 of 2010 yeah and
that's when you were working with him
yes mr. Dolan did you ever confront mr.
Leto with your family that's what you
say in your complaint I told him that I
told my family yes he started getting
very defensive and threatening me
because I told other people about what
happened What did he say he said he was
gonna stand here and tell you that I'm a
drug dealer he said he was gonna call my
parents tell them I was a drug dealer he
said I wouldn't go to college because he
was gonna call him tell him that I dealt
drugs and that they don't let those kind
of people there or if I get him a job
then he'd help pay me back he has no
intentions did you ever register a
complaint with the amusement park yes
when after he was laid off when was that
sometime in October October 2010 yes
why were you laid off mr. lado because
the season was over and that's it
so the amusement park closed yeah pretty
much I'm sorry did the amusement park
closed the part I was managing yes so
the answer is it did not closed not the
entirety now where did you go to work
after October I went to work for another
company named Pawn Stars what is that
it's a pawn company that has multiple
locations and I handle the Amazon and
eBay accounts for them how you paid a
salary or a commission or a combination
of both I'm paid a combination tell me
what the combination is it's a 10% on
ROI what is that return on investment
and at 2000 salary per month so whatever
that works out to be are you still
working for them yes you've been working
for them since when a few weeks now a
few weeks yeah how did you go to work
for in October I did not go to work for
anybody in October
who did you work for in November nobody
December
nobody January nobody February the
company I worked for an hour so you
started there the end of February
correct who supported you in October
November December January and part of
February myself in the state of
California your honor state of
California how unemployment how much did
you collect from unemployment from the
state of California five hundred sixty
dollars per month and when did you get
the job with this amusement park April
19 2010 and you work there until October
that is correct
so let me understand this he came to the
state of California and you worked here
marginally for a period of approximately
six months that's correct
and after you work marginally at a job
in the state of California for six
months then you're entitled to
unemployment for how long I believe it's
up to a year that's why they going
bankrupt now how long did you live in
Las Vegas I lived in Las Vegas for
probably like six months maybe how did
you support yourself there mr. Leto I
have wealthy family that's why this is
so absurd for one and that's how I
really proud of you they are yes no not
after today you don't think so I listen
to me not if they're wealthy and smart
well everybody's entitled to their own
opinion like mr. Dolan I think you're a
hustler mr. Leto I think you were real
hustler in any event you can't take
money from a 17 year old and when you
add up all of these dollars comes to a
little over $1700 that's what you're
gonna pay him from you $2,000 a month
salary that you haven't started to
collect yet judgment for the plaintiff
that's all very much
Judge Judy didn't need to hear from him
she just knew what kind of person he was
when he walked in the courtroom I'm a
tyrant and when I'm a manager I'm very
authoritative he's a liar in the con men
and he's pretty good at it I told him
what I wanted him to do he didn't do any
of it he made up some pretty good
stories I think it would be interesting
you know to maybe pursue like a slander
in a civil litigation or just something
really stupid they put you on TV and now
the next case all parties in a matter of
j'avais vs. Acosta step forward please
Debra Gervais is suing 21 year old
Jacqueline Acosta for trashing her home
and stealing money while house-sitting
mr. vellieux complaint alleges that the
defendant who was a co-worker of yours
was retained by you to do some dog
sitting for you she was going to be
staying at your house and doing the dog
sitting you were going on vacation yes
that is correct and Miss Acosta
according to you either herself and/or
friends
trashed her house and stole some money
that is correct and you want to be
compensated miss now when did you go on
vacation and when was she supposed to be
babysitting for your dogs this was the
second occasion we had asked Miss Acosta
to stay in our home the first event went
spectacular we were very pleased with
her so we asked her again my husband and
I were going for an extended time my son
who lived with us his girlfriend - do me
a favor just tell me when she was
supposed to be taking care of your pets
August 21st through the 24th of 2009 yes
ma'am
and is that when this occurred yes so
what's taking you so long to sue her
after the event
my son had come home in the home was in
disarray no no that's not what I asked
you mr. BAE what I asked you was this
happened August of 2009 which is now a
year and a half later my question to you
is what's taking you so long
to sue her well we had an agreement for
repayment for damages and things that
were removed from my and that would have
been in 2009 correct and she just a
second how much did she agreed to pay
you the total was $1,200
how much did she pay you I have receipts
that it totaled three hundred and ninety
one dollars see that's a reasonable
answer
she agreed to pay we didn't sue her
because she was in fact pain pain go
okay
well mr. BAE asked me to house to listen
to me very easy you trashed her house I
did not crash her house what did you pay
her $391 for because I felt that if she
believed that we trashed her house I was
going to just compensate listen to me
you see you could do with jams you
dancing doesn't fly you don't pay
somebody for something that you don't
acknowledge you did so I don't care what
you felt she felt if you said I didn't
trash the house or take anything or
neither did any of my friends she
wouldn't have paid a $391 I paid every
ninety one dollars because I was
basically 19 years old didn't know what
to do
I was never in trouble with the law so
of course I felt pressured to feel as
though I owed that money but I did not
owe anything you didn't get a job with
another law firm did you know pictures
for the house after she trashed it I do
as well as that I like that do you want
all the photos or just of the home I'll
take a look at all of them it's not a
difficult case
you weren't there were you LS who else
was fast there now stand who else was
there I'm not talking to you I'm looking
at you you see my eyes looking at you is
five of our other friends mammal female
both - just now sit okay judgment for
the plaintiff in the amount of eight
hundred and nine dollars thank you very
much
excuse me step out my son had called me
actually we were still away on vacation
and when he got home and the conditions
of the home he called me immediately if
by damaging you mean I didn't mop the
floor clean up after myself and okay
yeah I violated the house had no idea
that we would come home and or
experience what we miss Edmunds where's
your boyfriend he's at home what does he
take muscle relaxant pills for he got
back surgery and he needs them for that
when did he get back surgery about four
months ago and what kind of muscle
relaxants does he take he was taking
baclofen and is that what mister mrs.
grants dog ingested while you were dog
sitting yes so that means I assume that
your boyfriend was staying at their
house with you while you were dog City
my boyfriend came over a couple times so
that your boyfriend was staying at the
house because otherwise if he had back
surgery and muscle relaxants he wouldn't
have left the medication at home unless
he was staying there I had extra
medication just let's not play with each
other if you had extra medication who
give me the name of the doctor who gave
you extra Medicaid not for me it was his
medication so it'll give me the name of
the doctor who gave him extra medication
so we could add muscle relaxant
medication all over where he was staying
your house his house his mother's house
do you understand what I'm saying to you
all right
let's not play with each other so your
boyfriend was staying over there while
you were house-sitting and dog sitting
for mr. and mrs. grant while they were
on their honeymoon so far correct yes
well he cooked well what we were told
that he had multiple stressin to me
don't give me manushya look at the big
picture
of what I'm saying to you is anything
that I said inaccurate no your honors
not and while you were babysitting of
the dog with the boyfriend
you negligently or the boyfriend
negligently left the medication
available so that the dog ingested the
medication ultimately had to be
euthanized but before the dog was
euthanized
there was a vet bill that was run up in
the amount of it was initially 7,500 I
negotiated down as 6500 and then we had
pet insurance that paid another two
thousand swords 4500 plus some
incidental cost and that's what they
want you to pay to the vet because it
was as a result of your negligence Your
Honor I'm just laying out the case is
that pretty much the case that's very
accurate yes okay so now you're gonna
tell me miss Edmonds when did you start
house-sitting and Pet Sitting for the
grants I don't know the exact date I
don't have any do you have the
approximate date I believe it was I
don't know you know what date of I'm
sorry
there was November 22nd it was the week
of Thanksgiving and on what date did you
find the dog unresponsive and had to be
taken to the vet I found him I believe
it was two days after things three go
ahead when I came home from work the
pills had been locked me the bathroom
and the dogs can get them the dogs had
gotten into the bathroom into my stuff
and she startles how could they have
gotten into a locked back it wasn't
locked it was a slider door
well you said locked it was a bathroom
that I kept my stuff in there it wasn't
sorry okay it wasn't locked but I had
kept my stuff in there for three days
and they hadn't gone in there at all at
all but the day I came back she our
fault
it's not my fault it's an accident oh
listen to me I didn't keep that that's
it to me that's not an on purpose do you
drive a car yes do you have insurance
yes why do you have insurance in case
anything happen in case you have a
accident right that's not what we call
it on purpose that's an accident now an
accent is something that you don't
intend to happen you don't intend to if
it's somebody with your car you don't
intend to hit another car with your car
you don't intend to
run over a person with your car that's
called an accident and because we are
afraid that our car can be taken away
our homes can be taken away our wages
garnished we have insurance takes care
of taxes not on purposes there's a
difference between an on purpose and an
accident this was in fact an accident
not an on purpose there is no question
in my mind miss Edmonds that you did not
intend for their dog to ingest your
boyfriend's medication I want you to
understand that I don't believe that you
did this on purpose it was an accident
when you are driving in your car and
you're not paying attention and you hit
another car who is responsible because
the accident was right you see how easy
this is becoming miss Edmonds 10th
season I'm not ready yet
the dog is not as smart as you are they
don't know not to eat the muscle
relaxants that's why when you're in
charge you're supposed to be responsible
now do we understand perfect now you can
tell me what you want to tell me okay
I don't think that I'm liable for this
because they were on vacation and they
waited two days to come home I wasn't
able to do anything as far as the
decision so what you're telling me is
that it was your fault that the accident
originally took place because you
negligently left either the door open to
the bathroom or left the medication at a
place where the dog was able to get it
inside or outside the bathroom but that
it was ultimately their fault for not
coming home earlier on their vacation
once they were notified that the dog was
in the hospital that's what you're
telling me
that's what you're telling me it's not
what I'm telling you running so whose
fault was it that the dog was able to
get the medication it's my fault
ultimately that's going to step-by-step
whose fault was it that the dog was able
to get the medication hmm mine and whose
fault was it that the dog took the
medication not my fault the dog's fault
no no it had to be they were on their
honeymoon you're the dog sitter so it
was either your fault
your boyfriend's fault or the dog's
fault because that's the only people
that were there right you the boyfriend
and the dog whose fault was it
it's the dog's fault the dog's fault
there's the final bill there
now reference to us coming home two days
later we were unavailable on phone and
checked our email sporadically and this
all happened early Sunday morning late
Saturday night and we checked our email
Sunday late afternoon and that's when we
got the information called the vet at
that point got the whole story and we
were taking the red-eye on Monday to
come home and so that was basically the
earliest that we could have gotten there
so I know it's I don't think that you
actually bear any responsibility what I
don't have negligence on that part but
I'm just saying that we're not heartless
people we loved
okay you would have rush home so would
have come home yeah that's the child
like it's not my fault syndrome but I
actually think that after miss Edmunds
and I had a discussion just now maybe
something I said pierced her hair and
she understands that it was her fault
that the medication was left out right
just as if miss Edmonds if you were
babysitting for a two-year-old and you
were sitting and messing around with
your boyfriend on the sofa and the
two-year-old managed to get into your
pocketbook which was left in a place
where the two-year-old could get it and
ingested this medication I don't think
that's a likely situation though it's
completely different
there just a sec autos you don't think
that that's a likely situation you know
that happens all we're going to be a ten
initial listen to me
not by people who were foolish I'm sorry
I don't believe I was foolish yes you're
foolish you foolish to her at least
expressed in writing and then said to me
that it was the dog's fault they I took
the medication dog it was the dogs
fourth so I'm trying not my fault
because I didn't give him the medication
I ain't giving to you like it was treats
okay so yeah we you have children no I
don't but I have dogs
perfect like to keep it that way
judgment for the plaintiff to me about
the $4,500
it was just a tragic situation because
it's not my fault
we don't blame cat necessarily for it
it's an accident
but she is ultimately responsible for it
I don't give the dog the pills any do
anything we can't be financially
responsible I feel responsible I don't
feel like I need to pay for it we lost
our dog which is tragedy enough no more
pills no more dog sitting and then to
have this on top of it I think justice
was served today I'm glad that we came
to judge duty and now the next case all
parties in a matter of Catlin vs.
Crawford step forward please police
Kathleen is suing her former friend
Chris Crawford for loans to pay his rent
and to buy a laptop computer
mr. Crawford what kind of a relationship
did you have with miss Caplan it was a
friendship I've known miss Caplan for
years I met her about eight years and
when you say you have a friendship you
went out for dinner together we went up
to dinner together we went to movie
premieres Directors Guild watch movies
how did you get to the Directors Guild I
think she's in the guild and she would
invite me when they would have movies
there no that's not how I met her my
message
how did you get to the Directors Guild
oh because my son is an actor and I have
something to the film sag Society or
something and I go as his guest okay it
is your plane miss Caplan that you
advanced some money to mr. Crawford yes
some was alone for rent and some was the
balance of a credit card purchase of a
computer my mr. Crawford says that both
things were gifts it's both or was it
I'm not agreeing I'm just stupid
you can't stipulate you know what that
means mr. Crawford what stipulating
means that means when you both agree on
something she doesn't agree that these
things were gifts so you can't stipulate
so much you just try to hold on to
yourself when I come to you you'll
answer my questions I mean right now
it's my monologue
first miss Caplan I want you to tell me
about the computer okay
the truth is I'm not so wealthy that I
could just listen to me okay you want to
do a tryout to talk to your son you want
to go someplace else and talk about
things
find the therapist believe me it's not
too late all I want to know is how did
the computer come about when you
purchased it how much it cost how much
he paid back okay and how much is owed
so let's start with when you purchased
it okay I purchased it around December
31st 2009 I have the receipt when I
purchased it where did you purchase it
from at Best Buy overni was there when
you purchased it just me and the best
tragic you yes
so mr. Crawford well no I'm sorry mr.
copy was there he picked it out I'm so
sorry you see if you weren't so busy
trying to do what you're doing you would
pay attention to my question I said who
was there when you purchased it I was
there and mr. Crawford was present mr.
Crawford be you there when it was
purchased I was there and who picked it
out she told me to pick out what I'd
liked I pick today I did pick it out
okay now mr. Crawford in December of
2009 you would already know miss captain
for about seven years correct
and she took you to premieres and you
went out for dinner and you did other
things yeah I want you to think of the
last time you bought miss Caplan a gift
her birthday and when was that Julie
don't look at her - and I don't ask me I
don't I wouldn't I believe it's June
June June of 2000 2009 June of 2009 no
2010 so six months after she purchased
the computer for you you bought her a
birthday present because she wouldn't
leave me what did you buy her I don't
know what I bought her so eight years
that you've known her you bought her
nothing and so far she has purchased
this computer that she put on her credit
card how much was the computer the total
came to seven hundred and thirty four
dollars and
$0.72 your honor how much did he pay you
back okay I'm not sure exactly how much
he paid me but I know that the balance
due that he owed me was $300 I did not
pay her back I didn't know what I could
the second miss Caplan she's speaking I
was in no position to pay her back
please stop interrupting I'm not
speaking to you how do you know what the
balance due was if you don't know how
much he paid you back no that's what you
said make it miss Caplan
let's not play with me please I'm not
playing with you
yeah listen to me he would pay less than
$45 a month just a second would he pay
that directly to Best Buy no he wouldn't
he would mail it to me and then I would
mail it to Best Buy because I had other
purchases from Best Buy also then I
can't help you miss Caplan that's not
fair listen to me very carefully
madam you don't have any other purchases
on the Best Buy card because when I say
to you how much did he pay you back you
said I don't know if you gotta be here
because I had a piece of paper and every
month he would write down and he would
write down and he would initially oh
sure yeah me how could I miss you I was
in Hawaii because these two why listen
to me
show me the paper with his initials I
don't have the paper on me right now but
I'm telling you it was 1450 miscounted
the truth we show you the $1,150 miss
Caplan for the loan mizzle random if you
don't stop I'm gonna dismiss your whole
case do you understand yes okay if you
don't stop you're gone okay now let's
get to the twelve hundred and fifty
dollars in a check that you gave him
when did you give it to him okay I have
the check here when did you give it to
him on February 17th 2010 for eleven
hundred and fifty dollars tell me the
circumstances surrounding you giving him
that check the circumstances were as he
said we met at a place of Idaho where
you met I said 2010 that was seven years
after you met Kyle me the circumstance
okay writing the check I wrote him the
check because he got fired from his job
for being intoxicated I gave him
money to pay his rent because he told me
he had no rent so as a friend just a
second
may I see the check please yes and I
wasn't intoxicated I caught myself they
fired you Shh
I quit oh sorry miss captain I can't
help you my dear his signature is on the
back of it he'll even admit that I gave
that to him he'll admit that that was
his check he admitted it to me that he
needed help with the round just a second
hey this check is made out to cash B and
there is no signature on the back of it
there he is
there is scribble that I even went to
the bank they said it looks like
scribble because he was probably drunk
hey Your Honor I did take the check my
cash he admits it was under her terms
why would any normal person that wasn't
demented say to a judge who was just
missing a case because there was no
proof that that check was taken by you I
did take the check and I cashed it what
is which explain that to your honor
because it was a gift the check was a
gift and under the condition and the
terms number one I was no it's not my
question to you sir are you not
following me because I might get the
Rosewood to tell you I'm gecko as a gear
listen to me carefully
that's not my question my question to
you mr. Crawford is why would you tell
the judge who was just showing miss
capital in the door because she has no
proof that you cashed that check why
would you acknowledge to the judge that
yes I did take the check and I did catch
it and I used the money but it was a
gift why wouldn't you just keep your
mouth shut
that's my question can you have an
answer for that I hang around her too
much I guess I don't know how to do that
oh so now I have to be blamed for him
being mentally nuts
you won't effective
but your honor your honor to our channel
a step up not alone it says right on the
check alone because he was my friend
we're friends but so I want to help him
out and then it was a controlling thing
you could sue France because I moved to
Hawaii
there could be no longer people divorce
their lives and love them at one time
right be a control issue I've learned
not to lend people so much money and I
think that's where she flipped a lid
[Music]