after finally boarding the ferry headed
for moss deep city our heroes were eager
to get to ash's next gym battle when
suddenly a disguised Team Rocket showed
up revealing their true identity
threatening to capture Pikachu
back and forth the ensuing battle went
as our heroes valiantly struggled to
keep Team Rocket from succeeding in
their evil plot but suddenly in the
midst of the fighting and the angry
threats
Pikachu accidentally launched an
electric attack sending both sides
flying in opposite directions
please man
I'm unbeatable gaining ground on
that was a big electric attack hmm got
any idea where we ended up rock I don't
have a clue meanwhile I'm turning into a
giant prude
well hopefully a ship will come by
what's this it's a submarine you're
kidding
that's great ass you just got what you
were hoping for yeah cool now we just
got to let him know we're out here hey
can somebody help us please we're stuck
on your cell phone hello not those guys
you didn't detect anything on the sonar
no sir the surrounding area appears
empty very good team magma you're right
what are the odds we'd end up on their
submarine of all the rotten luck oh hey
look do you think that's team magma
secret base
reporting in sir the third division has
completed its patrol
calm down you needn't be so afraid my
name is Maxie I'm the leader of Team
Magma yes so what are you gonna do with
us
you can simmer down we're not going to
hurt you it's just that we're a bit busy
right now
so stay in the submarine and don't give
us any trouble until our mission is
complete listen
I'm sorry Maxie this is my fault
it's all right is there any sign of Team
Aqua yes we have detected some motion
under water and have reason to believe
that it's them but can't confirm they're
near Monceau Island I see
everything under control yes ma'am
that's good I knew I could count on you
you'll be free very soon Kyogre
please have a seat I'm sure we can
discuss this in a friendly way yeah well
I'm not talking to you guys come on Ash
I think we better hear what they have to
say yeah why
that's why why am I getting the distinct
feeling that you don't like us ash cuz I
don't that's why I know that you and
Team Aqua aren't friends but I also know
you want to steal ancient pokémon and
then use them to do bad stuff just calm
down
I don't think you should be making them
mad all I'm doing is telling the truth
you better watch your mouth
Janie it's fine right my friend you're
mistaken about us Team Magma sole
purpose is to unravel the mysteries of
our planet and in doing so we will build
a better world for everyone we have
absolutely nothing in common with a
bunch of crooks like Team Aqua why
should we trust you guys either way I'm
sure you realize that ancient pokémon
are legendary and not all that easy to
capture of course but we already have
our ancient pokémon that's right not
only that we also have the ability to
control in Chinpokomon with this blue
orb a blue warm to ease human sorrow
from the floods of long ago Groudon
dispelled storm clouds and caused
volcanoes to erupt forming more
inhabitable land our goal is to use
these Groudon in the very same way and
to establish direct contact with their
ancient world you see the power that
this world holds is way beyond measure
but even as we speak
Team Aqua works against us as they seek
to find Kyogre whose power suppose growl
Dawn's yet what they do not know is we
already have the Cayuga they seek in our
possession you do you captured Kyogre to
having Kyogre is useless to us but we
thought perhaps it would be helpful in
order to ruin team aquas plans
and then we found out some disturbing
news we discovered Team Aqua has a crowd
on open that means that both ancient
pokémon have been gone regrettably this
blue orb can only control a Groudon team
aqua has possession of a red hole but a
red orb can only control a Kyogre the
bottom line is that both of our groups
are faced with holding a pokemon that we
are now unable to control that is why
we're now on our way to monster island
it is there I hope to be able to
exchange our Pokemon but we can't have
kids getting in our way
Tabitha lock these children up at once
right
what's that what is it now function in
Toyotas cargo hold watch yes
let's go Kyogre now
this is Shelly the plans a success
Bravo I wouldn't expect any less from
the strategic commander for Team Aqua
nice work nice disguise Thanks
you're not exactly a Team Magma member
yourself are you I'm only here to help I
realize how important it is to release
Kyogre to the sea how else could it be
controlled with the red orb that's right
and very soon we shall have the power
that allows Team Aqua to rule the world
don't count on it you may be powerful
Team Aqua but so am i fire in the engine
room damage to the portside sinking seal
at the seventh and eighth bulkheads
immediately call the security pause
get it ash it's the blue or right
Pikachu
no you don't buddy Anna don't give it
did you get that all back
could you I want that Pikachu now go
buddy Anna
hold on was that a thunderbolt it was
but much more powerful and what's that
pattern that keeps showing up why you
now's our chance to get out of here are
you all right sir I'm fine but you've
got to hurry it up and capture that
Pikachu
Archy sir we have successfully released
Kyogre from Team Magma ship according to
plan
excellent work Shelley you have once
again proven yourself worthy of my trust
so now I think we should get this show
on the road
convey our will to Kyogre great riddle
and allow this great power to be
released now
hi Olga it is time
Dragonite you and i am a stop Kyogre
wrath but i'm afraid we'll need some
help no we can't dive in the ocean from
here yeah I'm scared but we've got to
jump there's no choice it's ash what's
he doing here
alright guys just close your eyes and
jump Pikachu
we're going into
foolish child you weren't planning on
going anywhere were you now be a good
little boy come with me
trainers which Pokemon would be most
effective against muscleman - okay
trainers did you chose Mudkip you were
right hey
Oh No hey got him what should we do now
Derek where's Maxie he's already left
for Monceau Island commander then we
must go there immediately right Team
Magma crumbles when faced with Kai Oguz
power time to finish this up once and
for all
Cayuga let's go
so Kyogre together you and i can make
quite a gene that's what you call a
blast-off
any idea where we are some decided I win
somewheres hmm isn't that team magma
hovering past so much for the deserted
island Theory let's go now it's a shame
is up dear
look at that color
yeah it's bright red Oh red Gyarados
I've seen that Gyarados before
now are you maxi hmm you have insulted
the name of Team Magma nah but these to
my dad now if I'm not mistaken one of
these two men is your commander correct
I would assume his mission was to steal
our Groudon although he failed quite
miserably didn'ti oh they have prisoners
this is good let's stay and see what
happens first you call for a meeting and
then try to sabotage us
it seems to me the only one doing the
insulting is you and that's not exactly
the best way to do business
look Archie you know as well as I do
that the Groudon means absolutely
nothing to you or your organization so
why don't you hand it over
hahahaha I guess you just don't realize
what a predicament you're in fact is we
got Kyogre to you what here's the deal
Team Magma will be dissolved today while
Team Aqua emerges as ruler of the world
or else if you prefer I could use Kyogre
to destroy everything while you stand
there this is better than my favorite
soap opera Team Aqua managed to capture
both Pokemon and now wants Team Magma to
break oh well I always say when you got
a bunch of crooks trying to out crook
each other that's the time when you
swoop in on um whoa you think Team Aqua
really thinks it can rule the world they
do have two ancient pokémon on their
side yeah we gonna go steal them in
different the divorce is a gift Oh
so then let's go put our promotion into
the ocean haha love that
it'll be okay Pikachu hang in there
buddy
it's you oh he gets you I don't
understand what's wrong
back off
no way are you getting Pikachu from me
hey ash it's me let's lift no way Shh
I'm undercover doing research my
assignment is to stop Team Aqua and team
magma from misusing ancient pokémon
that's what they're doing something
happened to Pikachu
yes your Pikachu bonded with that blue
orb didn't it
yeah I think so you see the intense
energy contained inside the blue and red
orbs can control ancient pokémon but if
any living being comes in contact with
these two orbs for too long
their amazing powers will completely
overcome the mind no you know even
humans have to be extremely careful when
they're handling them since you're
Pikachu was such a small pokemon most
likely it was unable to resist the
energy of the orb
so then plants what do you thinks gonna
happen to Pikachu don't worry I promise
you I'll find a way to break Pikachu's
bond with the blue orb now you two just
wait here a little bit longer okay how
awesome I can't believe this red
Gyarados is Lance's who is Lance he's a
distinguished member of the Elite Four
and right now he's serving as a Pokemon
g-man dragon Pokemon trainers are really
strong well I'm feeling a whole lot
better with someone like him on our side
looks like your dose is taking us to mom
sooo Island that's good it's probably
because Ash and Pikachu are there I just
hope that they're both okay
there it is I shall know in fourteen
equi guys that's not all it's full of
it's loaded down with that Kyogre and
Groudon - shall we lighten their load
yeah
I love that trick okay let's get a move
on and grab that thing before they get
back that Chi Yogesh or cancel a tub I
hope we have a good plan of course we do
we're gonna catch it with a net why need
it coming up hello little real
button-pusher show you how it's done
maybe it needs a little finesse oops
you know you broken it me out thank you
if you and James would have just bought
out it with a white fine
and time to go claim our prize ha and
where do you think you're going are you
from Team Magma Road on Archie we have
discovered intruders in Kyogre cargo
hold sir
so decided to seek your revenge huh but
isn't it Groudon that you really want
you fool we had nothing to do with that
oh no I have a bad feeling about this
come on okay now let's get what we came
for
ready Cacnea pin missile
ah it's time to come with us now Kyogre
No seal the deal with an electric attack
you might be an old fogy Pokemon but
you're still a water type which means
there's no fighting back
that blasting
as the ancient pokémon Kyogre is
released upon an unsuspecting world
Groudon also an ancient pokémon
prepares for the very same fate and what
is to become of pikachu bonded with the
blue orb prepare yourselves as the
awesome and immeasurable powers of an
ancient age are poised to shake our
modern world