>> Rosemary: IT'S THURSDAY,
NOVEMBER 16, AND THIS IS "THE
NATIONAL."
TONIGHT, THE LATEST PLANS FOR
LEGALIZED WEED.
>> Adrienne: WE'RE INSIDE
ZIMBABWE.
THE COUNTRY AT A CROSSROADS.
>> Andrew: WE BEGIN IN A
NEW-FAMILIAR PLACE, A
HIGH-PROFILE MAN AND A WOMAN
SAYING ME TOO.
FROM HOLLYWOOD HEAVYWEIGHTS TO
ENTERTAINERS, EVEN A FORMER U.S.
PRESIDENT, STORIES OF SEXUAL
ASSAULT AND HARASSMENT LEVIED
AGAINST POWERFUL MEN JUST KEEP
ON COMING.
THE ACCUSATIONS STARTED WITH
HARVEY WEINSTEIN SIX WEEKS AGO
AND IT HASN'T STOPPED.
GEORGE H.W. BUSH, KEVIN SPACEY,
RICHARD DREYFUSS, MANY MORE, AND
NEW ONE MORE HEADED TO THE LIST,
AL FRANKEN.
A RADIO HORSE ALLEGES THAT FRANK
EN FORCIBLY KISSED HER AND ON
ANOTHER OCCASION GROPED HER
WHILE SHE WAS SLEEPING.
SHE SAID THE TIDE OF VICTIMS
COMING FORWARD TO TELL HER
STORIES MADE HER FEEL SAFE
ENOUGH TO TELL HERS.
HERE'S PAUL HUNTER.
>> Reporter: IT HAPPENED ON A
U.S. STAGE SHOW PUT ON OVERSEAS.
THIS ONE IN KUWAIT IN '06.
THEN-COMEDIAN, NOW-SENATOR
FRANKEN ON THE LEFT.
ON THE RIGHT, THEN-MODEL,
NOW-RADIO HOST, LEANN TWEEDEN.
HIS LIPS WERE SLIMY AND HE STUCK
HIS TONGUE DOWN MY MOUTH.
I PUSHED HIM OFF BY MY HANDS.
>> Reporter: IT WAS BACKSTAGE,
SHE SAID, FORCED, AND UNWANTED.
>> I SAID, IF YOU EVER DO THAT
TO ME AGAIN, I WILL NOT BE SO
NICE ABOUT IT THE SECOND TIME.
>> Reporter: WHAT'S MORE?
THIS PHOTO WITH TWEEDEN ASLEEP,
FRANKEN ALL SMILES.
>> I WAS VIOLATED.
I FELT LIKE HE BETRAYED MY
TRUST.
>> Reporter: FRANKEN, THOUGHT BY
SOME TO BE A FUTURE DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, TODAY
APOLOGIZED, CALLING HIS ACTIONS
"DISGUSTING AND UNFUNNY."
THOUGH HE SAID HIS MEMORY OF THE
KISS DIFFERS FROM TWEEDEN'S.
LEADERS FROM BOTH PARTIES WANT
AN ETHICS INVESTIGATION AS
FRANKEN NOW JOINS AN
EVER-GROWING LIST OF POWERFUL
MEN CAUGHT IN ALLEGATIONS OF
HARASSMENT AND ASSAULT,
INCLUDING FILM PRODUCER HARVEY
WEINSTEIN, COMEDIAN LOUIS C.K.
AND REPUBLICAN SENATE CANDIDATE
ROY MOORE, WHO AMID APPLAUSE
TODAY, DISMISSED ALLEGATIONS
AGAINST HIM, INCLUDING THAT WHEN
HE WAS 32, HE FONDLED A
14-YEAR-OLD GIRL.
>> THEY'RE NOT ONLY UNTRUE, BUT
THEY HAVE NO EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT
THEM.
>> Reporter: ON CAPITOL HILL
TODAY, DONALD TRUMP DID NOT
ANSWER QUESTIONS ABOUT FRANKEN
OR MOORE.
TRUMP HIMSELF CAME UNDER FIRE
LAST YEAR OVER ALLEGATIONS OF
ASSAULT AND HARASSMENT.
>> President Trump: I BETTER USE
SOME TIC TACS JUST IN CASE I
START KISSING HER.
>> Reporter: BEFORE 60 MILLION
AMERICANS VOTED HIM INTO THE
WHITE HOUSE.
PAUL HUNTER, CBC NEWS,
WASHINGTON.
>> Andrew: TRUMP COULDN'T HOLD
IT IN FOR LONG AND POSTED THIS
ON TWITTER.
>> Andrew: NEW ALLEGATIONS
AGAINST ACTOR KEVIN SPACEY
TONIGHT.
AT LEAST 20 MEN NOW HAVE
COMPLAINED TO LONDON'S OLD VIC
THEATRE ABOUT INAPPROPRIATE
BEHAVIOUR ABOUT SPACEY WHEN HE
WAS AN ARTISTIC DIRECTOR THERE.
>> WE'VE LEARNED IT'S NOT ENOUGH
TO HAVE THE RIGHT PROCESS IN
PLACE.
EVERYONE NEEDS TO FEEL THAT THEY
CAN SPEAK OUT, NO MATTER WHO
THEY ARE.
>> Andrew: THE ALLEGED INCIDENTS
RANGE FROM BEHAVIOUR THAT MADE
PEOPLE FEEL UNCOMFORTABLE, TO
SEXUALLY INAPPROPRIATE TOUCHING.
SPACEY WAS ARTISTIC DIRECTOR AT
THE OLD VIC FROM ALMOST A
DECADE, 2004 TO 2013.
>>> THERE'S A LOT OF QUESTIONS
TONIGHT OVER THE DEATH OF A
TORONTO POLICE OFFICER.
HE DIED OF A FENTANYL OVERDOSE
AND HE WAS A MEMBER OF THE DRUG
SQUAD.
CONSTABLE MICHAEL THOMPSON DIED
LAST APRIL AFTER HE WAS FOUND AT
HIS HOME IN MEDICAL DISTRESS.
IT WAS ONLY A FEW MONTHS LATER
THAT THE TESTS REVEALED IT WAS A
DRUG OVERDOSE THAT KILLED HIM.
THERE WAS ENOUGH FENTANYL IN HIS
SYSTEM THAT THEY DON'T THINK IT
COULD HAVE HAPPENED FROM CASUAL
CONTACT.
ONE OF THE BIG QUESTIONS NOW IS
WHETHER THOMPSON GOT THE DRUGS
THROUGH HIS JOB.
THE SERVICE HAS REVIEWED THE WAY
THAT THEY LOG AND STORE
EVIDENCE.
>> IT'S ONE OF THE FIRST THINGS
THAT WE TOOK A LOOK AT TO SEE IF
THERE IS ANYTHING WE COULD DO ON
THE CHANCE THAT HE DID TAKE
DRUGS FROM THE UNIT TO TRY TO
PREVENT THAT FROM HAPPENING
AGAIN.
>> Andrew: TORONTO POLICE SAY
THEY'RE LOOKING INTO THE
SUPPORTS AND WELLNESS SERVICES
OFFERED TO THE FORCE TO TRY TO
PREVENT THIS FROM HAPPENING TO
ANY OTHER OFFICER.
>> Rosemary: WE KNOW MORE
TONIGHT ABOUT HOW MARIJUANA WILL
BE SOLD IN THIS COUNTRY AFTER IT
BECOMES LEGAL.
ALBERTA AND QUEBEC ARE THE
LATEST PROVINCES TO SPELL OUT
THEIR PLANS
THE QUEBEC GOVERNMENT WILL
CONTROL POT SALES THROUGH THE
LIQUOR BOARD.
A DIFFERENT MODEL OUT WEST.
ALBERTA WILL HAVE PRIVATE RETAIL
MANAGING THE SALES OF LEGAL POT,
SIMILAR TO WHAT MANITOBA HAS
ANNOUNCED.
FIVE PROVINCES HAVE FIGURED OUT
HOW THEY'RE GOING TO SELL WEED.
THERE ARE MANY ISSUES THAT
HAVEN'T BEEN IRONED OUT.
GIVEN THE GOVERNMENT WANTS IT
LEGAL BY CANADA DAY NEXT YEAR,
SOME PROVINCES AND INDEED POLICE
AGENCIES SAY THAT TIMELINE IS
STILL FAR TOO AMBITIOUS.
>> THE LEGALIZATION IS DONE BY
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT OF
MR. TRUDEAU.
IT'S NOT A CHOICE WE MADE.
>> Rosemary: QUEBEC IS ONE OF
THE PROVINCES URGING OTTAWA TO
PUSH BACK THE DEADLINE BY A
YEAR, IN PART BECAUSE THEY WANT
TO KNOW HOW THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT WILL DIVVY UP AN
EXPECTED HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF
DOLLARS IN NEW REVENUE.
>> THE COSTS ARE GOING TO BE
INCURRED BY THE PROVINCES, NOT
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, SO WHY
SHOULD THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
HAVE ADDITIONAL REVENUE WHEN
THEY HAVE VERY FEW LITTLE COSTS?
>> Rosemary: IT WILL INCREASE
EXTRA POLICING, AND STILL
UNKNOWN IMPACT ON THE HEALTHCARE
SYSTEM.
PROVINCES SAY THE TRUDEAU
DEADLINE IS
ARTIFICIAL, BUT OTTAWA PUSHES
AHEAD, SAYING THAT IT PUTS
CHILDREN AT RISK AND MONEY INTO
THE HANDS OF ORGANISED CRIME.
>> THE URGENCY IS WHAT IS
HAPPENING TO OUR KIDS AND
COMMUNITIES AND THE PRICE OF
DELAY IS UNACCEPTABLE.
>> Rosemary: ALBERTA ONE OF TWO
PROVINCES THAT REVEALED PLANS
FOR SELLING POT TODAY.
I SPOKE WITH THE PROVINCE'S
JUSTICE MINISTER EARLIER
TONIGHT.
MANY PROVINCES FEEL THEY CANNOT
BE READY BY THAT JULY 1
DEADLINE.
WHY ARE YOU SO CONFIDENT THAT
YOU CAN BE?
>> Interview: THE DEADLINE IS
CERTAINLY AMBITIOUS AND RELIES
ON US GETTING A BUNCH OF
INFORMATION FROM THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT THAT WE'VE OUTLINED
RECENTLY IN A LETTER TO THE
PREMIERS.
WE HAD A CHOICE BETWEEN GETTING
OURSELVES READY AND AIMING TO BE
READY IN TIME OR WAITING FOR THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO IMPOSE
THEIR MODEL ON US AND I THINK
THAT IT WAS MUCH BETTER FOR US
TO MOVE FORWARD AND IMPOSE A
MODEL THAT ALBERTANS WERE
COMFORTABLE WITH.
>> Rosemary: WHY DID YOU DECIDE
TO DO THE PRIVATE DISTRIBUTION
MODEL?
>> Interview: A LOT OF IT HAD TO
DO WITH FEEDBACK AND THE
GOVERNMENT DOESN'T HAVE TO PAY
UP-FRONT COSTS OR RISKS.
WE DON'T RETAIL ANYTHING, LIQUOR
OR RETAIL OUTLETS FOR
REGISTRIES OR ANYTHING LIKE
THAT.
>> Rosemary: I KNOW YOU HAVE
WORKED ON THIS FOR A LONG-TEAM
AND DID A LOT OF CONSULTATIONS.
IS THERE ANYTHING THAT YOU ARE
STILL CONCERNED ABOUT?
>> Interview: WE'RE WAITING FOR
A NUMBER OF PIECES OF
INFORMATION FROM THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT.
WE WOULD LIKE TO GET
REASSURANCES THAT THERE WILL BE
SUFFICIENT SUPPLY.
SO WE CAN MOVE THE ILLEGAL
MARKET TO THE LEGAL MARKET.
>> Rosemary: HAVE YOU HAD ANY
INDICATION FROM THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT THAT THEY CAN GIVE
YOU THOSE ANSWERS SOON?
>> Interview: NOT AS OF YET, BUT
MYSELF IN CONJUNCTION WITH THE
MINISTER FROM MANITOBA AND
WORKING WITH ALL THE MINISTERS
FROM THE PROVINCES AND
TERRITORIES HAVE WRITTEN A
LETTER TO THE PREMIERS IN TERMS
OF WHAT WE THINK WE NEED IN
ORDER TO HAVE READINESS AND THEN
THAT, IN TURN, CAN BE ADVOCATED
TO THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
>> Rosemary: THANK YOU FOR YOUR
TIME.
APPRECIATE IT.
>> Interview: THANK YOU FOR
HAVING ME.
>> Adrienne: NOT A LOT OF TIME
AND A LOT TO DO.
>> Rosemary: AND IT'S VERY
UNCERTAIN.
THAT GOES FOR A LOT OF THE
STORIES TONIGHT.
>> Adrienne: INCLUDING THE
LATEST DEVELOPMENTS IN ZIMBABWE.
LESS THAN 48 HOURS SINCE THE
MILITARY ROLLED INTO HARARE AND
STARTED CALLING THE SHOTS, THERE
IS PROOF THAT ROBERT MUGABE IS
ALIVE, PROOF THAT THE COUNTRY IS
READY FOR HIS PRESIDENCY TO END.
AS MARGARET EVANS TELLS US FROM
INSIDE HARARE TONIGHT, THERE IS
NO EVIDENCE TO SHOW THAT MUGABE
IS DANCING OFF THE STAGE
VOLUNTARILY.
>> Reporter: TWO DAYS INTO A
COUP, WHICH THEY SAY IS NOT A
COUP, BUT THE STREETS ARE QUIET.
THERE'S A SENSE OF THE PENDULUM
SWINGING.
EVERY NEWSSTAND IN TOWN SHOUTS
IT OUT.
ROBERT MUGABE, ONCE THE STRONG
MAN OF AFRICA, IS NOW UNDER
HOUSE ARREST.
TODAY PICTURES OF THE
93-YEAR-OLD EMERGED FOR THE
FIRST TIME SINCE THE TUESDAY
NIGHT TAKEOVER.
MEETING WITH HIS ALLEGED JAILER,
THE HEAD OF THE ZIMBABWE DEFENCE
FORCES AND SOUTH AFRICA ENVOYS
REPORTEDLY TASKED WITH
CONVINCING MUGABE TO STEP DOWN
VOLUNTARILY.
PEOPLE ON THE STREET ARE
CERTAINLY ANXIOUS FOR IT.
>> MUGABE HAS TO GO.
MUST GO.
HE SHOULD STEP DOWN.
>> Reporter: PUNDITS SAY IT'S
IMPORTANT FOR THE ARMY THAT
MUGABE HIMSELF MAKES THE MOVE.
>> FOR ALL INTENTS AND PURPOSES,
IT'S A MILITARY TAKEOVER, WHICH
IS LIKELY TO LEAD TO A
TRANSITION.
WHETHER OR NOT THIS TRANSITION
IS DEMOCRATIC OR NOT IS ANOTHER
QUESTION ALTOGETHER.
>> Reporter: RUMOURS ARE RIFE
AND MUCH STILL UNCLEAR AND
UNCONFIRMED, BUT THE EXPECTATION
IS THAT THE MAN MUGABE FIRED
LAST WEEK, HIS VICE PRESIDENT,
EMMERSON MNANGAGWA, BACKED BY
THE ARMY, WILL TAKE OVER THE
PRESIDENCY.
AND PERHAPS REACH OUT TO
OPPOSITION POLITICIANS,
INCLUDING MORGAN TSVARGARI.
>> IN THE INTEREST OF THE
PEOPLE, ROBERT MUGABE MUST STEP
DOWN.
1 IN LINE WITH THE NATIONAL
SENTIMENT AND EXPECTATION.
>> Reporter: ROBERT MUGABE HAS
NEVER BEEN KNOWN FOR DOING WHAT
IS EXPECTED OF HIM, BUT THE ARMY
IS NOW IN CHARGE AND THE
PROSPECT OF A SLIGHTLY MORE
DIGNIFIED EXIT FROM THE
POLITICAL STAGE MIGHT BE
TEMPTING, ESPECIALLY IF IT COMES
WITH GUARANTEES FOR HIS FAMILY
AND IN PARTICULAR HIS WIFE,
GRACE, SUCH A POLARIZING FIGURE
IN THIS COUNTRY.
MARGARET EVANS, CBC NEWS,
HARARE.
>> Adrienne: THERE IS A REASON
THAT CALLS FOR MUGABE TO GO ARE
MULTIPLYING, AND WHY THE PUBLIC
SEEMS SO EAGER TO THROW ITSELF
BEHIND WHAT IS WIDELY SEEN AS A
MILITARY TAKEOVER.
IT'S ABOUT THE DESPERATE NEED
FOR CHANGE IN ZIMBABWE, THAT
LOOKS A LOT LIKE THIS.
BANK LINEUPS IN 2008, AND BANK
LINEUPS A FEW MONTHS AGO.
THIS IS A COUNTRY WITH A CASH
CRISIS THAT DOESN'T GET BETTER.
JUST UNDER A DECADE AGO, THE
CURRENCY WAS SO DEVALUED, WE
WATCHED PEOPLE CART AROUND
WHEELBARROWS OF MONEY, BILLIONS
OF LARGELY-USELESS.
HOW MUCH MONEY DO YOU MAKE OUT
HERE?
>> $200 TO $300.
>> Reporter: WHAT CAN THAT BUY
YOU?
>> BUS FARE.
>> Adrienne: THAT CURRENCY WAS
DITCHED FOR THE AMERICAN DOLLAR.
ZIMBABWE HAD THE LARGEST PUBLIC
DEBT IN THE WORLD AND 80% OF
PEOPLE LIVING BELOW THE POVERTY
LINE.
SO U.S. CASH DWINDLED, TOO.
THERE'S A NEW BILL, BOND NOTE.
IT'S NO BETTER, ACCORDING TO
JOURNALISTS WHO ARE STRUGGLING
TO MAKE ENDS MEET AND MAKE THE
COUNTRY MAKE SENSE.
>> SOME BANKS WILL SAY YOU CAN
WITHDRAW $50.
AND SOME WILL GIVE YOU THE MONEY
IN COIN.
SO YOU CAN SPEND ALMOST YOUR DAY
WAITING FOR CASH.
>> Adrienne: IF YOU ARE EVEN
ABLE TO EARN MONEY.
UNEMPLOYMENT RANGES FROM 4%,
ACCORDING TO THE GOVERNMENT, TO
95% ACCORDING TO ACTIVISTS.
>> THIS INDIVIDUAL TOLD ME THAT
THEY WANT CHANGE.
ANY CHANGE IS BETTER THAN NO
CHANGE.
SO RIGHT NOW, PEOPLE ARE
OPTIMISTIC ABOUT HOW IT'S GOING
TO END.
>> Adrienne: ANY CHANGE THAT
LEAVES THEM WITH SOME CHANGE
SIMPLY TO MAKE DUE.
OF COURSE MUGABE'S LEGACY GOES
BEYOND ECONOMIC HARDSHIP.
HE AND THE GENERALS WHO ARE
TALKING CONTROL NOW PRESIDED
OVER PURGES AND PERSECUTION.
PEOPLE WERE ARRESTED, BEATEN AND
TORTURED.
SOME FLED TO CANADA.
THEIR MEMORIES CAME WITH THEM.
AND THESE DAYS ESPECIALLY,
THEY'RE CLOSE TO THE SURFACE.
>> I LEFT ZIMBABWE WITH MY
FAMILY IN 2001 BECAUSE WE DID
NOT FEEL SAFE UNDER MUGABE
RULERSHIP.
>> 2000 AND 2001 WERE THE WORST
YEARS OF MY LIFE.
MOST OF THE TIME YOU GO TO WORK
AND YOU THINK YOU WILL PAY FOR
NECESSITIES.
THEY WILL COME AND GET US FROM
WORK TO GO INTO THE FIELD.
AND OUR JOB WAS JUST TO SING AND
CHEERLEAD THEM WHILE THEY WERE
BEATING WHITE FARMERS.
TAKING OVER THEIR POSITION,
THEIR LAND.
>> WE WENT DOOR TO DOOR,
ENCOURAGING PEOPLE TO
DICTATORSHIP AND TO A ONE-PARTY
STATE.
AND FROM THEN ON, PEOPLE WERE
BEING TARGETED AND ONE
PARTICULAR DAY I WASN'T FEELING
WELL AND I DID NOT GO.
THEY CAME -- THE BOYS, HIS BOYS,
THE SO-CALLED YOUTH, THEY CAME
AND PICKED ME UP AND TOOK ME TO
THE POLICE STATION.
THE POLICE ARE SUPPOSED TO
PROTECT US AS CIVILIANS, BUT I
WAS BEATEN.
I WAS BEATEN.
>> A LOT OF TIMES YOU ARE
DRIVING HOME AND YOU JUST SEE
SUSPICIOUS CARS FOLLOWING YOU.
>> IT'S ONE OF THOSE THINGS THAT
YOU THINK, OK, IF I'M GOING TO
DIE, NOBODY WILL KNOW WHERE I
AM.
THE PLACES THEY WOULD TAKE US,
NO ONE WILL KNOW.
>> WHEN THEY RELEASE YOU, THEY
RELEASE YOU BAREFOOTED.
>> IT WAS VERY DIFFICULT.
WE LEFT OUR FAMILIES.
WE HAD TO LEAVE EVERYTHING THAT
WE HAD AND WE LEFT WITH A
SUITCASE FULL OF CLOTHES
LITERALLY AND A FEW BELONGINGS.
>> BY THE TIME I WOULD GET HOME,
I WAS EXHAUSTED.
I DIDN'T HAVE THAT MUCH MONEY TO
BRING MY CHILDREN AND BUY
TICKETS FOR US.
I LEFT MY CHILDREN IN THE
CUSTODY OF MY SISTER.
AS A PARENT, HOW DO YOU ANSWER
TO YOUR CHILD, OR HOW DO YOU SAY
GOOD-BYE TO YOUR CHILD.
IT'S NOT -- LIKE, GOOD-BYE IS
NOT A GOOD THING TO SAY AS A
PARENT TO YOUR OWN CHILDREN.
I DIDN'T KNOW HOW TO SAY
GOOD-BYE TO THEM.
I JUST CAME BACK AND CRIED.
IT'S ALL I COULD DO.
>> A LOT OF PEOPLE IN SUPPORT OF
THE ARMY AND WHAT THE ARMY HAS
DONE.
PEOPLE HAVE BEEN OPPRESSED AND
SUPPRESSED FOR A LONG, LONG
TIME.
>> AT TIMES I THINK, IS IT REAL
THAT MUGABE'S GOING?
>> FOR US TO SEE HIM LIKE THIS
AND TO KNOW THAT HE'S JUST A
MERE MAN, HAS BEEN AN EXCITING
THING TO WATCH.
THERE'S STILL A LOT OF WORK TO
DO TO RESTORE OUR NATION.
>> Adrienne: JUST SOME OF THE
PEOPLE THAT HAVE HAD TO PAY FOR
MUGABE'S RULE.
MUCH MORE AHEAD ON "THE
NATIONAL."
>>> RUSSIA'S CHANCES OF
COMPETING IN THE NEXT OLYMPICS
ARE LOOKING SLIMMER.
WE'LL GO RINKSIDE WITH MEMBERS
OF THEIR HOCKEY TEAM.
>> Rosemary: IS THE LIBERAL
GOVERNMENT THE BEST JUDGE OF HOW
IT'S DOING?
"AT ISSUE" PANEL WILL WEIGH IN.
>> Andrew: A MARKETPLACE HIDDEN
CAMERA INVESTIGATION WILL TAKE
YOU UNDERCOVER AT THE CAR
DEALERSHIP.
HOW THEY'RE ADVICE MAY COST YOU
MORE.
>> THE AVERAGE CONSUMER SEES
THAT AND THEY THINK, I CAN
AFFORD THAT.
NO PROBLEM.
IT'S JUST ANOTHER WAY TO BRING
CONSUMERS INTO THE DEALERSHIP
AND SELLING THEM SOMETHING THAT
THEY REALLY CAN'T AFFORD.
>> Rosemary: THEY MAY HAVE WON
BIG IN SOCHI, BUT AN OLYMPICS
WITHOUT A RUSSIAN FLAG OR ANTHEM
IS TONIGHT A DISTINCT
POSSIBILITY.
THE ELIGIBILITY OF HUNDREDS OF
ATHLETES IS IN QUESTION BECAUSE
OF THAT COUNTRY'S DIRTY PAST
WITH DOPING CONNECTED TO THE
KREMLIN.
>> RUSADA IS STILL NONCOMPLAINT.
>> Adrienne: THAT'S RUSSIA'S
ANTI-DOPING AGENCY.
IT'S BEEN SUSPENDED SINCE 2015
AFTER EVIDENCE EMERGED OF
WIDESPREAD, STATE-SPONSORED
DOPING.
KEY STEPS FOR REINSTATEMENT FOR
STEPPED OUT, BUT ANNOUNCED THAT
RUSSIA HAS NOT DONE ENOUGH.
>> THE ROADMAP FOR COMPLIANCE
FOR THE RUSSIAN ANTI-DOPING
AGENCY HAS BEEN FULFILLED IN
MANY WAYS.
THERE ARE STILL TWO ISSUES THAT
REMAIN UNFULFILLED.
>> Adrienne: AND THOSE TWO
ISSUES, AS YOU WILL SEE IN A
MINUTE, BIG STICKING POINTS.
CAUGHT IN THE MIDDLE, THE
ATHLETES.
MOSCOW CORRESPONDENT CHRIS BROWN
SPOKE TO SOME OLYMPIC HOPEFULS
THAT THINK THEY'RE IN THE
PENALTY BOX UNFAIRLY.
>> Reporter: EVERY DAY THAT GOES
BY IT SEEMS LESS LIKELY THAT
RUSSIAN ATHLETES WILL BE ABLE TO
COMPETE IN THE WINTER GAMES
THE WOMEN ON THE NATIONAL TEAM
KEEP PRACTICING HARD.
>> Interpretor: IT'S THE GOAL OF
EVERY ATHLETE.
WE WILL BE UPSET IF THEY DON'T
LET US GO.
>> Reporter: THE DECISION THAT
RUSSIA REMAINS NONCOMPLAINT CAME
OUT JUST BEFORE PRACTICE.
THEIR COACH WAS ANGRY.
>> Interpretor: WE HAVE A
COMPETITIVE TEAM THAT CAN FIGHT
FOR A MEDAL, BUT IT WILL BE THE
HIGHEST INJUSTICE IF WE CANNOT
COMPETE.
>> Reporter: THE CANADIAN
PROFESSOR THAT LED THE
INVESTIGATION CONCLUDED
OTHERWISE, THAT RUSSIA'S DOPING
AGENCY, SPORTS MINISTRY AND
SECRET POLICE ALL CONSPIRED
TOGETHER TO HELP MORE THAN 1,000
ATHLETES CHEAT DOPING TESTS OVER
TWO OLYMPIC GAMES.
THE REPORT CLAIMED THAT EVERY
MEMBER OF RUSSIA'S LAST OLYMPIC
WOMEN'S HOCKEY TEAM AT SOCHI HAD
DIRTY SAMPLES SWAPPED FOR CLEAN
ONES
THEY KNOW THIS, BECAUSE WHEN THE
DIRTY SAMPLES WERE TESTED, THEY
HAD MALE D.N.A., SOMETHING THAT
COULD NEVER HAPPEN NATURALLY.
>> Interpretor: I JUST DON'T
KNOW.
AS ATHLETES, OUR JOB IS TO GIVE
A SAMPLE.
MAYBE THEY DID SOMETHING.
I JUST DON'T KNOW.
OUR JOB IS TO TRAIN.
THEY ASKED US TO GIVE A SAMPLE
AND WE DID.
>> Reporter: THE NEW LEADERSHIP
OF RUSSIA'S ANTI-DOPING AGENCY
SAID THEY'VE DONE EVERYTHING TO
CLEAN UP THEIR ACT -- ALMOST.
>> Interpretor: THERE WERE TWO
POINTS THAT WERE BEYOND OUR
PREROGATIVE.
THOSE TWO POINTS ARE LETTING
THEM INTO THE RUSSIA LAB AND
ADMISSION FROM THE GOVERNMENT
THAT, YES, IT ORDERED THE
CHEATING.
THAT WILL LIKELY NEVER HAPPEN.
>> Reporter: VLADIMIR PUTIN
SUGGESTED THAT THE DOPING
CONTROVERSY IS BEING INFLAMED BY
THE WEST TO MAKE HIM LOOK BAD
HEADING INTO ELECTIONS JUST
WEEKS AFTER THE WINTER OLYMPICS
END.
WITH JUST THREE MONTHS UNTIL THE
COMPETITION, IT'S HARD TO SEE
THE COMPROMISE THAT WOULD LET
RUSSIA COMPETE.
CHRIS BROWN, CBC NEWS, MOSCOW.
>> Adrienne: IF THERE'S A
COMPROMISE, IT WILL BE THE
I.O.C. CHIEF WILL ANNOUNCE IT,
AWKWARD GIVEN HIS CLOSE RUSSIAN
TIES.
THE WORLD FIRST LEARNED ABOUT
RUSSIAN DOPING FROM THE
REPORTING OF THIS MAN, A GERMAN
JOURNALIST.
WE REACHED HIM IN SOUTH KOREA
AND HE SAID THAT THIS WILL BE
TRICKY.
>> Interview: MY FEELING IS THAT
THOMAS BACH WANTS TO AVOID
PUNISHMENT FOR RUSSIA.
IT'S OBVIOUS THAT HE HAS HAD A
TIGHT CONNECTION TO RUSSIA FOR
YEARS.
IF HE DOESN'T APPLY TOUGH
SANCTIONS AGAINST THIS COUNTRY,
THEN YOU HAVE LOST EVERYTHING
AND YOU LOSE EVERY CREDIBILITY.
AND IT GIVES OBVIOUSLY, THE
FEELING TO THE WORLDWIDE
AUDIENCE THAT THE COUNTRY IS
OBVIOUSLY ALLOWED TO DO
EVERYTHING.
>> Adrienne: THE I.O.C. WILL
DECIDE WHETHER OR NOT TO ALLOW
RUSSIA TO COMPETE IN
PYEONGCHANG.
IT'S WAITING ON RESULTS FROM TWO
COMMISSIONS.
ONE OF THEM IS RETESTING ALL THE
SAMPLES OF THE ATHLETES THAT
COMPETED IN SOCHI.
EVEN IF THE DOOR IS LEFT OPEN,
IT MAY NOT
NECESSARILY THE FINAL WORD.
EACH SPORT'S GOVERNING BODY
COULD DETERMINE ELIGIBILITY CASE
BY CASE BASED ON THE ATHLETES'
DOPING RECORDS.
>> Rosemary: BACK HERE AT HOME,
CAR SALES ARE A BIG ECONOMIC
INDICATOR AND THEY'VE BEEN
THROUGH THE ROOF IN RECENT
YEARS.
AS A CBC MARKETPLACE
INVESTIGATION HAS DISCOVERED,
SOME DEALERS USE QUESTION ADVICE
THAT COULD SEEP CANADIANS DEEP
INTO DEBT.
>> Reporter: WANT TO KNOW HOW
CAR DEALERS HAVE HIT RECORD
SALES IN CANADA?
IT BEGINS WITH PITCHES LIKE
THIS.
>> $112 BIWEEKLY, 0%, 7 YEARS.
>> Reporter: HALF OF ALL CAR
LOANS ARE SEVEN YEARS OR LONGER.
WE'RE ALSO BUYING MORE EXPENSIVE
CARS BECAUSE OF THE LOW
PAYMENTS.
>> THE AVERAGE CONSUMER SEES
THAT AND THEY THINK, I CAN
AFFORD THAT CAR, NO PROBLEM.
BUT IT'S JUST ANOTHER WAY OF
BRINGING CONSUMERS INTO THE
DEALERSHIP AND SELLING THEM
SOMETHING THAT THEY REALLY CAN'T
AFFORD.
>> Reporter: IN YOUR OPINION,
FOR THE AVERAGE PERSON, WHAT IS
THE BEST LENGTH OF TIME FOR A
CAR LOAN?
>> NO MORE THAN FIVE YEARS.
>> I WOULD SAY IDEALLY FOUR, BUT
STRETCH IT TO FIVE.
>> Reporter: SEVEN AND EIGHT?
>> NO.
>> Reporter: AND YET AT MOST
DEALERSHIPS, SURVEYED WITH
HIDDEN CAMERAS, THE CLEAR PUSH
WAS FOR LONG-TERM LOANS.
>> 84 MONTHS.
>> 7 YEARS?
>> 7 YEARS.
>> Reporter: WE SHOWED THAT
HIDDEN CAMERA TO ONTARIO'S AUTO
REGULATOR.
HE WAS NOT IMPRESSED.
>> THAT TO ME IS SHORTSIGHTED,
JUST A RECIPE FOR PROBLEMS.
>> Reporter: JOHN CARMICHAEL
SAYS THAT SALESPEOPLE SHOULD
EXPLAIN ALL THE LOAN OPTIONS AND
THE RISKS.
>> AND THAT'S THE CHALLENGE,
OBVIOUSLY, FOR A CONSUMER TO
MAKE A FULLY-INFORMED DECISION,
THEY NEED MORE INFORMATION THAN
THAT.
>> Reporter: PEOPLE CAN GET INTO
A TREADMILL OF DEBT.
TAKE CHANTAL MATTHEWS, WHO IS
LIKE THOUSANDS OF CANADIANS
SHE BOUGHT A CAR ON AN 8-YEAR
LOAN.
IT HAD MECHANICAL PROBLEMS FROM
THE START, SO SHE TRADED IT IN
EARLY, BUT THE TRADE-IN VALUE ON
THE CAR WAS LESS THAN THE DEBT
STILL OWING.
CHANTAL IS STILL PAYING THE DEBT
ON A CAR SHE NO LONGER OWNS.
IT'S BEEN COMBINED WITH THE LOAN
FOR HER NEW CAR.
>> WITH THE TWO CARS, $50,000.
>> Reporter: $50,000.
YOU SEEM VERY CALM ABOUT THAT?
>> I'VE ACCEPTED THE FACT THAT I
HAVE TO PAY IT.
I CAN'T GET OUT OF IT.
I HAVE TO PAY IT.
>> Reporter: CHANTAL IS NOT
ALONE.
1/4 OF CANADIAN TRADE-INS HAVE
BIGGER LOANS THAN THE CAR IS
WORTH.
AND THAT'S CALLED NEGATIVE
EQUITY.
>> Reporter: IT'S NOT GOOD.
>> IT'S NOT GOOD AND IT COSTS
YOU AND COSTS YOU BIG TIME.
>> Reporter: SALESPEOPLE SHOULD
SPELL OUT THE RISKS INVOLVED
WITH NEGATIVE EQUITY AND
TRADE-INS, ESPECIALLY ON THE
LONG-TERM LOANS.
IN OUR HIDDEN CAMERA TEST, THAT
RARELY HAPPENED.
>> WE CAN TRADE IN YOUR VEHICLE
AT ANY TIME AND UPGRADE YOU TO
ANY OTHER CAR.
YOU ARE NOT LOSING IN ANY WAY.
>> YOU WILL LOSE YOUR SHIRT.
IT'S CRAZY.
>> Reporter: THIS IS ALL ABOUT
NEGATIVE EQUITY.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> Reporter: IN THREE OR FOUR
YEARS, YOU OWE MORE THAN THE
CAR'S WORTH.
>> A LOT MORE.
>> YOU CAN TRADE IT IN AND WE
PAY OFF YOUR LOAN AND YOU GET
UNTO THE NEW CAR.
>> YOU PAY OFF THE LOAN?
>> WE DO, YES.
>> THAT'S TROUBLING.
NOBODY PAYS OFF LOAN.
HOW DO YOU PAY IT OFF?
YOU DON'T JUST PAY OFF THE LOAN.
>> Reporter: IF CANADIANS DON'T
UNDERSTAND THAT, THEY COULD FIND
THEMSELVES DROWNING IN DEBT.
>> Rosemary: THAT'S JUST
TERRIBLE.
IF YOU WANT TO SEE THE FULL
MARKETPLACE INVESTIGATION ON HOW
NOT TO BUY A CAR, CLEARLY, TUNE
IN TOMORROW AT 8:00 ON CBC
TELEVISION, OR
CBC.CA/MARKETPLACE.
THE "AT ISSUE" PANEL IS NEXT.
WE'LL ASK IF CANADA'S NEW
PEACEKEEPING COMMITMENT REALLY
ENOUGH?
>> Andrew: AND HOW A DAIRY
FARMER FOUND A SIMPLE FIX TO A
GLOBAL PROBLEM.
>> IT'S NOT A GREAT, BIG,
MULTIMILLION DOLLAR BUSINESS,
BUT IT'S A REAL BUSINESS.
AND YOU'RE HELPING THE COW AND
YOU'RE HELPING PEOPLE AND
HELPING THE ENVIRONMENT AT THE
SAME TIME.
SO YOU ARE DOING A
>> Prime Minister Justin
Trudeau: TIMES HAVE CHANGED.
NOW ALL TOO OFTEN, THERE IS NO
PEACE TO KEEP.
THE CONFLICTS WE FACE TODAY ARE
INTRACTABLE, MORE DANGEROUS,
MORE COMPLEX.
MODERN PEACE OPERATIONS TAKE
PLACE IN A CONTEXT THAT
TRANSCENDS BORDERS AND INCLUDES
A CHALLENGING RANGE OF ACTORS.
>> Rosemary: THAT'S JUSTIN
TRUDEAU BACK ON WEDNESDAY
ANNOUNCING HIS PLAN FOR CANADA'S
PEACEKEEPING COMMITMENT, LATER
AND LIGHTER THAN FIRST PROMISED.
EVEN THOUGH THE HOUSE OF COMMONS
ISN'T SITTING, "AT ISSUE" IS.
ANDREW, CHANTAL AND ALTHIA, GOOD
TO SEE, EVERYONE.
CHANTAL, IS THIS WHAT THE
LIBERALS TELEGRAPHED?
IS THIS THE RIGHT CALL?
>> Interview: TWO DIFFERENT
THINGS.
NO, IT DOESN'T ADD UP TO WHAT
WHAT WAS IN THEIR PLATFORM.
YES, THINGS ARE CHANGING, BUT
THEY WERE CHANGING WHEN CHRETIEN
WAS PRIME MINISTER.
AND CONFLICT OF CIVIL WAR
ERUPTED IN YUGOSLAVIA.
SO WHEN THAT PLATFORM WAS
DRAFTED, THE TIMES, THEY HAD
ALREADY CHANGED.
THE PEACEKEEPING HAD BECOME
PEACE MAKING.
IS THAT THE RIGHT CALL?
THAT'S A DIFFERENT ISSUE.
POSSIBLY.
POLITICALLY, DESPITE THE HEAT
THE GOVERNMENT GETS THIS WEEK,
IT'S PROBABLY THE EASIER CALL IN
THE SENSE THAT BEYOND THE
DIFFICULTIES AND THE DANGER,
THIS NOTION HAS SET IN THAT THE
PRIME MINISTER WANTED A SEAT ON
THE U.N. SECURITY COUNCIL AND
THERE WAS A DANGER THAT IF HE
DID SIGN THE PEACE MAKING,
PEACEKEEPING MISSION, THAT THE
SPIN WOULD HAVE BEEN THAT HE WAS
PUTTING YOUNG SOLDIERS IN HARMS'
WAY TO BUY A SEAT AT THE
SECURITY COUNCIL.
>> Rosemary: INTERESTING.
I SAW IT THE OTHER WAY.
I WONDERED WHETHER THE
ANNOUNCEMENT WOULD HURT THAT
BID.
I SEE CHANTAL'S POINT.
>> Interview: MAYBE IT'S A
REASON THAT YOU DON'T WANT TO BE
OVERT IN ANNOUNCING YOUR
INTENTIONS, BECAUSE YOU WILL BE
SECOND-GUESSED.
AS YOU WILL BE ON THIS.
THEY KNEW THAT TIMES HAD CHANGED
IN OCTOBER, 2015.
OR THEY DIDN'T KNOW AND SHOULD
HAVE.
AND ONLY HAVE LEARNED THIS IN
THE LAST TWO YEARS IN OFFICE.
EITHER WAY, DOESN'T LOOK REALLY
GOOD ON THEM.
IT WILL BE INTERESTING TO SEE
HOW OUR INTERNATIONAL PARTNERS
REACT TO THIS.
TOSS TRUE TO SAY THAT THERE IS
OTHER WAYS TO CONTRIBUTE BESIDES
JUST PUTTING BOOTS ON THE
GROUND.
IT'S LIKE THE COMBAT MISSION
AGAINST ISIS QUESTION.
WHY DOES IT NECESSARILY HAVE TO
BE A CHOICE BETWEEN THE TWO?
WHEN IT COMES DOWN TO IT, THE
CURRENCY OF THE THINGS IN TERMS
OF RESPECT FROM OTHER COUNTRIES
IS, ARE YOU WILLING TO PUT YOUR
OWN SOLDIERS' LIVES ON THE LINE?
IT'S A LITTLE EASY AND CHEAP TO
SAY, WE'LL THROW MONEY AT IT,
BUT WE'RE NOT GOING TO TAKE THE
RISKS.
>> Rosemary: THE RISK TO THE
PRIME MINISTER'S POINT, ALTHIA,
IS MUCH, MUCH HIGHER
THAT'S THE FACTS.
>> Interview: AND THAT'S CLEARLY
WHAT THEY'VE SPENT THE LAST YEAR
AND A HALF TRYING TO DECIDE.
THEY MADE THE COMMITMENT ABOUT
600 CANADIAN TROOPS GOING
SOMEWHERE.
150 POLICE OFFICERS.
$450 MILLION.
THEY SPENT SO MUCH TIME
REVIEWING IT.
I THINK THEY WENT TO AFRICA
THREE TIMES.
AND THEN THEY CLEARLY DECIDED IT
WASN'T WORTH THE RISK AND THEN
THEY COME UP WITH A STRATEGY
WHERE THEY APPEAR TO DO A LOT,
BUT THEN IT'S NOT THAT MUCH WHEN
YOU LOOK AT IT.
I DON'T THINK THE DISCUSSION,
ALTHOUGH THAT'S WHAT THE PRIME
MINISTER SAID IN THIS SPEECH
THIS WEEK, IS PEACEKEEPING
BECOMING PEACEMAKING
WE'VE KNOWN THAT FOR DECADES.
THE DISCUSSION THAT HAPPENED IN
THE LAST YEAR AND A HALF IS THAT
WE HAVE A VERY DIFFERENT FOREIGN
AFFAIRS MINISTER.
HE WAS A MAN THAT BELIEVED IN A
PERSONIAN IMAGE OF CANADA AND
BLUE BONNETS AND HAD A ROMANTIC
NOTION OF PEACEKEEPING.
AND NOW THE CONCERN IS DONALD
TRUMP AND I THINK THAT HAD A LOT
TO DO WITH THE ANNOUNCEMENT.
>> Interview: I AGREE, BUT IF
THEY'RE NOT LISTENING ABOUT WHAT
WAS SAID AROUND THE CABINET
TABLE WHEN JEAN CHRETIEN WAS
PRIME MINISTER.
THESE ISSUES CAME UP AND
RELUCTANCE TO ENGAGE IN THE
PEACEMAKING, PEACEKEEPING
MISSIONS DIDN'T START WITH
STEPHEN HARPER.
WE HAD STARTED TO WITHDRAW
BEFORE THAT.
>> Interview: AND THEY DIDN'T
WRITE THE PLATFORM.
IT SERVED THE SAME AS ELLE --
ELECTORAL REFORM PLEDGE.
IT WAS APPEALING TO THAT
ANTI-HARPER SENTIMENT, FEELING
LIKE WE NEEDED TO CHANGE COURSE.
THEY WERE CONTENT TO REAP THE
REWARDS OF THIS.
>> Rosemary: I WANT TO SAVE SOME
TIME FOR SOMETHING THAT ANDREW
-- IF YOU FOLLOW ANDREW ON
TWITTER, HE HAD MUCH TO SAY
ABOUT IT, BUT I WILL START WITH
ALTHIA.
I WILL MAKE HIM WAIT A MOMENT.
THIS MANDATE LETTER-TRACKER THAT
THE GOVERNMENT PUT OUT WHERE
CANADIANS CAN GO AND SAY, HEY,
HOW ARE YOU DOING ON YOUR
PROMISES?
IS THIS NORMAL FOR GOVERNMENTS
>> DON'T ALL GOVERNMENTS TRY TO
GRADE THEMSELVES?
THERE WAS A LOT MADE ABOUT
GOVERNMENTS NOT BEING OBJECTIVE.
I DON'T KNOW IF THAT'S THE
POINT.
HOW EFFECTIVE IS THIS?
>> Interview: GOVERNMENTS TEND
TO DO THIS INTERNALLY.
THEY DON'T TEND TO DO IT
PUBLICLY.
BECAUSE THEY MADE IT PUBLIC,
IT'S BECOME A DIFFERENT VERSION
OF GOVERNMENT SPIN.
SO THINGS IF THEY WERE REALLY
BEING CANDID AND HONEST, THE
BUDGET BEING BALANCED BY
2019-2020, THEY WOULDN'T PUT IT
IN THE LISTING OF UNDER WAY WITH
CHALLENGES.
THEY WOULD ACKNOWLEDGE THAT IT'S
A BROKEN COMMITMENT AND THEY
WOULD PUT IT IN GOVERNMENT-SPEAK
OF, NOT BEING PURSUED.
THEY'RE NOT BEING FRANK.
I THINK THERE'S A NUMBER OF
RISKS WITH THIS.
AT THE SAME TIME, IT'S PROBABLY
A LAUDABLE GOAL.
IT GIVES YOU AN INDICATION OF
WHAT THE GOVERNMENT THINKS OF
ITS OWN ACCOMPLISHMENTS.
IF YOU LOOK AT IT AS A
PROMISE-TRACKER, IT IS NOT THAT.
AND COMMITMENTS THAT YOU CARE
ABOUT, WHETHER IT'S ACCESS TO
INFORMATION LEGISLATION, LIKE A
LOT OF JOURNALISTS DO, THE
GOVERNMENT HAS TAKEN A ROSY
APPROACH TO LOOKING AT THEIR
REPORT.
>> Rosemary: WAY TO WORK IN MY
NAME.
OK, COYNE.
OFF YOU GO.
>> Interview: IT'S INTOLERABLE
TO PUT OUT A DOCUMENT FOR
ACCOUNTABLE AND THEN SPIN.
IF YOU REALLY WANT
ACCOUNTABILITY, YOU WOULD HAVE A
THIRD PARTY LOOK.
YOU WOULD MAKE IT CLEAR THEY HAD
AN ABSOLUTE UNVARNISHED MANDATE
TO SAY WHATEVER THEY NEEDED TO
SAY ABOUT IT.
THE MODEL WOULD BE THE AUDITOR
GENERAL, FOR EXAMPLE, LOOKING
INTO THE GOVERNMENT'S BOOKS.
BUT THEY DIDN'T DO THAT.
THEY PUT THIS THING OUT THAT
IMMEDIATELY, FRANKLY, BECAME A
LAUGHINGSTOCK.
>> Rosemary: THEY WILL PUT
SOMETHING OUT IN TWO WEEKS,
CHANTAL, WHERE IT WILL BE MORE
DETAILED.
WILL BE ABLE TO SEE HOW MANY
ROADS THEY BUILT, HOW MANY
RESERVES HAVE DRINKING WATER.
IT WILL BE MORE PRACTICAL WITH
THAT.
WILL THAT HELP?
>> Interview: YES AND NO.
I FIND IT VERY USEFUL BECAUSE IT
TELLS YOU A LOT ABOUT THE
MIND-SET OF THE GOVERNMENT, THE
KIND OF LENGTHS THEY'RE WILLING
TO GO.
LANGUAGEWISE, IT'S ALMOST "1984"
AND  ORSON WELLS AND THE WAY THE
LANGUAGE IS COUCHED.
WE WERE GIVEN ACCESS TO THE
MANDATE LETTERS, THE MISSION
STATEMENT FOR EVERY DEPARTMENT.
THAT WASN'T FAKE AND IT'S REALLY
USEFUL.
BUT THEN NOT TO DATE MYSELF, BUT
REMEMBER CHRETIEN AND THE RED
BOOK, HE NEVER SAID HE WOULD DO
ANYTHING ABOUT THE G.S.T., DID
HE?
[LAUGHTER]
SO WE DIDN'T REINVENT THE WHEEL
THIS WEEK.
>> Rosemary: NO.
AND PART OF THE PROBLEM IS, THEY
WERE WRITING IT OFF THE MANDATE
LETTERS AND NOT THE PLATFORM,
AND THERE ARE DISCREPANCIES
BETWEEN THE TWO.
>> Interview: YES, EXACTLY, LIKE
DOOR-TO-DOOR MAIL DELIVERY.
IT WAS A VERBAL PLEDGE.
IN THE PLATFORM DOCUMENT, IT
SAYS "LAUNCH REVIEW TO MAKE SURE
THAT CANADIANS GET GOOD SERVICE
AT A GOOD PRICE."
THAT'S NOT WHAT THEY TOLD
CANADIANS.
>> Rosemary: ANDREW AND CHANTAL,
LAST WORD.
>> Interview: THEY COULDN'T
BRING THEMSELVES TO SAY BROKEN
PROMISE.
YOU WONDER IF IT'S AS CYNICAL
AND OVERT OR HAVE THEY LOST
REALITY.
ONCE THEY SPEAK A LANGUAGE OF
EUPHEMISM, IT'S EASY TO FALL
INTO IT AND NOT KNOW YOU ARE
DOING IT.
>> Interview: YOU DIDN'T KNOW
THEY WERE TESTING WEED, EH?
[LAUGHTER]
>> Interview: JUST TRYING TO BE
FAIR.
>> Rosemary: ALL RIGHT,
EVERYBODY.
THANK YOU.
SEE YOU AGAIN NEXT WEEK.
>> Interview: THANK YOU.
>> Andrew: WHEN WE COME BACK, I
WILL TAKE YOU TO THE SHORES OF
PRINCE EDWARD ISLAND, WHERE AN
UNLIKELY ANSWER TO CLIMATE
CHANGE WASHES UP ON THE BEACH
ALL THE TIME.
WHAT DID YOU CALL IT?
>> THERE'S A LATIN NAME, BUT
IT'S ALL -- I DON'T KNOW.
WE CALL IT FOO-FOO.
>> YOU WILL SEE FOR THE FIRST
TIME IN THE LAST THREE YEARS,
THE EMISSIONS OF GREENHOUSE
GASES RISING AGAIN.
>> Andrew: THAT'S THE U.N.
SECRETARY GENERAL SPEAKING AT A
CLIMATE CONFERENCE IN BONN,
GERMANY, THIS WEEK.
HE'S URGING WORLD LEADERS TO DO
MORE TO FIGHT CLIMATE CHANGE.
WHERE TO START?
THIS WILL SURPRISE YOU.
HERE'S ALL THE GREENHOUSE GAS
EMISSIONS ON THE PLANET CAUSED
BY HUMAN ACTIVITY, BROKEN DOWN
BY SECTOR.
YOU CAN SEEING A CULTURE AND
FORESTRY AMONG THE BIGGEST
POLLUTERS.
DRILL DOWN A LITTLE DEEPER AND
GET THIS -- COWS ALONE HAVE 10%
OF ALL EMISSIONS AND IT'S THE
METHANE THAT THEY LITERALLY BURP
OUT.
THERE ARE 1.5 BILLION COWS.
SO IT'S SOMETHING THAT SCIENCE
AND RESEARCHERS HAVE DEVOTED A
LOT OF MONEY AND TIME EXPLORING.
THE FIX MAY HAVE BEEN RIGHT
UNDER OUR NOSES ALL THE TIME.
>> SO WE JUST WALK AROUND AND
SHAKE IT IN THE GROUND.
>> Andrew: SO IT'S SPRINKLING ON
TOP OF THE FEED.
KEN'S DAIRY COWS
ARE EATING SOMETHING THAT MOST
COWS NEVER SEE IN THEIR
LIFETIME, BUT WITH EVERY LICK,
THEY'RE HELPING THE ENVIRONMENT.
IT'S A BIT OF A WEIRD IDEA.
>> FOR SURE.
WE SAID, WE'LL GIVE IT A TRY, NO
HARM.
AND WE HAVE SEEN A DIFFERENCE
AND LIKE THE IDEA.
>> Andrew: SO HERE THEY ARE,
COWS ON THE CUSP OF SOMETHING
BIG.
THEY DON'T LOOK DIFFERENT FROM
YOUR AVERAGE, RUN-OF-THE-MILL
DAIRY COW, BUT IT'S WHAT IS
GOING ON ON THE INSIDE THAT IS
CAPTURING ATTENTION.
A LOT OF METHANE COMES OUT OF A
COW'S MOUTH, AND SOME THE OTHER
END, BUT THESE COWS HAVE MANAGED
TO REDUCE THEIR METHANE
EMISSIONS BY 20%.
>> THEY'RE EATING SEAWEED.
>> Andrew: DO THEY LIKE IT?
>> THEY LOVE IT.
IT'S SALTY.
THAT'S PROBABLY WHY THEY LIKE TO
EAT IT.
>> THERE'S OUR FOO-FOO.
THAT'S OUR ROCK WEED.
>> Andrew: THIS IS JOE DORGAN.
HE USED TO MILK COWS FOR A
LIVING.
>> Andrew: WHAT DID YOU CALL IT?
FOO-FOO?
>> YEAH.
THAT'S A REAL NAME FOR IT AND A
LATIN NAME.
WE CALL IT FOO-FOO.
>> Andrew: THE WAY THE STORY
GOES, MANY YEARS AGO, JOE WAS
LOOKING FOR NEW, ORGANIC WAYS TO
FEED HIS COWS.
HE ADMITS CUTTING METHANE
EMISSIONS WAS NOT EXACTLY TOP OF
MIND.
HOW DID YOU EVEN GET THE IDEA
THAT IF YOU FED SEAWEED TO COWS,
MAYBE IT WOULD DO THEM SOME
GOOD?
>> I ALWAYS KNEW IT WAS GOOD.
OLD PEOPLE USED IT FOR
FERTILIZER AND MINERALS FOR
THEIR ANIMALS YEARS AND YEARS
AGO.
SO WHEN I CHANGED MY DAIRY HERD
TO ORGANIC, I WANTED A SOURCE OF
MINERAL.
SO I SAID, LET'S USE WHAT WE
GOT.
>> Andrew: WALK ME THROUGH THE
PROCESS OF HOW YOU TURN THE RAW
PRODUCTS --
>> THIS IS THE RAW PRODUCT.
PUT IT IN HERE, UP THE CONVEYOR
BELT AND INTO THE SYSTEM AND
TAKES OUT THE ROCKS AND THE
SAND.
AND THEN IT COMES DOWN INTO THE
TUBS.
IT GOES THROUGH THE PROCESSOR
HERE AND THEN THE HAMMER MILL.
IT DOES ALL THE CHOPPING.
>> Andrew: SO IT BREAKS UP THE
CHUNKS OF SEAWEED?
>> YES.
>> Andrew: THAT'S WHAT I WAS
SEEING HERE.
>> THAT'S THE FINISHED PRODUCT.
>> Andrew: ALMOST LIKE A POWDER?
>> YES.
IT'S FINDING A SOLUTION TO A
PROBLEM WE DIDN'T CREATE.
IT MAKES YOU FEEL GOOD, BECAUSE
THERE'S A LOT OF TALK ABOUT
GREENHOUSE GASES AND, YOU KNOW,
COWS ARE GETTING BLAMED AND EVEN
THOUGH THEY'VE BEEN AROUND FOR
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF YEARS AND
IT'S NOT REALLY THEIR FAULT, IF
WE CAN HELP WITH THIS PROBLEM,
IT'S GREAT.
>> Andrew: I WONDER, CAN YOU
MAKE MONEY FROM IT, TOO?
>> WE HOPE DOWN THE ROAD WE CAN
SELL SOME CARBON CREDITS, BUT
IT'S NOT WHY WE'RE DOING IT.
WE STARTED DOING IT TO IMPROVE
COW HEALTH.
ANYTHING ELSE THAT COMES ALONG
IS A BONUS.
>> Andrew: COULD IT BE
LUCRATIVE?
>> IT COULD BE, BECAUSE METHANE
IS, YOU KNOW, QUITE MORE POTENT
THAN CARBON FROM THE CARS.
SO, YEAH, IT'S GOT POSSIBILITIES
TO BE AN INCOME.
>> Andrew: BACK IN JOE'S CORNER
OF THE ISLAND, HE, TOO, SEES THE
FINANCIAL BENEFIT OF THIS FIX.
HE JUST NEEDS MORE FARMERS TO
TAKE NOTICE.
>> IT'S A BUSINESS NOW.
IT'S NOT A GREAT BIG,
MULTIMILLION DOLLAR BUSINESS,
BUT IT'S A REAL BUSINESS
AND YOU'RE HELPING THE COW,
HELPING PEOPLE AND HELPING THE
ENVIRONMENT AT THE SAME TIME.
SO YOU ARE DOING A GOOD THING.
>> Andrew: JOE TALKS ABOUT
HELPING THE COW AND THIS IS WHAT
HE WAS INTERESTED IN ALL ALONG.
HIS COWS SEEM TO GIVE MORE MILK,
HAVE STRONGER REPRODUCTIVE
CYCLES
EVEN THEIR OFFSPRING WERE
HEALTHIER.
A LOT OF THAT HAS BEEN BACKED UP
BY SCIENCE, BELIEVE IT OR NOT,
BECAUSE METHANE IS EFFECTIVELY
WASTED ENERGY.
LESS METHANE IS A GOOD THING.
FROM HERE, THE STORY ACTUALLY
GETS REALLY EXCITING.
JOE'S DISCOVERY IS TINY COMPARED
TO WHAT MIGHT BE COMING NEXT.
THE SAME RESEARCHER WHO TESTED
JOE'S COWS PROVING THEY WERE
EMITTING LESS METHANE WENT ON A
WORLDWIDE SEARCH FOR A BETTER
SEAWEED THAT MAY PRODUCE METHANE
EMISSIONS EVEN MORE.
AND HE FOUND ONE, ALL THE WAY IN
AUSTRALIA.
ASPARAGOPSIS TAXIFORMIS IS THE
NAME OF THAT SEAWEED.
ONLY GROWS IN WARMER WATERS, BUT
LISTEN IT HIM DESCRIBE WHAT
HAPPENED WHEN HE TESTED THE
STUFF IN THE LAB AND GOT A
METHANE FLAT LINE.
>> SO I REDID THE EXPERIMENT AND
GOT THE SAME RESULT AGAIN.
I WAS EVEN DOUBTFUL THE SECOND
TIME BECAUSE I WAS SEEING NO
METHANE AT ALL.
IT WAS A COMPLETE INHIBITION OR
AT LEAST BELOW DETECTION, WHICH
IS SO LOW YOU MAY AS WELL SAY
IT'S GONE BECAUSE I CAN MEASURE
99.99% OF A REDUCTION.
>> Andrew: SO ELIMINATING
METHANE ALTOGETHER, THAT WOULD
BE SOMETHING.
ROB KINLEY HAS SINCE BEEN
TESTING THE SEAWEED IN LIVE
ANIMALS AND IS PLANNING TO
RELEASE THE DATA IN THE NEW
YEAR.
HE'S ALREADY TELLING US THAT THE
FINDINGS ARE BETTER THAN EVEN HE
COULD HAVE EXPECTED.
SO WE'LL WAIT FOR THOSE.
HE THINKS IT WILL TURN THE
INDUSTRY ON ITS HEAD.
>> Adrienne: REMEMBER, YOU CAN
GO
DEEPER ON THE STORIES OF THE DAY
EARLIER IN THE DAY.
SUBSCRIBE TO OUR NEWSLETTER AT
cbc.ca/thenational.
TAKES YOU INSIDE OUR JOURNALISM
EVERY AFTERNOON.
>> Andrew: ON "THE NATIONAL"
TONIGHT,
QUESTIONS FOR TRANSCANADA HAVE
THE AN OIL SPILL IN THE KEYSTONE
PIPELINE IN SOUTH DAKOTA.
BY THE TIME IT WAS DETECTED THIS
MORNING, 5,000 BARRELS OF OIL
HAD LEAKED.
THE TIMING SETS UP A FEW TENSE
DAYS FOR TRANSCANADA.
NEXT WEEK, IT'S EXPECTING
NEBRASKA TO DECIDE IF THEY WILL
ALLOW THE XL PIPELINE THROUGH
THE STATE.
WE'RE WAITING TO SEE WHAT
HAPPENS NEXT AFTER ONTARIO'S
PREMIER STEPS IN TO TRY TO BRING
A COLLEGE-WIDE STRIKE TO AN END.
THE STRIKE HAS SHUT 500,000
COLLEGE STUDENTS OUT OF COLLEGE
CLASSROOMS FOR NEARLY FIVE
WEEKS.
TODAY UNION MEMBERS REJECTED THE
LATEST OFFER AND TALKS BROKE
DOWN.
THAT PROMPTED PREMIER KATHLEEN
WYNNE TO STEP IN.
>> WE NEED THOSE YOUNG PEOPLE
BACK IN CLASS IMMEDIATELY.
I WOULD VERY MUCH LIKE TO SEE
STUDENTS BACK IN WEEK NEXT WEEK.
SO I MEAN IMMEDIATELY.
>> Andrew: HER GOVERNMENT
ANNOUNCED PLANS TO TABLE
LEGISLATION SOON TO SEND THEM
BACK TO WORK.
THE PROVINCIAL N.D.P. BLOCKED AN
ATTEMPT TODAY, BUT THE LIBERALS
SAY
WITH THE
CONSERVATIVES' SUPPORT THEY HOPE
TO TABLE THAT LEGISLATION
TOMORROW AFTERNOON.
QUITE AN ENTRANCE.
HERE'S A CULMINATION OF WHAT HAS
BEEN A LOT OF HYPE FOR A TRUCK.
THAT'S ELON MUSK WITH TONIGHT'S
BIG UNVEIL -- A BRAND IF YOU
ELECTRIC SEMITRUCK.
ACCORDING TO MUSK, IT CAN GO 800
KILOMETRES ON ONE CHARGE AT MAX
WEIGHT AND SPEED AND IT
APPARENTLY WILL ONLY TAKE LONG
TO CHARGE.
30 MINUTES FOR 600-KILOMETRES OF
RANGE.
HERE'S THE BIG SURPRISE
ANNOUNCEMENT, THE TESLA
ROADSTER.
HE SAYS IT GOES FROM 0 TO 100
KILL MEETERS AN HOUR IN 1.9
SECONDS AND CAN TRAVEL UP TO
1,000 KILOMETRES OPENING ONE
CHARGE.
MUSK SAID IT WILL BE ON THE
MARKET BY 2020.
WITH THAT STORY, WE'LL LEAVE
THINGS TONIGHT.
THAT'S "THE NATIONAL" FOR
NOVEMBER 16.
THANKS FOR JOINING US.
>> Adrienne: GOOD NIGHT.
>> Rosemary: GOOD NIGHT.