>> IT IS NOVEMBER THE 8th.
THIS IS "THE NATIONAL."
DESPERATE PEOPLE THE WORLD OVER
SEEK CANADA AS A SAFE HAVEN WITH
DOORS EASY TO OPEN.
WE BEGIN WITH TWO STORIES THAT
SHOW HOW WRONG MANY OF THEM MAY
BE.
TONIGHT, THE TRUDEAU GOVERNMENT
IS BRACING FOR AN INFLUX OF
PEOPLE CROSSING INTO CANADA FROM
THE UNITED STATES.
ALL BECAUSE OF CHANGES TO
IMMIGRATION RULES ANNOUNCED THIS
WEEK.
SOUTH OF THE BORDER.
CBC'S DAVID COCHRANE IS IN
OTTAWA.
SO, DAVID, IF WE ACCEPT FOR A
MOMENT THAT AN INFLUX IS
POSSIBLE, WHAT IS THE TRUDEAU
GOVERNMENT'S PLAN?
>> Reporter: ADRIENNE, THE
APPROACH SO FAR HAS BEEN SIMILAR
TO WHAT THEY HAVE DONE ON NAFTA.
WITH A FIRM, TARGETED AUDIENCE.
WE SAW POLITICIANS GOING ACROSS
THE UNITED STATES ON NAFTA WITH
A SPECIFIC MESSAGE ON TRADE.
THIS TIME, WE ARE SEEING TEAMS
OF DIPLOMATS AND POLITICIANS
GOING ACROSS THE UNITED STATES
WITH A VERY SPECIFIC MESSAGE ON
IMMIGRATION.
THE EMBASSY IN WASHINGTON, 11
CONSULATES AND A WAVE OF M.P.S
SPANNING ACROSS THE UNITED
STATES.
THE TARGET AUDIENCE IS A 300,000
PEOPLE LIVING IN THE U.S. UNDER
TEMPORARY PROTECTED STATUS THAT
SHIELDS THEM FROM DEPORTATION.
THE KEY WORD HERE IS TEMPORARY.
MOST ARE FROM LATIN AMERICA AND
HAITI.
DEPENDING ON THE COUNTRY, THAT
PROTECTION IS SET TO EXPIRE IN
WEEKS OR MONTHS AND THE FEAR IS
THEY COULD FLEE TRUMP'S AMERICA
FOR TRUDEAU CANADA.
IT IS ALL AN ATTEMPT TO AVOID
ANOTHER SURGE LIKE WE SAW THIS
SUMMER IN QUEBEC.
THAT WAVE WAS MOSTLY HAITIANS,
MANY OF THEM DRAWN BY FALSE
INFORMATION SPREAD ON CERTAINLY
MEDIA TELLING THEM THAT CANADA
WOULD ACCEPT THEM WITH OPEN
ARMS.
SINCE THEN, THE GOVERNMENT HAS
SHARPENED OUT THE MESSAGES.
IN MULTIPLE LANGUAGES.
AN EFFORT TO COUNTER INFORMATION
THAT CONTINUES AND EVOLVES.
>> OUR CONSULATE HAVE HAD
INSTANCES WHERE THEY HAVE SEEN
THE INFORMATION.
IN MEDIA OUTLETS AND HAVE
PRO-ACTIVELY REACHED OUT TO THE
EDITORS AND THE REPORTERS AND
SAID, THIS IS NOT TRUE.
>> Reporter: THEY ARE IN THE AGE
EVER DONALD TRUMP, IRONICALLY
ONE OF THE PROBLEMS IS FAKE
NEWS.
THE IMMIGRATION MINISTER TOLD US
ABOUT A SPANISH NEWSPAPER THAT
REPORTED WITH PEOPLE WITH
TEMPORARY PROTECTIVE STATUS IN
THE U.S., THEY WOULD BE GRANTED
ASYLUM STATUS IF THEY CAME TO
CANADA.
IT IS NOT TRUE.
THEY DISPATCHED A DIPLOMAT AND
GET A CORRECTION AND A FOLLOW-UP
STORY AND DRIVE HOME THE KEY
POINT THAT COMING TO CANADA IS
NOT A FREE TICKET TO STAYING IN
CANADA.
>> Adrienne: I GUESS THE BOTTOM
LINE IS DO YOU THINK ALL OF THIS
HARD WORK, THE STRATEGY IS GOING
TO WORK?
>> Reporter: THEY SURE HOPE SO
AND THEY HAD SOME SUCCESS WITH A
SIMILAR STRATEGY AND SLOWING
DOWN THE WAVES OF MIGRANTS AT
ROXON ROAD AND PUTTING UP SIGNS
AND MORE ACTIVE ON SOCIAL MEDIA
AND REACHING OUT TO THE HAITIAN
COMMUNITY ON THE ROXON ROAD
ISSUE.
A SENSE OF THE IMPACT, 250
PEOPLE A DAY COMING FROM NEW
YORK TO QUEBEC.
THAT IS DOWN TO 50 OR 60 PEOPLE
A DAY.
AT THE PEAK, 2 AND 3 WERE
HAITIANS AND NOW 1 IN 5.
IT SLOWED.
IT HAS NOT STOPPED.
THEY DON'T EXPECT IT TO STOP
THROUGH THE WINTER.
THEY SET UP A TENT CITY TO DEAL
WITH THE WAVE OF MIGRANTS OVER
THE SUMMER.
THEY ARE BRINGING IN HEATED
TRAILERS BECAUSE IF THE WEATHER
TURNS COLD, A TENT WILL NOT CUT
IT.
THE PEOPLE WILL KEEP COMING.
>> Adrienne: THANK YOU.
WE WILL SEE WHAT HAPPENS.
>>> THE NUMBER OF ASYLUM SEEKERS
WANTING TO CALL CANADA HOME HAS
SOARED THIS YEAR.
15,000 PEOPLE CROSSED INTO THE
COUNTRY ILLEGALLY.
SO FAR IN 2017.
ALL OF LAST YEAR, THERE WERE
FEWER THAN 2500.
>>> A LOT OF ASYLUM SEEKERS COME
FROM NIGERIA.
MANY CLAIMING SEXUAL ORIENTATION
AS THE BASIS OF THE FEAR.
CBC NEWS HAS LEARNED THAT LEGAL
AID OFFICIALS HAVE SEEN SO MANY
SIMILARITIES IN SO MANY CASES,
THEY ARE WORRIED SOME MAY BE
MADE UP.
TONIGHT, THE SENIOR
INVESTIGATIVE CORRESPONDENT
DIANA SWAIN LOOKS INTO THE
QUESTIONABLE CLAIMS.
>> Reporter: EVERY YEAR,
THOUSANDS OF ASYLUM SEEKERS
STREAM THROUGH THE PEARSON
INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT.
INCREASINGLY THOSE SEEKING
REFUGE IN CANADA ARE NIGERIAN.
THEY MAKE UP THE SECOND LARGEST
GROUP.
WITH AN UNIQUE DIFFERENCE.
ACCORDING TO LEGAL AID ONTARIO,
303 CLAIM SEXUAL ORIENTATION AS
THE REASON.
A LARGE PROPORTION SAYING THEY
ARE BISEXUAL AND THE DETAILS OF
THE PERSONAL STORY ARE SIMILAR.
THAT IS A PROBLEM FOR LEGAL AID
ONTARIO THAT IS CAPPED TO PAY
THE LEGAL COSTS AND WORRY THE
APPLICANTS ARE FABRICATING
STORIES THEMSELVES OR COACHED TO
LIE.
>> THERE ARE CERTAIN PATTERNS
WHEN YOU LOOK AT THEM OVER, YOU
KNOW, 40, 50, 60 TIMES YOU
WONDER ABOUT THE CORRECTNESS AND
CONSIDER THE CLAIMS MAY BE
FABRICATED.
>> Reporter: THERE IS NO
QUESTION NIGERIA IS AN
INCREASINGLY HOSTILE PLACE FOR
THOSE IN THE LBGT COMMUNITY.
PASSING A LAW THAT EFFECTIVELY
CRIMINALIZES SAME SEX
RELATIONSHIPS.
THE TORONTO LAWYER SAID HE
BELIEVES THAT IS THE REASON FOR
THE SPIKE IN APPLICATIONS.
HE SAID HE TURNED AWAY SOME
PEOPLE WHOSE STORY SEEM
SUSPICIOUS.
HE SAID THAT CAN BE TRICKY.
GIVEN THE NATURE OF THE CLAIM.
>> Interview: HOW DO YOU TEST
SOMEONE'S SEXUAL ORIENTATION.
WE CANNOT GO THERE.
THAT IS DISCRIMINATORY.
>> Reporter: THE APPLICANTS WHO
MAY BE LYING WITH SEXUAL
ORIENTATION THINKING IT IS TOO
HARD A CLAIM TO DISPROVE ARE
LIKELY FINDING OTHERWISE.
INCREASINGLY THE IMMIGRATION AND
REFUGEE BOARD IS TURNING THEM
DOWN.
ONLY HALF HAVE BEEN ACCEPTED
THIS YEAR.
THE SENIOR INVESTIGATIVE
CORRESPONDENT DIANA SWAIN IS
HERE.
CAN YOU WALK US THROUGH WHAT
LEGAL AID IS DOING ABOUT IT?
>> WE KNOW THEY SENT LETTERS TO
FIVE LAWYERS IN ONTARIO.
THEY WON'T DISCLOSE WHO.
THEY HANDLED A HIGH VOLUME OF
NIGERIAN REFUGEE CASES.
LEGAL AID IS ASKING IF THEY CAN
SHED LIGHT ON WHY SO MANY OF THE
CASES ARE SO SIMILAR.
AND HERE IS ONE OF THE
NARRATIVES.
LEGAL SAID SAID IT KEEPS SEEING
A STORY THAT GOES LIKE THIS, A
MAN MARRIED TO A WOMAN HAS AN
EXTRA-MARITAL RELATIONSHIP WITH
ANOTHER MAN.
HIS WIFE FIND OUT.
THEY RECONCILE.
NOW, ALL THREE PEOPLE NEED
PROTECTION FROM NIGERIA'S LAWS
ON SAME SEX RELATIONSHIPS.
MOST OF THE APPLICATIONS FOR
ASYLUM IN CANADA ARE HANDLED
HERE IN TORONTO WHICH IS WHY
LEGAL AID IS CONCERNED AND IS
GETTING THE BILL.
>> Adrienne: I UNDERSTAND ABOUT
THE BILLS, THERE IS A LOT MORE
TO THIS.
OBVIOUSLY.
>> THERE IS THE LEGAL COST, OF
COURSE, THE FINANCIAL COST AND
THERE IS A HUMAN COST AT THE
HEART OF THIS TOO.
THE HEAD OF REFUGEE AND
IMMIGRATION SERVICES FOR LEGAL
AID WHO YOU SAW IN THE STORY
SAID HE WORRIES THAT PEOPLE WITH
VERY LEGITIMATE REASONS FOR
FLEEING NIGERIA, FEARS OF BOCA
HARAM AND OTHER POLITICAL
PERSECUTIONS ARE COACHED BY
SOMEONE SOMEWHERE TO FABRICATE A
STORY ABOUT SEXUALITY.
BELIEVING IT HAS A BETTER CHANCE
OF SUCCESS.
AS WE SHOWED HALF OF THE CASES
ARE DENIED.
AND SOMEONE WITH LEGITIMATE
FEARS RISK BEING SENT BACK TO
NIGERIA BECAUSE OF TAKING A
GAMBLE ON A FABRICATED STORY.
>> Adrienne: RIGHT.
THE RISKS ARE STILL REAL.
>>> THANK YOU.
ROSEMARY, IT WILL BE SOME TOUGH
CALLS TO BE MADE AHEAD.
>> Rosemary: A LOT OF PEOPLE
POINT BACK TO THAT TWEET BY THE
PRIME MINISTER LAST JANUARY WHEN
HE SAID EVERYONE IS WELCOME HERE
FOR THE REASON THAT SO MANY ARE
ARRIVING HERE.
>> Adrienne: THEY ARE TAKING HIM
UP ON IT.
>> Rosemary: TONIGHT IS A YEAR
SINCE DONALD TRUMP WAS ELECTED
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
IF YOU JUDGE THE YEAR BY TRUMP'S
CAMPAIGN STYLE RALLIES, IT IS
POLITICAL UPHEAVAL.
IT IS DIVISION.
IT IS THE CAMPAIGN THAT NEVER
ENDED.
>> President Donald Trump: I SAY
IT IS TIME FOR US TO COME
TOGETHER AS ONE UNITED PEOPLE.
ONE YEAR AGO TONIGHT IN THE
U.S., IT LOOKED LIKE THIS.
AND LIKE THIS.
>> NOT MY PRESIDENT!
>> Rosemary: WHETHER THE FIRST
DAY OF A NEW AGE OF AMERICAN
GREATNESS OR THE START OF A
POLITICAL DUMPSTER FIRE, TONIGHT
WE ARE GETTING TO GET A READ ON
WHERE THE COUNTRY IS GOING NOW.
>>> OF COURSE, ONE PERSON WHO
LOVES RELIVING THE U.S. ELECTION
IS OF COURSE DONALD TRUMP.
WE LOOKED INTO IT AND OUT OF THE
PAST 365 DAYS, TRUMP HAS TWEETED
EITHER ABOUT HILLARY CLINTON OR
HIS ELECTION WIN ON 69 OF THEM.
ON AVERAGE, THAT IS MORE THAN
ONCE A WEEK, INCLUDING TODAY.
>>> TODAY'S TWEET IS A PHOTO OF
TRUMP, AT THE PRESIDENTIAL DESK
ON AIR FORCE 1 WITH SOME OF HIS
INNER CIRCLE.
HIS COMMUNICATIONS DIRECTOR, HIS
CONTROVERSIAL FAR RIGHT
POLITICAL ADVISOR.
HIS SON-IN-LAW, HIS STAFF
SECRETARY, AND SOCIAL MEDIA
DIRECTOR.
THE CAPTION...
>> HELLO VIRGINIA.
>> Rosemary: BUT THE LATEST
ELECTORAL LANDSLIDE IN THE U.S.
WAS IN VIRGINIA LAST NIGHT.
WHERE DEMOCRATS WON THE GOVERNOR
SHIP.
AND MORE THAN A DOZEN -- IT IS
THE ONLY REAL ELECTORAL VICTORY
SINCE TRUMP TOOK OFFICE.
IT HAS HIM FIRED UP.
>> YOU DON'T STAND FOR OUR
VALUES.
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY IS BACK, MY
FRIEND.
>> Rosemary: THE TRUTH IS
DESPITE TRUMP'S LOW APPROVAL
RATING, POLLS SHOW MORE THAN 80%
OF REPUBLICANS STILL BACK HIM.
IF LAST YEAR'S ELECTION WERE
HELD AGAIN, TONIGHT, HE WOULD
STILL HAVE AN AWFULLY GOOD
CHANCE OF WINNING.
>>> ONE YEAR LATER, WHAT DO WE
KNOW ABOUT WHERE TRUMP'S AMERICA
GOING?
CAN YOU PREDICT?
FOLLOWING THE POLLS AND
POLITICAL CURRENT IS THIS MAN'S
JOB.
A CORRESPONDENT WITH THE
WASHINGTON POST AND JOINS ME
FROM NEW YORK.
GOOD TO SEE YOU.
LET'S BREAK DOWN VIRGINIA FOR
CANADIANS AND THE DEMOCRATIC
WINS.
SHOULD WE READ ANYTHING INTO
THAT ABOUT WHERE AMERICA IS
HEADED?
>> Interview: YEAH, I MEAN, I
THINK YOU SHOULD.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT WE SAW
LAST YEAR IN THE ELECTION WAS
THAT DONALD TRUMP FACED OFF
AGAINST AN UNPOPULAR OPPONENT,
HILLARY CLINTON.
AND THAT ACTUALLY WORKED TO HIS
ADVANTAGE.
THERE WERE A LOT OF FOLKS STAYED
HOME AND WERE NOT JAZZED ABOUT
COMING OUT TO VOTE.
WHAT WE SAW IN VIRGINIA WAS WE
SAW DEMOCRATS WHO WERE VERY,
VERY MOTIVATED TO COME OUT AND
VOTE.
THIS IS A RACE THE DEMOCRATS
SHOULD HAVE WON.
HILLARY CLINTON WON VIRGINIA
LAST YEAR.
CURRENTLY HAS A DEMOCRATIC
GOVERNOR.
WHAT WE SAW, NORTH WAS EXPECTED
TO WIN 3 POINTS.
HE TRIPLED THAT.
THIS WAS AFTER THE OPPONENT HAD
RUN SOME HARD RIGHT
ANTI-IMMIGRATION ADS THAT ECHOED
WHAT DONALD TRUMP DID.
IT IS A CONTEST BETWEEN A
DEMOCRAT AND SOMEONE TRYING TO
RUN A TRUMP-STYLE CAMPAIGN.
THE DEMOCRAT WON BY A WIDER
MARGIN THAN EXPECTED.
>> Rosemary: TRUMP WAS
DISAVOWING THE LEFT TODAY, EVEN
THOUGH THEY ARE IN LINE WITH ONE
ANOTHER.
WHAT ARE REPUBLICANS READING
INTO THE WAY IT UNFOLDED LAST
NIGHT?
>> Interview: I THINK A LOT OF
REPUBLICANS ARE FREAKED OUT.
I MEAN THIS -- WE HAVE THE 2018
ELECTIONS LOOMING.
EVERYONE IN THE HOUSE OF
REPRESENTATIVES IS UP FOR
RE-ELECTION.
AND THERE WILL BE A LOT OF
REPUBLICANS WHO NEED TO GET PAST
THE PRIMARY WHO NEED TO GET PAST
A MORE CONSERVATIVE ELECTORATE
AND THEN THEY WILL FACE A
DEMOCRAT IN NOVEMBER.
THEY NEED TO FIGURE OUT IS IT
GOING TO BE HELPFUL TO STAND
WITH DONALD TRUMP.
THE ANSWER WAS IT MAY NOT BE.
>> Rosemary: WHAT SHOULD WE --
IT HAS BEEN A YEAR OF
UNPREDICTABLE THINGS IN CANADA
FOR US TOO.
WE HAVE BEEN AFFECTED BY TRUMP
AS MUCH AS YOU MAY BE.
WHAT SHOULD WE LOOK AHEAD TO HOW
IT MAY UNFOLD?
>> Interview: I THINK YOU PLAY
THE CLIP FROM DONALD TRUMP ON
ELECTION NIGHT LAST YEAR.
HE CALLED FOR A UNITED, UNITED
STATES.
HE CALLED FOR UNITY.
WHAT WE HAVE NEVER SEEN FROM HIM
OVER THE 365 DAYS SINCE IS AN
ATTEMPT TO BUILD THE UNITY.
HE CONSISTENTLY PANDERED TO THE
BASE AND REACHED TO THE PEOPLE
WHO VOTED FOR HIM.
WILL DONALD TRUMP DO ANYTHING AT
THIS POINT, DEEPLY UNFAVOURABLE,
HE LOST A BIG RACE THAT SHOWED
THAT HIS SORT OF POLITICS CANNOT
ALWAYS WIN EVERYWHERE.
DOES HE ACTUALLY CHANGE FROM
THIS POINT FORWARD?
THE SMART MONEY IS NO HE CAN'T.
THAT MEANS THAT THE REPUBLICANS
HEAD INTO 2018 WITH AN UNPOPULAR
PRESIDENT WHO A LOT OF AMERICANS
DON'T LIKE.
THEY ARE FACING AHEAD WITH A
STRONG, STRONG HEAD WIND AS WE
SAW LAST NIGHT.
>> Rosemary: CAN THE PRESIDENT
CHANGE IS THE QUESTION AT THIS
POINT?
>> Interview: RIGHT.
THE ALMOST IS ALMOST CERTAINLY
NO.
>> Rosemary: ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR MAKING TIME FOR
US.
I APPRECIATE IT.
>>> THE ELECTION OF DONALD TRUMP
HAD AN IMMEDIATE IMPACT IN
CANADA.
>> President Donald Trump: WE
WILL SEE IF WE CAN GET THE
PIPELINE BUILT.
>> LESS THAN A WEEK IN OFFICE,
HE APPROVED THE KEYSTONE XL
PIPELINE.
TRANS-CANADA IS DECIDING WHETHER
IT WILL GO AHEAD WITH
CONSTRUCTION.
IT COULD BE A POTENTIAL ECONOMIC
BOON FOR ALBERTA.
>> President Donald Trump: THE
UNITED STATES WILL WITHDRAW FROM
THE PARIS CLIMATE ACCORD.
>> Rosemary: CANADA AND THE U.S.
ARE AD ODDS ON CLIMATE CHANGE
AFTER THE PRESIDENT PULLED OUT
OF THE PARIS AGREEMENT, THE U.S.
IS THE ONLY COUNTRY IN THE WORLD
THAT IS NOT SIGNED ON TO THE
LANDMARK CLIMATE DEAL.
>> President Donald Trump: THE
FACT IS NAFTA, WHETHER MEXICO OR
CANADA IS A DISASTER FOR OUR
COUNTRY.
>> Rosemary: THE BIGGEST
WILDCARD IN U.S. CANADA
RELATIONS IS NAFTA.
NEGOTIATORS HAVE BEGUN THE
DIFFICULT TASK OF RE-WRITING THE
FREE TRADE AGREEMENT AND
POTENTIALLY REDEFINING THE
ECONOMIC RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN
CANADA, THE UNITED STATES AND
MEXICO.
THE OUTCOME OF NAFTA COULD
RESHAPE THE ENTIRE CANADIAN
ECONOMY, ESPECIALLY IF THE
PRESIDENT DECIDES TO RIP IT UP.
>>> A LOT RESTS ON HOW THE TWO
GENTLEMEN GET ALONG.
THEY ARE ABOUT TO MEET IN
VIETNAM.
I WILL GO IN-DEPTH ON THAT
COMPLICATED AND STRANGELY GOOD
RELATIONSHIP COMING UP.
>> Andrew: WHAT WE ARE LEARNING
ABOUT THE PLANE CRASH THAT
KILLED ROY HALLADAY.
>> Adrienne: THE SURPRISES YOU
FIND IN A CAMP FOR SYRIANS
DISPLACED BY WAR.
SOME HAVE BEEN HERE A FEW DAYS
HAVE NO IDEA ABOUT THE ISIS
WOMEN JUST STEPS AWAY.
>> Adrienne: HOW DID YOU FEEL
ABOUT THE ISIS WIVES BEING OVER
THERE?
[ CBC News theme ]
You can't just
sit back
and play with your
own little world.
There are other
worlds out there.
Lots of them.
or brush them aside.st igm
You see, the world you know
is really made up of
lots of other worlds.
And all of them have
their own problems,
which in fact,
become your problems.
And worlds aren't simply
made up of problems,
good things happen,
exciting things.
And they all affect you.
The thing is, to unde,
And to understand,
you have to have a complete
and comprehensive
view of matters.
And where to get
this information?
It's easy.
The National News.
Nightly.
On CBC Television.
So welcome other worlds
into your life.
It's almost fun.
The National News.
Reporter:
Five nights a week
in the national news
room of CBC Television,
the stories come in from
all parts of the world,
to be interpreted
and prepared for use on
The National.
[clicking and clacking
of typewriters]
The facts are checked
and the backgrounds gathered.
[rotary phones being dialled]
On the spot reports
are collected,
then the films and the tapes
are evaluated and edited,
readied for
the air.
CBC's correspondents
in all corners of the world
report and interpret
the news.
[dramatic]
Wherever things
are happening,
you'll get
the complete information,
right here on
CBC Television.
I'm Warren
Batis.
Those are just some
of the things
that go into
The National.
Join me.
[ dramatic ]
[ CBC News theme ]
REMMER POINTS OUT
IT DOES NOT COME WITHOUT RISK OF
UP STAGING A PRESIDENT WHO IS AN
ACTUAL TV CELEBRITY AND ENJOYS
THE SPOTLIGHT.
AND OF DISPOINTING PROGRESSIVES
IN OTHER WESTERN COUNTRIES
LOOKING TO TRUDEAU AS AN
EXAMPLE.
RONA AMBROSE, A FORMER FOE AND
MEMBER OF THE PRIME MINISTER'S
NAFTA ADVISORY COUNCIL TO HELP
CANADA KEEP THE DEAL, AGREES.
AND OFFERS THIS WARNING.
>> I THINK IT IS JUST A FINE
LINE BETWEEN, YOU KNOW, LOOKING
LIKE A CELEBRITY AND REMEMBERING
THAT YOU ARE THE PRIME MINISTER.
AT THE END OF THE DAY, PEOPLE
EXPECT YOU TO GO TO WORK AND
WORK HARD FOR YOU.
I THINK THERE COULD BE SOME
DANGER THERE.
>> Rosemary: THAT IS PROVING TO
BE TRUE.
THERE ARE A HANDFUL OF
PROGRESSIVE POLICIES THE PRIME
MINISTER HAS NOT YET MOVED ON,
INCLUDING THE PEACEKEEPING
PROMISE THAT HAS NOT BEEN
FULFILLED.
THE PLEDGE FOR ELECTORAL REFORM,
ABANDONED ENTIRELY AND HIS
PROMISE FOR PAY EQUITY
LEGISLATION TO CLOSE THE GENDER
GAP ON SALARIES HAS BEEN PUSHED
BACK TO NEXT YEAR.
>>> BACK AT THE DINNER IN
WASHINGTON, THEY SMILE FOR
PICTURES.
USING HIS GLOBAL BRAND TO
INFLUENCE THE RELATIONSHIP WITH
TRUMP SEEMS TO BE WORKING.
THE UNPREDICTABILITY, THERE IS
NO GUARANTEE IT ALWAYS WILL.
>>> AHEAD, DOES DONALD TRUMP'S
DIVISIVE LANGUAGE HAVE HIGH-TECH
WORKERS LOOKING NORTH OF THE
BORDER?
WE WILL LOOK INTO CANADA'S BRAIN
GAIN.
>>> YOU MAY HAVE NOTICED A
DIFFERENT POPPY.
PINNED TO SOME JACKETS IN THE
LEADUP TO REMEMBRANCE DAY.
CHECK IT OUT.
THE POPPIES ARE MEANT TO HONOUR
INDIGENOUS PEOPLES WHO SERVED IN
THE MILITARY IN CANADA.
ON THIS ABORIGINAL VETERANS'
DAY, WE ASKED SOME GRADE 7 AND 8
STUDENTS ON THE THUNDERCHILD
FIRST NATION TO SHOW US THEIR
WORK AND THE TEACHER SHOT THE
VIDEO FOR US AND ASKED THEM WHAT
THE POPPIES IN THIS DAY MEAN TO
ALL OF THEM.
>> WE ARE DOING THIS AS A WAY TO
CULTURALLY INCLUDE FIRST
NATIONS.
>> HOW LONG DID IT TAKE TO BEAD
YOUR POPPIES?
>> A DAY AND AND A HALF.
>> WHY DO YOU HAVE ABORIGINAL
VETERANS' DAY SEPARATE FROM
REMEMBRANCE DAY?
>> TO HONOUR OUR ABORIGINAL
VETERANS THAT WERE NOT TREATED
AS EQUALS WHEN THEY GOT
[ CBC News theme ]
When there was beginning to be
a sense that maybe
this was
calming down,
someone set fire to a car,
people stared running
and here come
the riot police.
My best National newscast moment
was my very first one,
when I called my parents and I
told them that I had a story
coming up in
The National
and that Peter was actually
going to say my name
and we were all on the phone
together with televisions on
in Vancouver
and in Toronto,
and we're all listening
for Peter to say the name.
It was kinda...
Yeah, that was...
That was
amazing.
Adrienne Arsenault, CBC News,
Delta, British Columbia.
The CBC's Adrienne Arsenault
tells us what happened.
Adrienne Arsenault
is in Beijing.
for the Party Congress.
Our Adrienne Arsenault
joins us again tonight
from Havana.
I think when The National
has mattered the most
is when huge things happen -
world events.
I distinctly remember watching
Peter on 9/11.
I remember...
And...
the calm sort of things
that he brought to that.
It's those big moments
that stay with me.
Good evening again,
I'm Peter Mansbridge.
They were deliberate.
They were deadly.
The most devastating terror
attacks in the history
of the United States.
Can I say the first time
I hosted The National.
That was such a mind-blowing
experience because
there are these giant doors -
it's like you're
walking into castle.
The doors open up,
you walk in, you can hear
a pin drop in that studio.
And understanding the high
esteem and high standards
to which people hold
that program.
I'll tell you it's
a nerve wracking thing
to of hosted that
program for the first time,
this was years ago.
But it was such
a rewarding experience
and such
a learning experience.
2002 in Salt Lake City,
watching the men's team win
first gold medal
in 50 years,
and then realizing that the pass
I had allowed me to go to
the side of the rink and watch
the Canadian players
with their medals around their
neck and be able to say
to Eric Lindros
and Al MacInnnis like,
"Can you come over here?
Can I talk to you?"
And trying really hard not
to be a fan and still
be a journalist.
A year ago people were wondering
whether you were going to play
again, here you are with
a gold medal around your neck.
Yeah! This has been
a great ride.
I have known Ian
"Handsome-man-thing"
for 25 years.
And when I...
My first job
at The National was as
an editorial assistant,
so that was the very first
job I had at CBC.
25 years ago I was photocopying
scripts and delivering
newspapers at
The National.
And one of my
jobs was to -
on a huge story, which was
the LA riots -
from afar,
be Ian Hanomansing's researcher.
Clearly the jury's decision
was the spark
but as the CBC's Ian Hanomansing
reports it wasn't the cause.
[sirens]
Ian: This is South Central LA,
today it is tense.
But even on a good day residents
say this is a part of America
where the "American Dream"
doesn't exist.
I was on a payphone and looking
around at all this chaos
and calling back to Toronto
and talking to someone,
this young editorial
assistant who
was so smart and instantly
understood what we needed.
And I remember one of the things
she said to us was
"I'm here for you guys
throughout the night
for as long
as you need us."
And it just felt so
comforting and her guidance was
so good and that
was Adrienne.
I have known this man
for 25 years
and I love him
like a brother.
And I screamed very loudly,
in a good way.
>> SYRIA DOES NOT GENERATE MANY
GOOD PICTURES THESE DAYS, THESE
SHOW CIVILIANS HEADING BACK TO
RAQQA.
AT LEAST INTO THE ONE SLIVER OF
THE ONE NEIGHBOURHOOD THAT HAS
BEEN OPENED.
IT IS STILL DAMAGED, SOME
BUILDINGS DANGEROUS.
BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY, THERE IS
DEMINING.
THIS IS A START.
6 MILLION OTHER SYRIANS ARE NOT
SO FORTUNATE.
THEY ARE LIVING IN SQUALID
CONDITIONS IN CAMPS FOR
INTERNALLY DISPLACED PERSONS.
WE GOT ACCESS TO ONE OF THE
CAMPS IN THE TRIP INTO SYRIA.
THERE IS THE PAIN YOU WOULD
EXPECT AND SOME SURPRISES.
>> FORGET DRIVING AT NIGHT.
WITH CHECKPOINTS, YOU NEED
LIGHT.
HOW ELSE WOULD YOU EVER SEE
THIS.
THESE ARE PEOPLE ON THE RUN FROM
ISIS FROM THE REGIME FROM NEW
MILITIAS.
AND THIS IS THE EDGE OF THE IDP
CAMP NORTH OF RAQQA.
JUST 2600 TENTS PER 30,000
PEOPLE.
IT IS FLAT OUT MISERABLE.
AND IT IS CONFUSING AT FIRST.
FOR ALL THE PEOPLE IN THE DIRT,
SOME HAVE REAL SHELTER.
YOU MAY BE SURPRISED WHO.
>> ALL THE KIDS.
WHICH IS WHY THEY ARE
UNCOMFORTABLE US BEING HERE.
THIS IS ONE HOLDING AREA FOR THE
FOREIGN WIVES AND CHILDREN OF
ISIS FIGHTERS.
SOME OF THE WOMEN MAY BE
PROSECUTED.
BUT NO ONE KNOWS WHAT TO DO WITH
THE THOUSANDS OF KIDS BORN TO
ISIS FAMILIES.
WE ASK IF ANYONE WANTS TO TALK.
AWAY FROM THE EVER PRESENT
GUARDS.
THERE IS ONE.
SHE IS FROM AZERBIJAN, SHE
INSISTS TO PROTECT HER IDENTITY.
HER LITTLE SISTER YELLING AT HER
NOT TO TALK.
BUT SHE IS THE LEADER IN THE
FAMILY NOW.
AND MAKES THE DECISIONS.
THE DOOR CLOSES AND HER TOUGH
TONE CHANGES.
SHE IS BARELY 18.
HER SON IS NEARLY 3.
THE MAN SHE WAS FORCED TO MARRY
WAS KILLED.
SHE WAS MADE TO MARRY AGAIN.
HE IS DEAD TOO.
WHAT DOES SHE THINK OF ISIS NOW?
SHE TALKS ABOUT BEING BROUGHT
HERE.
SHE TALKS TO NO ONE, SHE SAID
SHE SAID SHE HOPES TALKING TO US
WILL LET PEOPLE KNOW THAT BEING
CONNECTED TO ISIS IS NOT SO
CLEAR-CUT.
THE THING IS EVEN OFF CAMERA,
EVERY WOMAN IN THE ISIS COMPOUND
TALKS OF BEING A VICTIM.
AND MANY ARE.
THE AUTHORITIES ARE NOT
CONVINCED OF THAT.
IT IS NOT QUITE JAIL.
THEY CANNOT SEEM TO LEAVE.
JUST OUTSIDE THE COMPOUND, A
SPRAWLING SPACE WITH LITTLE TO
NO PROTECTION FROM THE ELEMENTS.
SOME HAVE BEEN HERE ONLY A FEW
DAYS HAVE NO IDEA ABOUT THE ISIS
WOMEN JUST STEPS AWAY.
HOW DO YOU FEEL ABOUT THE ISIS
WIVES BEING OVER THERE?
TINY BUT TOUGH.
SHE IS 70.
ADOPTED THE KIDS, HER
GRANDCHILDREN.
THEIR PARENTS WERE KILLED IN AN
AIR STRIKE.
COME SEE WHERE WE ARE LIVING,
SHE TELLS US.
THIS IS NOT HER TENT.
THE STRANGERS WERE NOTHING
THEMSELVES ARE SHARING.
WHEN WAS THE AIR STRIKE THAT
KEPT HER UNDER THE HOUSE?
NEARLY BLIND AND RESPONSIBLE FOR
THESE KIDS, EVERYTHING HAS BEEN
ABOUT FEEDING THEM.
EVEN BEFORE THE AIR STRIKES,
THEY WERE BARELY HANGING ON.
WHAT ISIS IT IS A CONSTANT
CONVERSATION HERE.
IN ANOTHER TENT ACROSS THE CAMP,
A ONCE FAMOUS RAQQA WEDDING
SINGER.
WHEN ISIS CAME, THAT WAS IT FOR
THE SINGING FOR YOU?
THE FAMILY LEFT RAQQA 7 MONTHS
AGO, SHEDDING THE FEAR OF ISIS
MORE EVERY DAY.
THEY WOULD BEHEAD ME FOR SHOWING
SKIN.
THEY ARE CONSUMED WITH WORRY.
ABOUT NOT BEING ABLE TO FIND
THEIR SON.
ISIS ARRESTED HIM.
EXHAUSTION IS A FACT OF A PLACE
LIKE THIS, SO IS THE EFFORT TO
PRESERVE DIGNITY.
CELEBRATING THE BRAND NEW TO THE
WORLD.
AND THE LITTLEST OF PLEASURES.
BUT THIS PLACE IS IN TROUBLE,
THE ICE COLD RAIN IS COMING.
AN INTERNATIONAL GROUP STRUGGLES
TO GET IN.
AND EVERY SINGLE DAY MORE SHOW
UP ON THE TOTALLY UNSERVED EDGES
OF THE CAMP.
THEY STOP, SIT DOWN AND DECLARE
IT HOME.
>> Rosemary: IT IS STARTLING TO
SEE THAT.
YOU WERE THERE AND YOU TALKED TO
THE PEOPLE.
WHERE DO THEY FIND ANY HOPE,
ADRIENNE, THEIR LIVES WILL GET
BETTER?
>> Adrienne: IT IS A HUMAN
CONDITION TO ALWAYS LOOK FOR A
LITTLE BIT OF HOPE.
THEY SAY THEY HAVE NOT BECAUSE
THEY THINK THEY CAN GET THROUGH
THIS BECAUSE IT IS TEMPORARILY
AND THEY ARE GOING HOME.
BUT WHAT THEY ARE GOING TO LEARN
IS THAT HOME IS GOING TO BE SO
DIFFERENT BECAUSE IT IS NOT JUST
THE VIOLENCE, BUT IT REALLY IS
THE POLITICS OF THE PLACE THAT
HAVE CHANGED EVERYTHING.
IT DOESN'T TAKE MUCH OF A LOOK
AT THE BROKEN PLACE TO WONDER IF
RAQQA, IF SYRIA CAN BE REBUILT
AGAIN.
BUT THE THING ABOUT WAR IS THAT
WHEN THE GUNS STOP, THAT'S WHEN
THE CONSTRUCTION ALWAYS BEGINS.
THE QUESTIONS, THOUGH, ARE HOW
DO YOU REBUILD AND WHO GETS TO
DECIDE WHO DOES THE REBUILDING?
[]
THIS REAL ESTATE PITCH FOR A
SOUTHERN DAMASCUS SUBURB MAY
OFFER A CLUE.
REIMAGINING OF A NEIGHBOURHOOD.
PARKS AND HIGH RISE CONDOS AND
AN UNDER GROUND SHOPPING MALL.
OBVIOUSLY THIS IS A FAR CRY FROM
WHAT IT LOOKS LIKE DURING THE UP
RISING WHEN FOUR SYRIANS, FILLED
WITH UNAUTHORIZED SETTLEMENTS
CALLED FOR A REGIME CHANGE.
THAT SUBURB WAS VIOLENTLY TAKEN
BY THE GOVERNMENT.
IT CHANGED.
THE SETTLEMENTS IN 2011, AND
MORE RECENTLY, ALL THAT GREEN
GONE.
THE SETTLEMENTS TOO, THE WAR
TOOK THEM ALL.
NOT FOR A MOMENT DOES ANYONE
THINK THAT THE VIOLENCE AND THE
WAR IN SYRIA IS REALLY OVER.
BUT WHAT IS BECOMING
INCREASINGLY CLEAR IS THAT
BASHAR al-ASSAD IS IN PLACE.
HE IS STILL EFFECTIVELY IN
CHARGE AND THAT MEANS HE IS IN
CHARGE OF REBUILDING TOO.
HE IS WORKING FAST.
HE WANTED A POLITICALLY
PROBLEMATIC SETTLEMENT GONE FO E
YEARS.
HE CLAIMED THE TERRORISTS HID IN
THE TREES.
>> THE SITUATION IS CATASTROPHIC
FOR THE PEOPLE THAT USED TO LIVE
IN THIS AREA.
>> Reporter: THIS MAN IS A SWISS
SYRIAN ACTIVIST AND ACADEMIC WHO
HAS STUDIED THE RECONSTRUCTION.
HE SAID A 2012 LAW CALLED DECREE
66 IS A POLITICAL WEAPON FOR
ASSAD.
IT ALLOWS HIS GOVERNMENT TO CUT
DOWN AND REDEVELOP AREAS OF
UNAUTHORIZED HOUSING AND
INFORMAL SETTLEMENT.
>> Interview: IT IS A MATTER
TARGETING POPULATION EFFECTED BY
THE SOCIETY THAT REVOLTED
AGAINST THE REGIME.
>> WITH SO MANY SYRIANS WHO
OPPOSED HIM DEAD OR DISPLACED,
THE DECREE MEANS THE
NEIGHBOURHOODS CAN BE FILLED
WITH NEW PEOPLE FILLED BY THE
REGIME.
WE TRIED TO GET PICTURES.
YOU SEE A LITTLE EVIDENCE IN
RECENT SATELLITE IMAGERY.
HUGE MOUNDS OF EARTH.
THE MACHINES THAT MOVE IT
AROUND.
THIS IS HAPPENING.
AND IF ASSAD SEES REBUILDING AS
A CHANCE TO ENGINEER OUT
OPPOSING VOICES, MORE WAR IS
SURELY AHEAD.
IT WILL TAKE A LOT OF MONEY TO
REBUILD.
THE COMPANIES FROM IRAN,
LEBANON, RUSSIA, CHINA ARE
ALREADY ONBOARD WITH THEIR BIDS.
ASSAD SAID HE IS WILLING TO TAKE
BIDS FROM OTHER COUNTRIES TOO.
INCLUDING THE UNITED STATES,
PROVIDED THAT FIRST HE GETS AN
APOLOGY FROM THE AMERICANS.
>>> YOU CAN FIND MORE OF THE
REPORTING FROM SYRIA ONLINE,
INCLUDING STORIES FROM THE
PEOPLE WE TALKED TO IN THEIR OWN
WORDS.
SURVIVING ISIS AT
[ theme ]
[hockey rink ambience]
Reporter: Because of his size,
and particularly in
this league, which is
a really rough league --
are you scared
for him at all?
No. Wayne -- Wayne has --
if you watch him closely,
there are very few times that --
that he'll really get hammered.
He seems to have eyes
on the back of his head,
at times, but he -- instead
of forcing against a check,
Wayne has the knack
of rolling with the check.
And he never, ever, gets hurt
badly in that respect.
You're not scared?
No.
[skates scraping]
[audience cheering]
What he's found,
and what we've found,
that they're checking
him a lot closer,
and they're going to conti.
But I think he has enough
brains, enough matzy,
to overcome all
the checkers on him.
A number of the goals
he's getting, and the number
of points he's getting
must surprise even you.
I mean, it's impossible for a 16
year old to do that in Junior A.
That's something that we've
never expected or dreamed of.
We thought play September,
come Christmas,
that he would help
our hockey club.
Here he came to our training
camp, we dropped the puck.
From day one, he's helped b
and continued
to score, and score.
[shouting]
[ice scraping]
How much do you think,
Wayne, when you're --
when you're operating a play?
When I'm out there I try to
think as far ahead as I can,
you know, even before
the play develops.
I try to think where
the puck's going to go,
and where to be,
you know?
When I go in on a goal,
I think about everything
else but scoring.
I just go in there.
And, like the other night, in
Ottawa, I was going to do
something, I was thinking
of it anyway,
and all of a sudden, everything
just went blank, and all
of a sudden I looked up
and the goalie's right there.
And I just have
to go around him.
Reporter: Is that instinct
you think, or what is it?
Wayne: Part of it's instinct, y,
but a lot of it takes
a lot of practice.
Not -- not in the older age,
but when you're younger
four, five, six,
even 10 and 11, you know?
And I worked on it
then real hard,
and it's been paying
off for me.
What do you want for him?
You want -- you want him
to be the next Bobby Orr?
Well, I don't think
he could be a Bobby Orr,
but whatever Wayne wants,
and like I said earlier,
as long as we can get his
schooling out of hockey,
I think both his mother,
and myself,
have accomplished everything
that all the time
has gone in to, with him.
Right now, I want to play two
solid years of Junior A hockey,
and get my grade 12,
or at least 13.
If I stay in junior hockey,
I go farther in school.
But --
University?
Yes, I'll be going to attend
university for sure.
Even if you turn pro?
I don't know.
That's too far ahead.
I know that I'm going
to grade 13.
After that I'll make up my mind
what I'm going to do.
Walter Gretzky: Still
four years away too,
so anything could happen
in four years.
We had always hoped
that as long
as we got Wayne his
schooling through hockey,
we pretty well accomplished o
in respect to Wayne,
and hockey.
Wayne: I don't know what's
going to happen, you know.
I just hope that
I make pro hockey.
Oh!
[crowd cheering]
[ theme ]
>> President Donald Trump:
AMERICA WILL NO LONGER SETTLE
FOR ANYTHING LESS THAN THE BEST.
THE FORGOTTEN MEN AND WOMEN OF
OUR COUNTRY WILL BE FORGOTTEN NO
LONGER.
>> Andrew: SINCE DONALD TRUMP'S
ELECTION VICTORY, WE HAVE HEARD
A LOT OF TALK THAT HIS HARD LINE
STANCE ON IMMIGRATION COULD HURT
THE UNITED STATES TECHNOLOGY
SECTOR.
WE ARE ASKING, AS WORKERS AROUND
THE WORLD LOOK FOR FRIENDLIER
SHORES IS CANADA REAPING A BRAIN
GAIN.
>> CANADA IS IN AN UNIQUE
POSITION FOR IMMIGRATION
ADVANTAGE.
>> Andrew: IS CANADA IN A
STRONGER POSITION BECAUSE OF
TRUMP?
WHAT IS GOING ON?
WE ASKED THE BUSINESS REPORTER
RENEE FILIPPONE TO DRILL INTO
THAT.
>> TECH IMMIGRATION SO FAR THIS
YEAR IS ON TRACK TO MEET AND
WHAT WE KNOW HOW IS LIKELY BEAT
LAST YEAR'S NUMBERS.
OVER THE PAST DECADE, THERE HAVE
BEEN AN OVERALL INCREASE IN TECH
SECTOR IMMIGRATION, NEARLY
DOUBLING IN FACT SINCE 2007.
SO NOW WE HAVE THE NUMBERS FOR
THE FIRST 8 MONTHS OF 2017,
SINCE TRUMP WAS ELECTED AND FOR
THAT TIME PERIOD, NEARLY 7,000
PEOPLE HAVE COME TO CANADA,
ALMOST AS MANY AS LAST YEAR AND
THERE ARE FOUR MONTHS TO COME.
>> Andrew: HOW DO WE KNOW THAT
TRUMP IS THE ONE DRIVING THAT?
>> Reporter: IT IS DIFFICULT TO
TRACK THE MOTIVATION.
IMMEDIATELY FOLLOWING THE
VICTORY OF TRUMP AND THE
INAUGURATION, THERE WERE SPIKES
IN INTEREST IN CANADIAN TECH JOB
POSTINGS.
THERE IS MORE RECENTLY, A SURVEY
OF 150 TORONTO TECH COMPANIES.
62% SAY THEY SAW MORE AMERICAN
APPLICANTS THIS YEAR.
>> Andrew: TO GO DEEPER, I
PRESUME YOU HAVE TO TALK WITH
FOLKS WHO ARE MAKING THE MOVES.
WHAT DID YOU FIND THERE?
>> I MET WITH TWO INDIVIDUALS.
A MAN FROM INDIA WHO SPENT THE
LAST 6 YEARS IN SILICON VALLEY
ON A TEMPORARY WORKING VISA TIED
TO HIS JOB AT LINKDON AND MOVED
TO TORONTO A YEAR AGO AND A
WOMAN WORKING FOR TWITTER IN
SINGAPORE, BUT THAT COUNTRY
DOESN'T RECOGNIZE HER SAME SEX
PARTNER AND ARE LOOKING TO START
A FAMILY AND WANTED TO MOVE.
HAVE A LISTEN TO WHY PETRA AND
VICRUM DECIDED AGAINST THE U.S.
>> THE PLAN WAS TO MOVE BACK TO
THE U.S. AFTER MY STAY IN
SINGAPORE.
DONALD TRUMP BECAME PRESIDENT
AND I THOUGHT MORE, IS THAT A
BETTER PLAN THAN THE UNITED
STATES?
>> THE VISA REGULATIONS THAT
U.S. IMPOSES ARE QUITE
RESTRICTIVE.
ESPECIALLY TO PEOPLE BORN IN
CERTAIN POPULOUS COUNTRIES.
AND THAT KIND OF PUTS THEM ON A
TRACK TO WAIT FOR LIKE A GREEN
CARD.
IT BASICALLY TAKES THEM 20 PLUS
YEARS TO GET A GREEN CARD.
>> ALWAYS THOUGHT -- I THINK HE
IS MAKING CANADA GREAT.
>> Andrew: OKAY.
THEY CROSSED THE U.S. OFF THE
LIST.
TURNING TO CANADA, WHY COME HERE
SPECIFICALLY?
>> Reporter: THE CANADIAN TECH
SECTOR IS BOOMING.
OVER THE PAST FIVE YEARS, LABOUR
GROWTH IN THE SECTOR HAS BEEN
DOUBLE THE REST OF THE CANADIAN
ECONOMY.
SO THERE ARE JOBS, THESE ARE
HIGHLY SKILLED ONES.
STILL, VICRUM AND PETRA HAD TO
WEIGH THE PROS AND CONS.
>> I PUT IN MY PERMANENT
APPLICATION AND IT WAS APPROVED
IN AUGUST.
>> ONE FRIEND SAID TORONTO IS
THE BEST KEPT SECRET IN NORTH
AMERICA.
I RECOMMEND PEOPLE GET A PARKA.
>> Interview: I KNOW CANADA HAS
AN IMMIGRATION SYSTEM WHICH IS
SO MUCH MORE RATIONAL THAN OTHER
SYSTEMS.
>> PEOPLE IN TORONTO HAVE BEEN,
CHOOSING TORONTO?
IT IS EXPENSIVE HERE.
I AM LIKE YOU HAVE TO THE TRIED
CALIFORNIA.
>> IT IS TRUE THAT I DID HAVE TO
TAKE SOME SALARY CUT.
ESPECIALLY ON AFTER-TAX BASIS.
I REALLY THINK STILL ALL IN ALL,
IT HAS BEEN A GREAT DECISION SO
FAR.
>> Interview: SOMEONE I SPOKE TO
AND HE ASKED IF THERE WERE POLAR
BEARS THERE AND STUFF.
I TOLD HIM YES.
>> Reporter: THERE ARE
SOMEWHERE.
NOT TORONTO.
>> Andrew: HOPING THE
IMMIGRATION NUMBERS DO NOT DROP
AFTER THAT.
I UNDERSTAND IT WAS WEEKS TO GET
APPROVAL TO WORK HERE.
HOW IS THAT THE CASE?
>> PETRA CAME UNDER THE PILOT
PROGRAM.
THAT WAS LAUNCHED IN JUNE TO
BRING IN TALENT IN A MATTER OF
WEEKS.
THE CBC NEWS HAS OBTAINED EARLY
NUMBERS FROM THAT PROGRAM.
IN JUST THE FIRST TWO AND A HALF
MONTHS, THE GOVERNMENT RECEIVED
MORE THAN 2,000 APPLICANTS FOR
THESE TEMPORARY WORK PERMITS.
AND SAID, YES, TO 1,600 OR 80%
OF THE APPLICATIONS.
ANDREW, THAT IS A LOT OF PEOPLE
IN A SHORT PERIOD OF TIME.
MANY DESTINED FOR THE TECH
SECTOR.
THESE ARE PEOPLE WHO MAY NOT
HAVE BEEN LOOKING TO CANADA IF
IT WERE NOT FOR WHAT WAS GOING
ON IN THE U.S.
>> Andrew: INTERESTING.
THANK YOU.
>>> NOW, YOU MAY HAVE NOTICED
THAT THERE HAVE BEEN JUST THREE
OF US IN STUDIO.
THAT IS BECAUSE IAN, YOU HAVE
ACTUALLY BEEN WORKING ON A
STORY.
THAT IS GOING TO BE A REGULAR
THING FOR US ALL ON DIFFERENT
DAYS.
ABOUT FENTANYL.
>> TODAY WORKING THE PHONES.
WE ARE EXPECTING THE LATEST
NUMBERS FROM THE B.C. CORONER
OFFICE TOMORROW AND EXPECTING A
TREND TO CONTINUE.
300 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN DYING OF
OVERDOSES THIS YEAR.
DESPITE ALL THAT HAS BEEN DONE
IN B.C. TO TRY TO REDUCE THE
NUMBER OF DEATHS.
FOR EXAMPLE, THE VANCOUVER
POLICE DEPARTMENT ENCOURAGES
DRUG USERS TO MAKE SURE SOMEONE
IS WITH THEM TO CALL 911 IN CASE
THEY OVERDOSE.
THEY WILL NOT BE ARRESTED.
IN FACT, AND THIS MAY SURPRISE
SOME OF YOU ACROSS THE COUNTRY,
THE DPD HAS DECRIMINALIZED
POSSESSION OF COCAINE AND
HEROIN.
MORE TOMORROW.
YOU WILL MEET THE MOTHER OF
TRISTAN KROKER.
HE DIED WEEKS AGO.
IT IS TOUGH FOR HER AND HER
FAMILY.
I WANT TO PLAY A CLIP OF HER.
SHE WAS OUTSIDE HER CONDO IN THE
VANCOUVER CONDO OF NEW
WESTMINSTER.
DESCRIBING THE LAST TIME SHE SAW
TRISTAN.
THE MORNING OF THE DAY HE DIED.
>> WE HAD A FIGHT AND HE WENT
OUT THAT WAY AND I DROVE OFF
THAT WAY.
THAT IS THE LAST TIME I SAW HIM.
THAT WAS THE
["The National" theme]
And this is something else
that's in use now,
and will one day be
a part of every home.
It's called
the video phone.
It's very simple to use.
Pick up the dial,
punch the buttons...
And I just press a button
and here I see Lloyd, hi!
Hi, Sandy.
And how are you?
I'm fine, thank you.
I can't see you yet.
You can't see me?
You can just punch up a button.
Oh, there you are,
there you are.
See, I'm right
in front of the lens.
Beautiful, mhm.
Very good,
but I can control this.
if I'm off centre,
you can't see me anymore.
So...
You'd only want to do that if
you weren't properly dressed,
though, wouldn't you?
Right, so there'll be
no peeking at ladies
when they're dripping wet
and fresh from the tub.
[eerie, futuristic]
Say, what's going
on here?
Hey, what's your name,
what are you doing?
Je m'appelle William Liberman,.
Oh, he says
he's Willy Liberman,
and he's learning
how to speak French.
Well, tell me how this little
machine works, Willy.
Well, this is a teaching
machine, and it's very simple.
Even an adult could use it.
[chuckles]
You see, in this box
on magnetic tapes
are 22 15-minute French lesson.
Mhm.
So say I want lesson number .
I turn the dial and pull the.
Yes.
Now, after each phrase in Free
so if I want,
I can repeat the phrase
into this microphone
right here.
Mhm.
And it will be recorded
on another channel.
Later, I can turn back and hear
both myself and the teacher
and I can check
my pronunciation.
That's great.
Say, Willy, how would
you like to have
a nice, juicy hot dog?
Oh, oui monsieur!
Oui? Bon, trs bien!
Sandy, can we use your oven?
By all means,
get right in there.
[speaking French]
Lloyd, Willy's machine
is not experimental,
it's actually being used
in schools today.
Lloyd: Well now, here, Sandy,
I see a very old
and a very
beautiful painting.
It looks great, but I don't
quite see the point.
What's this got to do
with the future?
Well it is very beautiful, I a.
It was painted by Aelbert Cuyp.
And it was painted in the 17th,
and now hangs in the art
gallery in Toronto.
It's worth about $20,000.
You see, some things
won't change.
Ovens and telephones
and teaching aids
may get newer and
more progressive,
but this painting
represents something
which is very dear to us--
and that something,
in a word, is art.
["The National" theme]