[♪♪♪]
>> Ian: IT IS NOVEMBER 10TH.
THIS IS THE NATIONAL.
WE BEGIN WITH MAJOR STORIES
DEVELOPING IN THE NATION'S
CAPITAL TONIGHT.
>>> WE ARE COMING TO YOU FROM
THE NATIONAL WAR MEMORIAL.
IN OTTAWA.
AND ON THE EVE OF REMEMBRANCE
DAY, WHEN CANADIANS WILL BE
REFLECTING ON SACRIFICES.
CBC NEWS LEARNED EXCLUSIVE
DETAILS ABOUT OTTAWA'S PLAN FOR
THE FUTURE OF TODAY'S TROOPS.
IN A TRAUMATIC MOVE, THE
GOVERNMENT APPEARS TO BE THE
CHANGING THE FACE OF
PEACEKEEPING.
MURRAY, WHAT CAN YOU TELL US
ABOUT CANADA'S PLANS THEY WILL
ANNOUNCE NEXT WEEK?
>> CANADA WILL HOST A
MINISTERIAL MEETING IN
VANCOUVER.
THE LIBERAL GOVERNMENT INTENDS
TO OFFER UP A LIST OF HIGH-LEVEL
EQUIPMENT AND TROOPS THAT IT CAN
HAND OVER TO THE U.N. FOR
SPECIFIC PEACEKEEPING MISSIONS.
WHAT IT WILL NOT DO IN
VANCOUVER, THIS NEXT WEEK IS
COMMIT TO A SPECIFIC MISSION,
THAT'S SOMETHING EVERYBODY HAS
BEEN WAITING FOR.
>> Ian: LET'S CONTRAST THIS TO
THE ORIGINAL PEACEKEEPING PLEDGE
THAT THE LIBERALS MADE IN 2016.
>> Interview: IN THE SUMMER OF
2016, THE LIBERALS PROMISED TO
DELIVER 600 TROOPS AND 150
POLICE OFFICERS.
THE U.N. HAS BEEN ANXIOUS FOR
CANADA TO MAKE A DECISION
OFFERING BIG ROLES IN MISSIONS
IN MALI, THE CENTRAL AFRICAN
REPUBLIC, SOUTH SUDAN AND THE
REPUBLIC OF CONGO.
WHAT THE NEW ANNOUNCEMENT MEANS
IS THAT DEPLOYMENTS WHEN THEY DO
EVENTUALLY COME WILL LIKELY BE
SMALLER AND HIGHLY SPECIALIZED.
THINK OF TRANSPORT PLANES AND
HELICOPTERS AS OPPOSED TO
SOLDIERS AND TANKS.
AND A LOT OF THE SPECIALIZED
SKILLS WILL BE IN DEMAND LIKE
BOMB DISPOSAL AND TRAINING FOR
OTHER U.N. PEACEKEEPERS,
PARTICULARLY WOMEN.
>> Ian: PEACEKEEPING IS SO
IMPORTANT TO CANADA, SO
IMPORTANT TO PAST LIBERAL PRIME
MINISTERS.
WHY IS THE GOVERNMENT GOING DOWN
THIS DIFFERENT ROAD INSTEAD?
>> Reporter: PEACEKEEPING HAS
CHANGED.
IT DOES NOT LOOK LIKE THE
PEACEKEEPING MOST CANADIANS
WOULD RECOGNIZE.
IT IS MORE DANGEROUS.
IT REQUIRES LONG, MULTI-YEAR
COMMITMENTS.
AND THERE IS A FEAR OF GETTING
BOGGED DOWN.
AND GHOST OF KANDAHAR.
CANADA WAS NOT EXPECTING TO BE
IN A LONG GUERRILLA WAR IN
AFGHANISTAN.
A LOT OF COUNTRIES ARE INVOLVED
IN INTRACTABLE CONTRACTS WHERE
THERE IS NO PEACE TO KEEP.
>> Ian: THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> Reporter: THANK YOU.
>>> THE BIG STORY IN THE CITY
TONIGHT INVOLVES THE FINANCE
MINISTER, BILL MORNEAU.
AFTER SPENDING WEEKS IN A CLOUD
OF CONTROVERSY, WE HAVE LEARNED
HE IS NOW UNDER INVESTIGATION BY
THE ETHICS COMMISSIONER.
MARY DAWSON CONFIRMED TODAY SHE
IS OFFICIALLY LOOKING INTO THE
CASE.
THE BIG QUESTION HERE WHETHER
THERE WAS A CONFLICT OF INTEREST
WHETHER MORNEAU SPONSORED A
PENSION BILL.
WHILE STILL OWNING SHARES IN HIS
FAMILY'S PENSION COMPANY.
DAVID COCHRANE IS FOLLOWING THE
STORY FOR US TONIGHT AND, DAVID,
WHAT MORE CAN YOU TELL US ABOUT
THE INVESTIGATION?
>> Reporter: IAN, IT HAS TO DO
WITH BILL C27, THE PENSION
REFORM BILL THAT CRITICS SAID IF
IT PASSED, MORNEAU'S COMPANY
COULD MAKE A LOT OF MONEY,
PENSION ADMINISTRATION SERVICES
IS WHAT IT DOES.
THE ISSUE IS THE FACT THAT BILL
MORNEAU OWNED A MILLION SHARES
IN MORNEAU SCHAPEL AT THE TIME
HE TABLED THE BILL AND WERE NOT
HELD IN A BLIND TRUST.
THE CONSERVATIVES ASKED FOR AN
INVESTIGATION.
THE NEW DEMOCRATS ASKED FOR AN
MARY DAWSON IS GIVING THEM AN
INVESTIGATION.
THIS MEANS THE TWO MOST
IMPORTANT PEOPLE IN THE
GOVERNMENT ARE NOW BEING
INVESTIGATED BY THE ETHICS
COMMISSIONER.
BILL MORNEAU AND JUSTIN TRUDEAU
FOR HIS CHRISTMAS VACATION ON
THE AGA KHAN ISLAND.
>> WHAT IS THE FINANCE MINISTER
SAYING?
>> HE SENT A STATEMENT AFTER THE
NEWS BROKE AND BILL MORNEAU SAID
HE IS PROMISING TO FULLY
COOPERATE.
THIS IS WHAT HE SAID...
AND, IAN, WE SHOULD POINT OUT
THAT MORNEAU FOLLOWED DAWSON'S
ADVICE TO THE LETTER AND HOW TO
HANDLE HIS PERSONAL WEALTH AND
ENDED UP IN THE MESS.
HE HAS TAKEN OTHER STEPS TO
CLEAR HIS NAME.
PROMISING TO SELL THE SHARES AND
DONATE THE PROFITS TO CHARITY.
THAT IS $5 MILLION, POTENTIALLY,
THAT HE IS PREPARED TO GIVE AWAY
TO CLEAR HIS NAMES.
IF DAWSON FINDS WRONGDOING IN
THE INVESTIGATION, SHE CAN FINE
HIM MORE.
500 BUCKS.
THE MONEY WOULD NOT BE THE
PROBLEM FOR BILL MORNEAU, THE
FACT HE IS NAMED AND SHAMED AND
VIOLATING THE CONFLICT OF
INTEREST ACT.
>> Ian: LATE ON A FRIDAY NIGHT.
IT GOT BUSY IN THE OTTAWA
BUREAU.
THANK YOU.
>>> ADRIENNE, WE ARE HERE
BECAUSE OF REMEMBRANCE DAY
TOMORROW AND WE HAVE MORE
COVERAGE TO COME FROM THIS CITY.
>> Adrienne: WE WILL DEFINITELY
GET BACK TO YOU SOON, IAN.
WE HAVE TO TURN NOW TO A STORY
THAT HAS GRIPPED PEOPLE AROUND
THE WORLD TODAY AND REALLY FOR
MUCH OF THIS WEEK.
THAT IS THE STORY OF THE NEW
INSIGHTS INTO THE SEXUAL
REVELATIONS THAT ARE SHAKING THE
ENTERTAINMENT BUSINESS.
FROM COMIC LOUIS C.K., AN
ADMISSION OF GUILT.
FROM ELLEN PAGE, HIGHLY PERSONAL
STORIES OF EMOTIONAL ABUSE.
AND ASSAULT.
THIS WEEK, THE HUMAN AND
FINANCIAL COST SEEM TO BE
MOUNTING BY THE HOUR.
WE SEE MORE CLEARLY THE DREAM
FACTORY DARK SIDE.
>> HOW DO WOMEN STILL GO OUT
WITH GUYS WHEN YOU CONSIDER THE
FACT THERE IS NO GREATER THREAT
TO WOMEN THAN MEN.
>> Adrienne: REVERED OR SMASHING
SOCIAL NORMALS.
HE CONFIRMED HE MASTURBATE IN
FRONT OF YOUNG WOMEN...
NOW, HE DID NOT SAY THE WORDS
SORRY OR I APOLOGIZE IN THE
STATEMENT.
BUT APPARENTLY HE DID TO SOME OF
THE WOMEN DIRECTLY.
>> THAT'S RIGHT, SEVERAL OF
WOMEN RECEIVED MESSAGES FROM HIM
OR SPOKE TO HIM ON THE PHONE AND
HE EXPRESSED FEELING SORRY HIS
BEHAVIOUR.
YOU KNOW, ONE OF THE THINGS THAT
IS INTERESTING ABOUT THIS
BEHAVIOUR IS THAT IT REALLY HITS
DEEPLY.
AND AN APOLOGY IS A GREAT MOVE
TO MAKE, BUT IT DOESN'T
NECESSARILY ERASE THE PAIN OR
THE TRAUMA OF THE ORIGINAL
EXPERIENCE.
>> Adrienne: THE DAMAGE AND
ABUSE OF POWER CAN CAUSE WAS
MADE PAINFULLY CLEAR TODAY WHEN
THE CANADIAN ACTOR ELLEN PAGE
TOOK TO FACEBOOK.
SHE WROTE ABOUT AN INCIDENT ON A
SET OF AN X-MAN MOVIE.
SHE WAS JUST 18 WHEN DIRECTOR
BRETT RATNER INVITED AN OLDER
WOMAN TO HAVE SEX WITH PAGE TO
MAKE HER REALIZE GAY...
PAGE DESCRIBED BEING HARASSED
AND ASSAULTED...
>>> NOW, LAST YEAR, LOUIS C.K.
EARNED AN ESTIMATED $52 MILLION
U.S., MORE THAN HALF OF THAT
FROM TWO NETFLIX SPECIALS.
TODAY, NETFLIX CALLED DOWN HIS
NEXT SPECIAL.
FX CUT HIM OUT OF THE SERIES HE
PRODUCED AND THE NEW FILM WILL
NOT BE RELEASED.
ALSO THIS WEEK.
BB CANCELLED A STORY OF
WESTWICK.
THERE ARE SO MANY MEN UNDER
SUSPICION.
LET'S GO THROUGH IT.
THE PRODUCER JAMES TOBACK.
KEVIN SPACEY, JEREMY PIVEN,
DUSTIN HOFFMAN, ANDY DICK, AND
MAGICIAN DAVID BLAINE.
THE SHEER VOLUME HAS FORCED THE
LA DISTRICT ATTORNEY TO FORM A
SPECIAL TASK FORCE OF VETERAN
PROSECUTORS TO INVESTIGATE
SEXUAL ABUSE IN THE
ENTERTAINMENT INDUSTRY AND
REACHES INTO CANADA.
MONTREAL POLICE SET UP A HOTLINE
LAST MONTH TO REPORT SEXUAL
ASSAULT IN A FEW WEEKS, 463
CALLS.
THE POLICE HAVE NOW OPENED 98
CRIMINAL INVESTIGATIONS.
>>> IN THE POLITICAL ARENA, AN
ALABAMA REPUBLICAN STANDS
ACCUSED OF SEXUALLY PREYING ON
UNDER AGE GIRLS.
SOME SUPPORTERS STILL RALLY
AROUND ROY MOORE AND THE RUN FOR
THE SENATE.
A STATE OFFICIAL DEFENDED MOORE
BY CITING COUPLES IN THE BIBLE
WITH A BIG AGE DIFFERENCE
INCLUDING MARY AND JOSEPH.
LYNDSAY DUNCOMBE LOOKED INTO WHY
PEOPLE ARE DEFENDING WHAT SEEMS
INDEFENSIBLE.
>> I BELIEVE IN THE SECOND
AMENDMENT.
>> Reporter: LONG BEFORE THIS,
THERE WAS THIS.
THAT IS THEN ALABAMA CHIEF
JUSTICE ROY MOORE.
PERSONALLY INSTALLING A GRANITE
MONUMENT TO THE TEN COMMANDMENTS
IN THE COURTHOUSE.
HE LOST HIS JOB.
BUT BECAME A POPULOUS HERO TO A
FACTION OF ALABAMA EVANGELICALS.
THEY APPLAUDED WHEN AGAIN THE
CHIEF JUSTICE MOORE DEFIED THE
SUPREME COURT AND REFUSED TO
ALLOW SAME SEX MARRIAGES.
BUT DEFENDING HIM NOW?
>> I AM WORKING ON 31 YEARS AND
I STILL DON'T UNDERSTAND.
>> Reporter: JOHN ARCHIBALD IS A
LONG TIME ALABAMA JOURNALIST.
>> SO MANY OF ROY MOORE'S
SUPPORTERS ARE EVANGELICAL.
THEY ARE RELIGIOUS.
IS IT SURPRISING TO YOU THAT AT
LEAST SOME OF THEM ARE DEFEND
BEING HIM IN THE FACE OF THE
ALLEGATIONS?
>> Interview: IN SOME WAYS IT IS
STUNNING.
NOT EVERYONE IS.
THERE ARE A SELECT FEW ROY MOORE
SUPPORTERS WHO SAY WE DON'T CARE
IF THESE ALLEGATIONS ARE TRUE.
PART OF IT IS THE STATE OF THE
COUNTRY AND THE WORLD.
IN THAT OUR POLITICS IS SO
DIVIDED AND DIVISIVE THAT MANY
PEOPLE, AND WE ARE THE EPICENTER
OF THIS HERE IN ALABAMA, I WOULD
SAY, TEND TO BE MORE OBSESSED
WITH THE POLITICAL LEANINGS THAN
WE ARE VIRTUALLY ANYTHING ELSE.
>> Reporter: WHEN WE TALK ABOUT
THE PARTISANSHIP, WE ARE NOT
TALKING ABOUT THE TRADITIONAL
REPUBLICAN, DEMOCRATIC DIVIDE.
>> MANY SAY IT IS A CONSPIRACY
TO DEFAME MORE IN 30 DAYS BEFORE
AN ELECTION.
THE QUESTION IS WHETHER IT IS A
CONSPIRACY ORCHESTRATED BY
DEMOCRATS OR A CONSPIRACY
ORCHESTRATED BY ESTABLISHMENT
RE
[contemporary]
Reporter: And over on the
some place else side
maybe you'll find you're
somebody else
which is plenty
to worry about,
even if you happen to feel
pretty good at the time.
But you live in a town.
Any town.
And you spend most of your time
as if you know
what it's all about.
You know where you're going.
Really you don't know because
it's the town that's going
and you're just along
for the ride.
[stops]
[no audio]
[fast drum beats]
oh sinnerman
where you gonna run to?
all on that day
I run to the sea
the sea would be a boilin'
all on that day
run to the sky
the sky would be a pourin'
all on that day
oh sinnerman
where you gonna run to?
TOGETHER IN ORDER TO EFFECTIVELY
HEAL WHAT THE CRISIS HAPPENING
ON THE GROUND.
>> Andrew: LET'S GET CONCRETE.
YOU CALL IT A PUBLIC HEALTH
CRISIS.
YOU HAVE FALLEN SHORT OF CALLING
IT A PUBLIC HEALTH EMERGENCY.
IS THAT COULD COME DOWN THE PIPE
THAT WOULD OPEN UP RESOURCES
ACROSS THE NATION?
>> WE MADE IT VERY CLEAR OVER
THE PAST MONTHS, I HAVE BEEN
HEALTH MINISTER, IT IS A
NATIONAL PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS.
WE ARE NOT CALLING IT AN
EMERGENCY BECAUSE REALLY AND
TRULY IT WOULD NOT PROVIDE ME
WITH MORE LEVERS OR TOOLS TO
WORK WITH ON THE GROUND.
WE RECOGNIZE IT IS A VERY
SERIOUS SITUATION.
WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE ARE LOSING
AN AWFUL LOT OF PEOPLE.
AND THE COLLATERAL DAMAGE ON THE
GROUND IS HUGE FOR FAMILIES,
FRIENDS AND SERVICE PROVIDERS.
>> Andrew: SO AGAIN, I GUESS THE
QUESTION IS, WHAT MORE CAN WE
DO?
WE SPOKE TO A NUMBER OF PEOPLE
WHO STARTED TO THINK THAT MAYBE
THE WAY FORWARD IS TO
DECRIMINALIZE DRUG USE.
BEYOND MARIJUANA.
WHAT IS YOUR ANSWER TO THAT?
>> OUR GOVERNMENT HAS MADE IT
VERY CLEAR WE HAVE NO INTENTION
OF DECRIMINALIZING DRUGS.
OR ANY MORE DRUGS AT THIS TIME.
WHAT WE ARE LOOKING AT, THOUGH,
HOWEVER IS TO CONTINUE TO WORK
TOGETHER IN CLOSE COLLABORATION
WITH ALL LEVELS OF GOVERNMENT.
>> Andrew: THE QUESTION IS, I
MEAN, AT WHAT POINT DOES THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SAY, LOOK,
THINGS HAVE GOTTEN SO BAD, WE
NEED TO DO SOMETHING DRASTIC
BEYOND SIMPLY CONTINUING WHAT WE
ARE DOING?
>> AGAIN, WHEN I WAS NAMED
HEALTH MINISTER LAST MONTH, I
WAS ABLE TO GO TO VANCOUVER
ACTUALLY AND GO VISIT THE
DOWNTOWN EAST SIDE JUST TO SEE
EXACTLY WHAT WAS HAPPENING
THERE.
I MET WITH INDIVIDUALS THAT WERE
LIVING WITH SUBSTANCE ABUSE
ISSUES.
I ALSO MET WITH MANY SERVICE
PROVIDERS.
ALSO MET WITH POLICE OFFICERS
AND FRONT LINE INTERVENERS TO
GET A REAL PICTURE OF WHAT WAS
GOING ON DOWN THERE.
AGAIN, AS INDICATED, WE
RECOGNIZE THERE IS NO ONE
SOLUTION TO EFFECTIVELY DEAL
WITH THIS.
WE DO KNOW WE HAVE TO WORK
TOGETHER.
WE HAVE TO DO ALL THAT WE CAN TO
PUT OUR ENERGY FORTH IN ORDER TO
EFFECTIVELY HEAL THE SITUATION.
BECAUSE WHEN WE LOSE ONE LIFE,
WE RECOGNIZE THAT IT IS
AFFECTING MANY FAMILIES, MANY
MUNICIPALITIES.
AND THE MORE WE CAN DO TO HEAL
WITH THIS, THE BETTER IT WILL
BE.
>> Andrew: WE HAVE TO LEAVE IT
THERE MINISTER.
THANK YOU FOR TAKING THE TIME.
>>> I WILL HAND THINGS OVER TO
YOU, IAN.
I KNOW FROM YOUR REPORTING ON
THE SUBJECT, THERE ARE A LOT OF
PEOPLE FRUSTRATED AND WONDERING
WHAT THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
WOULD BE WILLING TO DO IF THE
STATUS QUO CONTINUES.
I GUESS THAT IS AN ONGOING
QUESTION.
>> Ian: AFTER OUR COVERAGE
YESTERDAY, I GOT A LOT OF TWEETS
AND E-MAILS AND PEOPLE ARE
DIVIDED ON THE ISSUE OF
LEGALIZING HEROIN AND COCAINE.
ONE THING IS BEYOND DISPUTE.
A LOT OF PEOPLE ARE DYING,
SPECIFICALLY IN BRITISH
COLUMBIA.
IF THOSE LIVES MATTER,
GOVERNMENTS HAVE TO TRY TO COME
UP WITH DIFFERENT STRATEGIES OF
SOME SORT.
>>> TOMORROW ROSEMARY AND I WILL
COVER THE CEREMONY HERE IN
OTTAWA.
CANADA'S WAR DEAD ARE REMEMBERED
OVERSEAS.
IN BELGIUM, THEY MARKED A
DEFINING MOMENT IN CANADIAN
HISTORY.
THIS TORCH LIGHT PROCESSION
TRACED THE FINAL ROUTE OF THE
MONEY FIRST WORLD WAR BATTLE OF
PASSIONDALE.
IT WAS 100 YEARS AGO TODAY THAT
THE BATTLE ENDED.
CANADA SHOWED WHAT IT COULD DO.
AT A GREAT COST.
4,000 CANADIANS DIED.
TAKING THE VILLAGE BACK.
FOR SOME REMEMBRANCE DAY IS
LITERAL.
THEY ONLY HAVE A MEMORY OF A
LOVED ONE KILLED IN SERVICE.
YOU WILL MEET THE CANADIANS
DIGGING UP THE PAST TO TRY TO
GIVE THE FAMILIES CLOSURE.
>> I FIND IT IS IMPORTANT
BECAUSE IT RETURNS THEIR
IDENTITY TO THEM.
THEY ARE NO LONGER MISSING.
THEY ARE NO LONGER F
Reporter: Morning glory
did its work.
The gully was over run
to waylay open to Ortona.
In to this town
the Germans fell back.
And these were Germans of the
first parachute division.
The town would be defended.
The worst was still ahead.
[explosions]
[rapid gun fire]
Man: We used to say,
it was true,
the German was a good soldier.
But then as soon as our chaps.
That's not true here.
Here we fight
until we kill them.
They're Germans but I
admire their guts.
I'll say this.
I'm very proud because
my men are
better than the Germans here.
Remember, we attack,
they defend,
but how they defend.
[rapid gunfire]
[gun shots]
Today I spent several
hours in Ortona.
It wasn't hell, it was
the courtyard of hell.
It was a maelstrom of noise,
of pot-splitting steel.
Our tanks in the square
seem to be ripping
the town to pieces.
And the enemy's empty tank
shells and mortars
were crashing in to the
buildings everywhere.
[singing]
joyful and triumphant
oh come ye, oh come ye
to Bethlehem
Reporter: They were still in
Ortona when it was Christmas.
From the killing,
the men withdrew by turn
to celebrate the day.
[singing continues]
oh come let us adore him,
oh come let us adore him
Reporter:
The rest was short.
The return to the murderous
streets immediate.
[rapid gunfire]
[explosion]
Reporter: They called it
Little Stalingrad.
And from their
experience here
would instruct
the Allied armies
on the craft
of street fighting.
[bell tolls]
This is Peter Stursberg
of the CBC
reporting from the
Italian front.
For the dead of Ortona,
the bell of its cathedral,
the cathedral of St. Thomas
the apostle tolls.
For the Canadians who died
in taking the town
and for the dust and ashes
of the cathedral itself,
the bell tolls.
[bagpipes play]
Reporter: The soldiers of Canada
would move on to fight again.
For those whose home
had been Ortona,
the ordeal of war
at last was over.
[bell tolls]
>> Ian: THAT IS THE TOMB OF THE
UNKNOWN SOLDIER RIGHT BY THE
NATIONAL WAR MEMORIAL IN OTTAWA.
REMAINS OF A SOLDIER NEVER
IDENTIFIED.
NOT TOO FAR FROM WHERE WE ARE,
THERE ARE PEOPLE DEDICATED TO
FUTURE FACES AND NAMES TO THE
LOST SOLDIERS.
NAHLAH AYED MET A TEAM DIGGING
INTO THE UNKNOWN.
TO BRING LIFE TO THOSE WHO GAVE
IT SO MANY YEARS AGO.
>> Reporter: THE INEVITABLE
INVASION OF PROGRESS.
THEY ARE WARRIORS OF THE FUTURE.
MAKING INROADS WHERE THERE WERE
ONCE TRENCHES.
MOVING ON, AS INEVITABLY WE TRY
TO DO.
EVEN AFTER DEVASTATING WAR.
AND YET, JUST AS INEVITABLY, THE
PULL OF THE PAST IN FRANCE IS
JUST AS HARD TO REPEL.
>> Interview: THEY BROUGHT OUT A
LOT OF MACHINE GUNS AND
ARTILLERY.
>> Reporter: IT BRINGS THOUSANDS
HERE.
KEEN TO UNEARTH HISTORY.
AND THE MEMORIES OF THE MISSING.
YOU ONLY HAVE TO VISIT SOME OF
THE WAR GRAVES HERE TO
APPRECIATE JUST HOW MANY
SOLDIERS DIED IN ANONYMITY.
IT IS BELIEVED SOME 27,000
CANADIANS ARE STILL MISSING IN
ACTION WITH NO KNOWN GRAVE.
THE LEGACY OF TWO WORLD WARS,
AND THE FULL-TIME PREOCCUPATION
OF ONE WOMAN.
SARAH COMES TO FRANCE TWICE A
YEAR.
A FORENSIC ANTHROPOLOGIST.
HER OFFICE HERE IS THE
COMMONWEALTH WAR GRAVE
COMMISSION.
HER JOB IS TO PULL THE PAST INTO
THE PRESENT.
AND IDENTIFY FALLEN SOLDIERS
THEY STILL FIND HERE TO THIS
DAY.
FOR ME, PERSONALLY, I FIND IT IS
IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT RETURNS
THEIR IDENTITY TO THEM.
THEY ARE NO LONGER MISSING.
THEY ARE NO LONGER FACELESS.
THEY ARE NO LONGER NAMELESS.
>> Reporter: WE WERE NOT ALLOWED
TO FILM THE SOLDIERS' REMAINS.
SHE USED A PLASTIC MODEL TO
EXPLAIN WHAT SHE DOES.
>> I LAY EVERYTHING OUT IN
ANATOMICAL ORDER.
I SEE DO I HAVE DUPLICATES.
AND WHAT MARKERS THAT I CAN LOOK
AT THAT HELP ME GET AN AGE AND
SEX.
THE ONE THAT I -- WHEN I HAVE
IT, I GET EXCITED ABOUT IS THE
CLAVICLE HERE.
THAT ONE IS THE LAST TO FUSE IN
THE ENTIRE BODY.
THAT ALLOWS -- GIVES ME AN IDEA
OF OVER 30, UNDER 30.
>> Reporter: ONE FIND, NEAR THE
NEWLY BUILT PRISON CAME WITH
CRUCIAL CLUES.
>> Interview: WE FOUND A BOOT.
WE FOUND A BAYONET.
A BUTTON HERE.
THANKFULLY WAS LEGIBLE.
SO THERE IS CANADIAN SCOTTISH
YOU CAN READ AROUND.
16th BATTALION AT THE VERY TOP.
>> Reporter: EVERY STORY STARTS
WITH A PHONE CALL TO THE WAR
GRAVE COMMISSION.
WITHIN 15 MINUTES, A TEAM IS ON
THE WAY.
LAST YEAR, IN JUNE, HE GOT A
CALL WHEN THE CREWS MADE A
DISCOVERY.
>> Interview: WHICH IS RIGHT ON
THE FRONT LINE, REALLY, ON THE
GERMAN...
>> Reporter: THIS WILL BE
RETURNED TO THE FAMILY.
>> Reporter: HE FOUND A
TOOTHBRUSH, THE TOOTHPASTE.
THE REMAINS AND AN UNUSUAL
NUMBER OF ARTIFACTS WERE
REMARKABLY WELL PRESERVED.
FOR AN INVESTIGATOR, IT WAS
GOLD.
>> Interview: IT WAS FOUND ON
HIS FINGER.
THIS IS THE SIGNET RING.
IT CAME OUT OF THE GROUND LIKE
THAT.
WE DID NOT CLEAN THAT.
FOR US, WE WERE LUCKY BECAUSE WE
ALSO FOUND AN IDENTIFICATION
DISC.
SO THIS NOW HAS SOME CORROSION
AND DAMAGE, CAN YOU READ SGTHW.
AND CATH FOR CATHOLIC DOWN AT
THE BOTTOM.
YOU DO HAVE TO PUT UP THAT WALL,
I GUESS, TO MAKE SURE YOU
JUST -- YOU VIEW THEM AS
INDIVIDUAL CASES TO BE ABLE TO
GET THE WORK DONE.
THE HARD WORK BEGINS IN OTTAWA
AT THE CASUALTY IDENTIFICATION
UNIT.
LOOKING AT OLD MAPS, THE BATTLE
AND THE UNITS INVOLVED WHERE THE
REMAINS WERE FOUND.
>> NAMES OF EVERY SOLDIER THAT
DIED.
>> Reporter: IT IS THE CASUALTY
LIST, AND THEN WAR RECORDS TO
COMPARE THE MEASUREMENTS.
ONCE AN IDENTITY IS CONFIRMED,
IT IS EVERY POSSIBLE MEANS TO
FIND NEXT OF KIN.
THEN THEY MAKE A PHONE CALL THAT
CAN CHANGE LIVES.
>> Interview: THEY WERE HOPING
SIMPLY BY TAKING HILL 70, IT
COULD CONVINCE THE GERMANS TO
EVACUATE.
>> Reporter: IN AN OVERGROWN
BATTLEFIELD IN FRANCE, THEY ARE
LEARNING ABOUT THE BATTLE OF
HILL 70.
A LITTLE KNOWN CANADIAN LED
OFFENSIVE AGAINST GERMAN FORCES
100 YEARS LATER.
>> THE 16th BATTALION, TO THEIR
RIGHT.
>> Reporter: JACK KENNEDY IS A
HISTORY TEACHER FROM BOSTON
WHOSE CANADIAN GREAT UNCLE DIED
IN THE BATTLE.
ONE DAY KENNEDY GOT A PHONE CALL
SUGGESTING HIS UNCLE HAD BEEN
FOUND.
HE WAS SURE IT WAS A HOAX.
>> Interview: THERE WAS A PART
OF ME THAT WAS A LITTLE BIT
CYNICAL.
THAT WAS WAITING FOR, OKAY, NOW
THIS IS GOING TO HAPPEN.
YOU KNOW, YOU NEED TO MAKE A
DOWN PAYMENT ON A FLIGHT TO
PARIS, PLEASE FORWARD US A
CHEQUE FOR -- AND WE ARE WAITING
FOR THAT OTHER SHOE TO DROP.
>> Reporter: LORRAINE CAME FROM
MANITOBA TO TRACE HER GREAT
UNCLE'S FINAL DAYS.
ALL OF 22 WHEN HE WAS KILLED.
ALSO IN THE BATTLE OF HILL 70.
>> Interview: NO ONE REALLY
TALKED ABOUT IT.
I KNEW THERE WAS A PICTURE
THERE.
ALL I KNEW IT WAS A SOLDIER ON
THE WALL.
I DON'T THINK WE EVER KNEW WHAT
A SOLDIER DID IN THOSE DAYS.
>> Reporter: ALL THAT IS LEFT IS
THAT PICTURE AND A LETTER.
THAT BROKE THE NEWS OF HIS
DEATH.
KILLED IN ACTION ON AUGUST 15TH,
1917.
WHEN IT IS POSSIBLE, A CROSS
WILL BE ERECTED IN HIS MEMORY.
IN THE INTERIM, SHE KEPT HER
UNCLE'S MEMORY ALIVE.
SO WHEN A PHONE CALL CAME ASKING
HER TO DONATE DNA TO HELP
IDENTIFY AN UNKNOWN SOLDIER, SHE
DIDN'T HESITATE.
>> Interview: I SAID BY ALL
MEANS.
IF IT WILL HELP.
I SAID AFTER 100 YEARS, I SAID,
HOW IS IT POSSIBLE.
ANYTHING IS POSSIBLE NOW, I
GUESS.
>> Reporter: IN THE MAIL, SHE
GOT ONE OF THESE TO COLLECT A
DNA SAMPLE.
HERE IT IS PURIFIED AND ANALYZED
TO CREATE A GENETIC PROFILE.
IT CAN BE COMPARED TO A POSSIBLE
RELATIVE.
THE RESULTS IN THE CASE ALLOWS
THE PROCESS TO PROCEED TO THE
FINAL STEPS.
THE REVIEW BOARD IS THE FINAL
HURDLE.
THEY HAVE TO BE UNANIMOUS.
IN HER CASE, IT DID NOT TAKE
LONG AND SHE WAS CALLED THAT
AFTERNOON.
>> Interview: I SAID, WE
CONFIRMED THAT THE REMAINS OF
INTEREST ARE IN FACT REGINALD
JOSEPH JOHNSON.
>> Interview: THANK YOU, I SAID
FOR ALL OF YOUR WORK.
WHAT A GREAT CHRISTMAS PRESENT.
>> Reporter: AT THE COMMONWEALTH
WAR GRAVE COMMISSION, THIS IS
THE ULTIMATE AIM, TO ALWAYS PUT
NAMES TO THE HEADSTONES AS
SOLDIERS ARE LAID TO REST.
MAJOR HAROLD SHAWNESSY AND
PRIVATE JOHNSON HAVE THEIR OWN.
THEY WILL BE BURIED WITH THE
BOOTS IN WHICH THEY SERVED.
>> EVERYBODY HAVE A LAND TO
HOLD?
>> Reporter: THE FAMILY NOW ON
THEIR OWN EXTRAORDINARY JOURNEY,
TO THE SAME PLACES, BUT LOOKING
VERY DIFFERENT NOW.
IT IS EMOTIONALLY DIFFICULT TO
WALK IN THE FOOTSTEPS OF FAMILY
NEAR HILL 70.
>> JOHNSON WOULD HAVE BEEN 300
YARDS OR MORE THAT WAY.
>> Reporter: WHERE JOHNSON FELL
WHICH IS NOW NEAR TO A PRISON,
THE PARKING LOT WHERE SHAWNESSY
DIED AT THE FRONT LINE.
>> Interview: MY MOTHER AND MY
AUNT, WHO WOULD HAVE BEEN HIS
NIECES, IT TAKES TIME TO
PROCESS.
>> HERE IS THE IDENTIFICATION
DISC.
>> Reporter: PART OF THE
EXPERIENCE, THE OVERWHELMING
SURPRISE OF INHERITING THEIR
UNCLE'S BELONGINGS.
>> SOME COIN.
>> Reporter: IF YOU WONDER, IT
IS EXACTLY WHY LOCKYER WEARS THE
GLASSES.
>> THANK YOU.
>> Reporter: NEARLY 100 YEARS TO
THE DAY THEIR TURN HAD FINALLY
COME.
AND TO HOLD A PROPER BURIAL,
WHEN IT IS POSSIBLE HAS BEEN
KEPT.
>> Interview: IT WAS MY DUTY.
WE KNOW WHERE HE IS AND WHAT
HAPPENED TO HIM, AND HE IS BEING
BURIED WITH GREAT RESPECT AND
DIGNITY.
AND THAT'S IMPORTANT.
>> Interview: CANADA CARES.
YOU KNOW, AND THE FACT THAT
AFTER 100 YEARS, CANADA COULD
TURN AROUND AND GO TO THESE
PARTICULAR LENGTHS TO PUT THIS
TOGETHER, I THOUGHT WAS
INCREDIBLY IMPRESSIVE.
>> Reporter: AND INTENSELY
PERSONAL.
TO LOCKYER TOO.
HER GRANDFATHER FOUGHT IN THE
SECOND WORLD WAR.
HER REGRET, NOT ASKING HIM MORE
QUESTIONS.
SHE NOW FINDS JOY IN PROVIDING
ANSWERS.
>> Interview: THE CANADIAN
MILITARY HISTORY, CANADA'S
HISTORY, AND THEN INDIVIDUAL
FAMILY FAMILIES, THEIR PERSONAL
HISTORY AS WELL.
THAT IS KIND OF -- AS YOU CAN
TELL, I AM STARTING TO GET
EMOTIONAL WITH THAT.
IT IS HUGE.
>> Reporter: NAHLAH AYED, CBC
NEWS, FRANCE.
>> Ian: WELL, TOMORROW, THIS
YEAR'S SILVER CROSS MOTHER WILL
LAY A WREATH BEHIND ME.
IN MEMORY OF THE MOTHERS WHO
LOST CHILDREN IN SERVICE OF THIS
COUNTRY.
I SPOKE WITH HER A FEW DAYS AGO
ABOUT HER DAD WHO SERVED IN THE
SECOND WORLD WAR.
AND ABOUT HER SON WHO SERVED IN
SOMALIA BUT NEVER CAME BACK.
>> Interview: IT WAS AN
ACCIDENT.
THAT IS THE HARD PART.
TO FIND OUT THAT HIS BEST FRIEND
HAD HAD AN
Duncan McCue: The world wars.
Korea. Vietnam.
Wars far removed from
Canada's first peoples.
White man's battles,
some said,
on battlefields
in foreign lands.
But the wars reached in to
Indian, Inuit and Métis homes
across the country.
Aboriginal men and women
volunteered in the thousands.
Many sacrificed their Indian
status to do so.
Many sacrificed their lives.
Over 6,000 Aboriginal people
joined the armed forces
during World War II.
For many, the threat of Nazism
expanding to this country
seemed very, very real.
But even while
they were fighting
fascism on the front lines,
Aboriginal soldiers were
fighting racism at home.
Harry and Theresa both
grew up in the Prairies.
Both in Métis settlements on
the fringes of white society.
The Métis knew about battles.
Their enemies were poverty,
tuberculosis,
and indifference.
We'd get up at 6:00
in the morning,
go to bed at
whenever the sun goes down
just to make a living --
just to put food on the table.
There was no money involved.
There was nothing.
No, there was nothing
there for us.
I come home crying once
and I told my mother
and she says what's
the matter with you?
You know?
And I says well they beat me up
outside, they're after me.
And she says what for?
I says well they call me dirty,
stinking Indian.
And he says go on away,
you know.
You tell them kids
over there that
your great grandfather
was pure white.
Duncan: While Canada ignored
Aboriginal calls for help,
the Aboriginal people
answered Canada's.
Some were thirsty
for adventure.
Some felt a duty
to defend the Queen
who had signed their treaties.
Others wanted three
square meals a day.
Theresa: Our whole
community enlisted.
All the guys were gone.
There was not very many
young people left.
The older guys went too.
I mean the married people went.
Our community was devastated.
Harry: My father says well,
he says you're a man.
You're a soldier.
You're fighting
for your country.
That's the words that he said.
And he dug in his pocket,
pulled out 52 cents,
put it on the table
and says now go and get
a bottle of Catawba wine.
[laughs]
Duncan:
For 18 year old Harry,
who's father Joseph
was a World War I vet,
the war brought the first
taste of alcohol
and the first taste
of equality.
Harry: It was the first time in
my life I had any clothes
that I could talk about.
So, and they give me boots
and they give me soap
and they give me a towel,
and all them things that
help us every day.
Duncan: Theresa's brother
George Dion
enlisted immediately.
When Theresa signed up,
18 years old,
she didn't want anyone
to know she was Métis.
Theresa: If you told anybody
you were Métis,
that you weren't accepted
in to their circle,
and we always strived
to be accepted.
Of course.
Duncan: Theresa served
in the women's corps
posted in Alberta.
Harry went overseas,
spent two years in England.
[♪♪♪]
>> Ian: IT REALLY IS INTERESTING
TO SEE HOW THE PHOTOS COME TO
LIFE.
IT IS ONE OF HUNDREDS OF PHOTOS
FROM THE FIRST WORLD WAR.
THE VIMY FOUNDATION RECENTLY...
THE DIANA ABEL WILL LAY A WREATH
AT THE MEMORIAL TOMORROW.
REPRESENTING THE MOTHERS WHO
LOST A CHILD IN SERVICE.
ABEL LOST HER SON IN SOMALIA,
DURING ONE OF CANADA'S MOST
CONTROVERSIAL PEACEKEEPING
MISSIONS.
WE SAT DOWN IN HER HOME IN
BRAMPTON, ONTARIO, TO REMEMBER
HER SON MICHAEL.
>> Interview: THE MOST IMPORTANT
THING IS HERE IS -- THIS WAS
PRESENTED TO ME AT THE FUNERAL.
IT IS TATTERED AND TORN.
I ALWAYS SAID THEY WOULD
NEVER -- BECAUSE OF THE SOMALIA
INCIDENT.
>> GOOD EVENING, THERE WAS A
BARRAGE OF QUESTIONS TODAY ABOUT
THE CONDUCT OF CANADIAN
PEACEKEEPERS IN SOMALIA.
OPPOSITION M.P.S SAID IT IS
CLEAR THE OPERATION IS IN
CRISIS.
>> SINCE FEBRUARY, FOUR SOMALIS
HAVE BEEN KILLED BY CANADIANS
AND TWO ARE INVESTIGATED AS
HOMICIDES.
>> MUCH OF THE WORK WAS SUPERB,
THEY SAVED THOUSANDS.
AND YET THE SCANDALS WERE SOME
OF THE MOST SERIOUS AND UGLIEST
IN THE RECENT MILITARY HISTORY.
AND MANY WHO SERVE THERE
RETURNED...
>> Ian: WHAT SHOULD CANADIANS
KNOW ABOUT THE MISSION?
>> Interview: THEY DID THEIR
JOB.
THEY DID THEIR JOB UNDER VERY
DIFFICULT CIRCUMSTANCES.
AND MY SON'S JOB, THEY WERE AT
THE AIRPORT, ENSURING THE PLANES
COULD LAND.
BECAUSE IT WAS A HUMANITARIAN
MISSION AS WELL.
SO THEY HAD TO GET THE FOOD FROM
THEIR TO THE AREA, WHICH THEY
DID.
>> Ian: THE PICTURE OF YOUR SON
WITH THE KIDS IN SOMALIA.
THEY LOOK -- THEY LOOK HAPPY.
>> Interview: OH, YEAH.
HE USED TO GIVE THEM THINGS.
WE USED TO SEND THINGS TO HIM.
>> CANDY AND COOKIES AND
DIFFERENT THINGS LIKE THAT.
THE LAST BOX I SENT HIM WAS
T-SHIRTS.
IT NEVER GOT TO HIM.
THAT WAS FOR THE KIDS.
WE FOUND OUT IT WAS AN ACCIDENT.
THAT WAS THE HARD PART TO FIND
OUT THAT HIS BEST FRIEND HAD HAD
AN ACCIDENT WITH HIS GUN AND HE
WAS DEAD.
HE WASN'T COMING HOME.
HE LOVED HISTORY.
HE DID NOT COME HOME DURING R&R
FROM SOMALIA, HE WENT TO SEE THE
SITES.
HE LOVED CARS.
HE LOVED MOTORCYCLES.
HE HAD A BIG HARLEY.
HE LOVED THAT.
HE LIKED THE INDEPENDENCE OF IT.
HE LIKED THE OPEN ROAD.
MY GRANDSON, JOHN, HE WILL BE
ESCORTING ME ON NOVEMBER THE
11th.
HE IS THE SPITTING IMAGE OF
MICHAEL.
AND HE WANTS TO JOIN -- HE
APPLIED AND WANTS TO BE IN THE
MILITARY AS WELL.
>> Ian: HOW DO YOU FEEL OF THE
PROSPECT OF YOUR GRANDSON BEING
IN THE MILITARY?
>> Interview: SCARY.
SCARY.
MY FATHER WENT OFF TO WORLD WAR
II.
MY HUSBAND WAS.
IT IS A SENSE OF PRIDE, I THINK,
TO THINK THAT THE FAMILY
BUSINESS.
HE IS GOING INTO THE FAMILY
>> Ian: AS PEOPLE WELCOME YOU ON
NOVEMBER THE 11th IN OTTAWA, AS
THEY SEE YOU AS THE SILVER CROSS
MOTHER, CARRY OUT YOUR DUTIES,
WHAT SHOULD THEY BE THINKING.
>> Interview: THINKING THAT THE
YOUNG MEN AND WOMEN PUT THEIR
LIVES ON THE LINE FOR CANADA.
THEY DO THEIR JOBS.
THEY DO THE BEST THEY CAN UNDER
SOMETIMES VERY DIFFICULT
CIRCUMSTANCES.
BUT THEY DO THEIR JOB.
>> Ian: I ENJOYED SO MUCH OF THE
CONVERSATION.
IN PARTICULAR, THAT PHRASE THAT
SHE USED THAT HER FATHER, HER
HUSBAND AND HER SON AND PROBABLY
HER GRANDSON AS WELL ALL PART OF
THE FAMILY BUSINESS.
>>> WE TELL YOU HOW YOU CAN TAKE
PART IN THE CBC
[audience applause]
It pleases me to be here
to give this award to Gordon.
I've known Gordon
for a long time.
And I know he's
been offered this award before
but he has never accepted it
because he wanted me to come
and give it to him.
So...
[audience laughter]
Anyway, he's somebody of a rare
talent and all that
and here's a video clip
now of his
recent and not so recent
achievements.
Right now we're delighted
to welcome to our show
our very good friend, the
fabulous Gordon Lightfoot.
[applause]
["Saturday Clothes"]
I feel a little sad
to watch them leave
but I'll be cool because
I don't believe
the railroad men grew restless
for to hear the hammers ring
their minds were overflowing
with the visions of their day
and many a fortune won and
lost and many a debt to pay
just like an old time movie
about a ghost from
a wishing well
in a castle dark
or a fortress strong
with chains upon my feet
you know that ghost is me
and I will never be set free
as long as I'm a ghost
you can see
the church bell chimed
till it rang 29 times
for each man on the
Edmund Fitzgerald
the legend lives on
from the Chippewa on down
[applause]
[applause continue]
Thank you.
Can I leave now when you make
your speech? I think I will.
[applause]
[applause fade]
Okay!
Alright, here it is.
One grateful guy from Orillia.