it's number 465 one account at amount of
molnar versus burden prize have been
sworn in you may be seated and have a
seat you watch mr. Mullin are you and
the defendant were married we've been
divorced for a long time ten years yes
ma'am and you have two children yes I
bet two papers and this is what I gather
your divorce was amicable and you agreed
on child support order in the amount of
$1,000 a month month and that was
satisfactory and was paid for many years
right and then the defendant met and
wanted to marry and relocate so far
correct yes ma'am
and at that point you had been divorced
for eight years yes ma'am and you asked
mr. molnár if he would consent to your
relocating with his children that's
correct because you wanted to marry and
your husband lived out of the
jurisdiction
mr. Molnar agreed and up until that time
he had seen the children yes ma'am but
he said if you're going to move with the
children I want a reduction in my child
support because it's going to be more
expensive for me to visit them yes ma'am
and you agreed yes ma'am to reduce his
child support and half to five hundred
dollars a month in what month and year
was that mrs. burden July of 2007 and
for how long did mr. molnár mrs. burden
pay you the $500 a month for two years
Your Honor I'd like to make a point that
I not only paid that but I paid above
and beyond that amount give me an
example mr. Mullin I was paying her $200
extra knowing that the kids are
expensive
I also that's the minimum that I do I
was paying for their phones insurance
college funds when you say you were
paying for their phones you paid those
directly yes ma'am he did pay for their
cell phones as far as paying to in just
a minute did he ever pay you an amount
over the $500 a month I think once
possibly twice but there was numerous
times he paid me less than $500 that's
absolutely not true
and that can be proven
okay I may ask you to do that okay now
there came a time mrs. burden when you
decided that that agreement should no
longer be binding when was that was last
year January of 2009 the children were
getting older that it was more expensive
I felt it was time for so it was about a
year and a half later after your
agreement yes ma'am so within 18 months
of agreeing to allow him to reduce his
child support because he would move you
decided that that agreement should be
vacated
it wasn't the friendly agreement he
showed up the day before we moved and
said I'll let you move because there was
no problem with us moving fine and dandy
the day before we move we have
everything packed he shows up saying it
says in our degree you can't move in
order for you to move you got to cut my
child support in half so it was more
like a bribe and what am I gonna do I
said sure sure fine whatever okay so you
filed an application for increased child
support just an order that I can go
through the state where I wouldn't have
to call him every month and say hey it's
the 15th can you pay me my child support
and I see the application that you filed
yes ma'am Your Honor I wonder what this
is for modification I'll check all she
filed for was to have the amount and the
understand you mrs. burden what this is
going to tell me is all you are
requesting is that the order be made
payable through the course yes ma'am not
for any more money
I wanted something fair ah so you are
asking for more money that's what I say
they would have said five hundred that
would have been fine they'd be spurred
let's not play with each other you and I
don't be a passive-aggressive you
weren't looking to get less money you
were looking to get more money if they
felt that was fair that would have been
great burden you're playing with me
anyway here just a second because the
lawsuit is an interesting one
mr. molnár filed this application and
the date that was set was during the
week that he was remarrying and he asked
you to change the date yes and he was
given assurance that you would do
whatever was necessary
to change the date you went to court he
wasn't there you allowed the hearing to
continue and there was a child support
order that was made that was two and a
half times as much as your original
agreement and he had to get a lawyer to
overturn that default judgment because
he wasn't there and he wants you to
compensate him for the attorneys fees to
overturn the default judgment that's
what he's asking for that's what the
lawsuit is about you say he should have
changed his wedding date he should know
that was his his problem I read your
answer and you have a counterclaim you
say he's harassed you okay that's what
the lawsuits about so now I'm going to
read your application when you were
served with this he was served with it
on those are actually his papers he was
served April 16th
his wedding that wasn't until August 4th
we went to court on July 29th when did
he call you mrs. burden after he
deserved the paper he received the
papers okay aren't you and can you tell
me what the conversation was you tell me
what the company wanted to know what
that was but I'd already told him in
February expect these papers to come I'm
asking for a court order so I don't have
to call you every month and ask for my
child support okay
mr. Muldaur now it's your turn he was
served with these papers these papers
are very clear well the former wife told
you that she was merely asking for an
order to be made payable through the
courts so that she wouldn't have to call
you that's not what these papers said
the papers clearly say in English and
you look like an intelligent man so I'm
sure that you read and comprehend in
English that she is asking for a
modification of the order because the
circumstances of the children have
materially changed that it's been three
years since the order was last issued
that the court should modify the order
pursuant to the child support guidelines
and make an order for health insurance
so it doesn't just say here that the
order should be made payable through the
court it was requesting other relief
Judge Judy continues in a moment is what
you're saying that you haven't patented
or that he didn't deal people
Judy William Molnar says ex-wife Stacy
Burton owes for legal fees resulting
from a child support hearing that was
held during the week he got married
Stacy's countersuing for her Westman now
I assume that when you got these papers
any man who has anything to lose would
take these papers to an attorney
did you know ma'am why not well based on
our conversation she was very upset I've
always paid my child support on time
what was she upset about sir that she
even started this process well but she
started it right and she said she would
rectify it I want to remind you I was
out of work at the time too did not have
money to go hire an attorney don't tell
me all I want you to do was tell me what
she said to you don't give me a glow
that you have have it dismissed Savitch
told him no what did you tell he was
very well aware what I thought it was
aware of Miss burden I said I said Court
to get a child support order through the
court and insurance for the children so
you did not tell him that you would
either change the date or modify the or
I tried to call the Attorney General he
said you'd better take care of this you
better deal with this so I got on the
phone immediately as soon as we don't
know how to know it somebody says cheap
miss burden let's not play with me no so
what did you say to him after he said
you better take care of this I will call
the attorney general's office and the
connotation of that is that you would
take care of it by calling the attorney
general's office to change the date
because it was on our son's birthday I
didn't set the date so you told him you
would change the date I told him I would
try to change the date did you change
the date they said I don't know did you
change the date I couldn't did you call
him and tell him that you did not change
the date yes when did you call him and
tell him that you did not change the
date within 30 minutes what did you say
to him they will not change the date
I called absolutely not true who did you
speak to with the attorney general's
office mrs. burden I don't have a name
whoever answered the phone I explained
we had a court date that we needed to
get the date
and they said we don't change the dates
I don't have a name but I do know that
he called the Attorney General even they
testified oh no no no just a second I'm
asking you I don't have a name I didn't
know it was gonna be an issue at the
time well it turns out to be an issue
because there was a default judgment
that he had the default judgment
overturned which means a judge found
that at least someone had been misled
about whether or not there was going to
be a hearing your honor he was serve on
729 it to the sheriff at his front door
I don't playing you need to appear in
everywhere through there it says you
must appear you may get a default
judgment burden this matter was already
adjudicated before another judge who
overturned the default then I gave him
half of that child support back I wasn't
out for money just a second then it was
very easy you signed this document you
know you have to get your story straight
first you told me that all you wanted to
do was get the order paid through the
court then you say you told me well
that's really not true what I really
wanted was a fair order whatever the
court thought was fair and you told me
that you wanted an order for health
insurance so of it well you didn't tell
me that at the beginning madam I'm sorry
I just want what's fair for my children
look miss burden I understand that and
the law also provides that you should
have what's fair for your children but
what you don't do is you don't make an
agreement with them that allows you to
move out of the jurisdiction and a year
later sue him for increased child
support that smacks of being unfair now
I'm not getting into that because I
assume that he continues to pay the
child support that he at least agreed to
when the ax that you decided to move I
haven't gotten child support since
September not a penny
he's paid it he's paid the state but the
day that and I have the letter from the
judge the day that he judge was supposed
to sign our order it's noted you said
everything got put behind they say that
your sir is what you're saying that you
haven't gotten it or that he didn't pay
it I haven't got it well who cares about
that Megan Kerik mustn't listen to me
that has nothing to do with him to pay
me directly
she said no she wanted it this way she
can live with it this absolutely right
right birth next time absolutely right
he can't trust you
so has nothing to do with him you have a
beef take it up with the court he's not
going to send it to you directly I
wouldn't send it to you directly because
you weren't straight up with him go
ahead
Your Honor he had months to do either it
says right on their file an answer
within 20 days he did nothing this
burden he did I know he got married a
week after the court date madam you were
getting child support for eight years
you chose to modify the order and you
chose to modify an order in a way that
was certainly not anticipated by the
plaintiff when he said okay you want to
get married it's gonna make it more
difficult and more costly for me to see
my children so I have to be compensated
for that because I don't not going to
give you what I've been giving you and
it's gonna cost me more to see the
children and you agree to it and then a
year later you filed for a modification
more money and you were given as a
matter of fact at the default hearing
how much was the order that the judge
granted you one default 1390 and I gave
half just a second you didn't give it
back to him until he sued to have the
judgment overtax not true when did you
give it back to him I don't have the
canceled check it was as soon as he paid
it I gave him half of it back she did
that I mean that's fine why didn't you
tell the judge that that's an
unreasonable order when I went up there
that day they said how much are you
getting I said five hundred a month they
said well he made a hundred and
thirty-five thousand dollars in eight
months last year he should be paying you
more and I said I'd also like to have
insurance for my children because they
haven't had it in three months
all I'm asking you is you heard the
judge make an order mm-hmm right yes
ma'am at any time when the judge made
that order did you say it's really not a
reasonable order because I know that
he's not working now just I'm asking you
a question
no man right did you at any time say to
the judge he didn't come and because he
may have been under the impression that
I was going to change the date no
there's no way to change the date mr.
Millar do you have the order
I would like to look at it overturning
the default judgment yes ma'am I'd like
to take a look at it I have it right
here I'd like to see it
sir you paid an attorney a certain
amount of money right yes how much it's
to get the default judgment overturn
$7,900 did you ever not have health
insurance for your children no ma'am
is that right no it's not correct when
he lost his job in November he had
insurance through the end of the month
at that point he had the option to
choose Cobra he never invoked the Cobra
I took the children to the doctor I had
no insurance card no they were covered
under Cobra No show me the policy
listen part of my problem with awarding
you the full amount of the attorney's
fees is mr. Momo you're a pretty bright
guy and just as you got a lawyer when
things started to become a bit of a
sticky wicket if you would gotten an
attorney to appear for you on that date
and asked for continuance you would have
gotten it I had no reason to disbelieve
or she convinced me I did not need to
appear on numerous occasions I mean it
was an Academy Award performance let me
just tell you I was sold hook Landing
line & sinker knowing what was gonna
happen that day I don't work for an
attorney I'd never been to court I
didn't know what was gonna happen that
day I just rented the courts didn't
should get a divorce he had we got a
divorce the seconds did you have an
attorney during oh yeah we had a mr. it
was his gym buddy who wrote and
represented both of us first so he could
save money you agree miss burden don't
play a victim with me you were smart
enough lady to have to agree to a
reduced order of child support and to
petition the court a year later for an
increase in child support once you moved
from his perspective you agreed to
something and a year later you chose to
modify it because things in China I
don't think he's a crazy guy the only
problem is what you did cost him a lot
of money and that much better been spent
you know putting into children's college
fund not sending it to you he's trying
to use the children's college fund to
pay for his attorney he's that low
you have to pay for part of his attorney
because I think that he was misled mr.
burden now I'm going to hear your
counterclaim alright my counterclaim is
for harassment and assault
most recently he assaulted my husband in
the motor house and your husband I'm
interested in you he called me in August
when all this started instead I mean
after the hearing yes ma'am
go ahead and said did you hear about
that man killing his wife in Las Vegas
over child support and I said no I said
why and he goes I'm just letting you
know what else so that's what started I
had phone call after phone call after
phone call I have a log of how he's
called I have police reports I don't
want you to give me police reports I
want you to tell me when he called and
what he said you better get that
straightened out that's what he said
and I had that on recording is that what
he said to you yeah that's what he meant
that is not a threat and that's not
harassment but I believe that you did
low him into a sense of security that he
did not have to be present on 7:29 you
let the judge proceed with a hearing to
go into his income to modify the order
without saying a word and that madam as
far as I'm concerned as unfair
I think that mr. molnar had an
obligation and what he should have done
was sent in a note to the court and at
least cover himself by saying I am
getting married that we can we please
either move the date up or move the date
back but I'm not going to be there
should have done that I do think however
that he was lulled into a false sense of
security by you I'm awarding him $2,500
on his counterclaim and awarding you
nothing on your claim for harassment
thank you very much
Roddy's excuse can they step out I'm
sorry it was perceived that I deceive
him I don't live my life like that
clearly I was deceived and I bought it
and for that I feel a little bit stupid
he is my children's father and I would
like to have a decent relationship with
him the message here is do the right
thing and see what you're gonna do and I
had no reason to believe that she was
not gonna do what she said she didn't do
it not to go through the state for your
child support hire an attorney if you
don't have money for an attorney you
won't get a fair shake he's glad that my
day in court and then that I prevail
versus price-wise my sworn in judge may
be seated ladies have a seat please mr.
Peterson Mr Price was your roommate and
he was your roommate at a time that the
two of you got drunk and had a fight and
during the course of that fight you were
injured Mr Price according to your
complaint bit your ear and a portion of
your ear was removed you want him to pay
you $5,000 for plastic surgery correct
me on what date was the fight April 25th
at about 3:30 in the morning and on what
date will you no longer roommates near
the end of October of this year so you
stayed there April May June July August
September and October almost seven
months afterwards how large an apartment
is this it was a house it was a
three-bedroom house who else lived there
for the beginning of it it was actually
just Kent and I we had a couple
roommates move in and out during that
time and between April and October I
want you to tell me approximately how
many parties you had in the house
probably 10 to 15 at least during that
time and that's after the fight that you
had with mr. price that's me I'm both
you and mr. price were present at those
parties yes ma'am so you're gonna tell
me sir why you're bothering me now
explain to me sir why you chose today to
bring an action in court partner of
getting plastic surgery and when you
have an injury like this you actually
have to wait up to six to eight months
for it to heal before they can even give
you an estimate to get it fixed
so I had a long period of healing show
me a copy of the police report for
assault I actually have the police
report here here
bingo
offset Ural drunk I was actually not
intoxicated I had two drinks the entire
nightmare Kent had been drinking the
entire time it wasn't the first time
that he had actually been angry when he
was shhh
so the two of you were wrestling on the
floor each of you with throwing punches
at the other but missed is that what I
gather happened yes ma'am well that's
what you say okay go ahead okay so the
evening that this happened
listen let's proceed very fast sir I
have limited sympathy with a bunch of
drunken kids who get into a fight and
one of them gets hurt that's what
happens it was not the first time he had
been angry when he was drunk we had
multiple altercations I had not been
involved in them before I had just seen
them and as part of being a good friend
that's why I actually didn't press
charges listen to me I don't care
and I understand that we are we were in
a house and you know I was on the lease
with him how many parties 10 to 15
parties between April and October was
there alcohol at those parties the same
as was described by the police officers
when they came to this party the party
that we were at that evening was
actually not in her house listen to me
we were at somewhere else and then we
had come back to our house there were
lots of people in that house with
alcohol sir right I'll qahal most of
them intoxicated according to the police
yes and they had showed up at our house
after the incident happened no buts
about I'm asking you is this sir
between April and October the other
parties that you had in your house all
had alcohol because I assume this wasn't
the only party that you had that was
attended by people who were consuming
alcohol no it was yes I understand that
we had a lot of parties it whereas the
words we're DOJ's afterwards yes we did
because I was trying to give him a
chance to actually be a good person I
had told him on multiple occasions after
the incident he said that he would
actually pay for all of the costs April
actually was there for all of it after
the incident I was a good friend April
and she charges
everybody except to me you get drunk you
fight with each other that's what
happens somebody gets hurt I didn't want
to be fucking hung at him I shouldn't
have let him hang you shouldn't have put
him in a headlock
because that's what you did to me
Trevor you put each other in headlock
and well yeah I didn't want to fight
anymore so I try and push him off of me
so you were finished with fighting yes I
did so the game was over
yes is dismissed next case next case
time a 454 in a calendar in a matter of
apathy versus price no justice today
you're still under oath
go Your Honor I'm at Kent here in LA he
I don't care where you met him I want to
know what you're suing him for we were
living together at my parents house and
there was always his dream to be a DJ
and I was his girlfriend and I loved him
and I wanted to help make his dream come
true
he went to go apply for a credit card at
Guitar Center and he didn't get the
credit card because he didn't have any
recent credit so you let him buy a
computer well he asked me if I would
cosign with him on the card because he
didn't have any credit and I did and
when he loved him and he wanted to make
his dream come true
yes that's what you said yes so why are
you here bothering me because your honor
we made a verbal agreement that he would
pay for all the bills in a timely manner
and he did he paid for all of it is
right you agreed to pay her back on the
credit card no I did not when's your
birthday my birthday is June 24 June
24th yes
when was the computer purchased and I
believe like the end of March March I
want you to count on your fingers hold
up to my dad hold up March April
march/april at the end of March May June
Judge Judy continues in a moment in a
separate case 22 year old is suing
ex-boyfriend Kent price for a loan to
buy a laptop computer
Kent claims it was an early birthday
gift now price you have a computer yeah
you have a computer that was paid for by
the plaintiff it wasn't paid for by
either of us who paid for it
it's it's still to be paid actually
bought it for me as an early birthday
present it's not an early birthday
present it's only an early birthday
present for idiots listen to me sir she
wanted to make your dream come true
did she make your dream come true you
got a computer no pay for it okay now
the only problem is he's supposed to
make payments he's supposed to make
payments you didn't make all those
payments right I made some of the
payments for the confine how many
payments did you make for how many
payments did mr. price make um they
wouldn't give me the information on the
credit card site because he had the
account and he had been paying for it
it's about the same amount your honor
but he stopped paying after I broke up
with him he had been paying for
everything miss Appleby I can't help you
with that madam I can only help you with
the amount of money you paid for I'm
hoping that if he stops paying and you
don't pay they'll come and take back his
computer so what would the amounts of
the four payments that you made total
seventy seventy dollars mm-hmm gonna pay
for the computer he paid he had
purchased he's great for the computer
but he does have to pay for all at once
yeah but it's under both our names you
know can't help you
we don't get involved with what we call
anticipatory breaches in court because
you're not broken up now he's not gonna
pay for the computer to likely but he's
not gonna pay for the computer but
courts do not indulge in that
you're entitled to the $70 that you paid
for it and keep your fingers crossed
that he's gonna pay for the rest right I
don't feel I need to pay for the rest
then mr. Brice shall bring you back to
court do you understand don't be an
idiot I mean you want to use the main
signer on the credit card at my spot
another step before that paid off just a
second there's no such word as bought do
you go to college no I don't I don't
know well you should that's all 17000
spoken to the point buddies excuse me
step out I was the honest person and I
let me use my credit because he was my
best friend we've already agreed to pay
half but she was so money hungry she
wanted all this he was getting angry at
people for no reasons he's slammed my
dog's head against the wall he bit my
roommates ear off and it just wasn't
working out he was drunk that night and
he attacked me and it was a very angry
person he was on top of me pinning me
down to the point I couldn't breathe so
I did bite I tried to push him off me
and during that he actually latched on
my ear and when I pushed him off it
completely ripped off I'm not Braveheart
I don't just bite people's ear off I was
just in shock that it had happened it
was horrible it was he's one of my best
friends right him and her they both
we're not friends overall I'm sad that I
lost to my best friends to be completely
honest with her and now the next case
all parties in a matter of concise
overseas Graham 20 year old David
Canseco is suing his former friend 22
year old Nicholas Graham for damaging
his car when he kicked and punched it
during a night of partying mr. Canseco
what is your claim that the defendant
who was friend of yours damaged your car
you want to tell me the story about this
please well all began on the night I had
nothing to do then I Nick was texting
what we're gonna do on 7:21 2010 we were
talking over the phone text messages and
he asked me if I were interested in
going into a club that night I told him
if there was nothing else going on that
I would be willing to go when I showed
up later on after getting a hold of him
I began going into his house when I got
there he was telling me little
information being barely brief when I
got to his house we were waiting for
these girls to meet up with us we met up
with the girls and that's when we all
went in the car from there we left from
Cyprus my vehicle I was driving from
Cyprus California all the way to Los
Angeles when we were on the way there
Nick had his own
beverage and he had been drinking from
where we were leaving at his house to
the club that entire Drive which is over
an hour and when we got there we were
notified that this club that we went to
it wasn't anything that we were
expecting it was a hookah lounge
something open night walk up and you can
do karaoke I'm not into that I didn't
want to pay $30 per person just to
listen to random people go up and yada
la so I was over it and then we told
Nick we were going home so again going
to the car we got in my vehicle and we
came back we're on the way to Cyprus
when we were on the way to cybers Nick
continues where you live in the area yes
and when we got to his house Nick invite
us into just relax and cool off for the
night since we didn't do anything and it
was a waste of money gas time and
everything when he got back to his house
we're in his room we were just relaxing
Nick had been already under the
influence I don't know what possessed
him that began crawling to the girls and
he groped one of the girls now when the
girl was handled like this she freaked
out she grabbed her bags she told her
friend let's go let's get out of here
I'm scared I want to go home I want to
get out of here they grabbed their bags
they ran downstairs they just left the
house I told Nick just to relax sitting
his bed night was over we're gonna leave
just stay here when I went outside the
girls were right there just sitting
there waiting for me so I told him all
right because she was calm they didn't
know where their car was parked it's a
kind of confusing little neighborhoods
called Tanglewood it's a little maze I
was explained to them where their car
was and that is about the time when Nick
called me and I picked up my phone I put
on speakerphone and I was with the girls
and we heard him saying that he wanted
to not really hurt him only what you
heard I heard that he wanted to bash my
face in destroy my car and my life
calling me names cussing me out
screaming at me all types of absurd
things I didn't know what to do Otis Mr
Graham live with his parents where were
your parents that night they were home
they were awake at the time when we
arrived there they were home and awake
mm-hmm they went to sleep shortly after
we got there though so they went to
sleep after they saw you I kind of stuck
him in the house we went upstairs and
then I don't understand what that means
they weren't technically allowed to be
at my house so you snuck them in mm-hmm
how did you sneak them in your house
my parents were in the living room which
is not connected to the front door I we
just easily walked up the stairs how
long do you 22 why would it be
prohibited to have company in your house
for 22 year old young man it was too
late
how did you know that rules yes
well tell me what the rule is well my
stepfather goes to sleep around 9:00
p.m. at night they don't want anyone in
the house pass in so you never have
company past 9:00 p.m.
usually they arrive before 9:00 p.m. and
then they would leave afterwards they're
allowed to stay there after 9:00 p.m.
but no one can walk in and out of the
house after that because he will wake up
from the front door just sometimes they
just slam it it's the old door what do
you mean sometimes they slam it you got
where I'm going it's your mother right
yes your mother and I are in sync you
understand that yep he had brothers and
sisters I'm a sister how old my sister
is 25 she had the same rule you did yes
my sister's moved out of the house now
though she's out of the house now but
when she was living listen to me very
carefully when your sister was living in
the house that she had the same rule you
did they couldn't have any company
coming in after 9 o'clock yes is that
right it's so interesting I always
wanted my children to be in my house
rather than someplace else interesting
that your house is different so you
snuck your friends in and and we were in
my room don't what were you doing the
only reason why I had to brought them to
my house when the girls first arrived at
my house I told him I wanted them to
park around the corner I did not want
them to know where I lived
I didn't even know them I only knew them
from one time I believe I met her at a
club and I got her phone number so what
should bring her home for because he he
wanted me to he right went on the way
back we wanted to smoke some weed he
said hey why don't we go to Nick's house
he's got a Bangla smoked some weed in
his room I said no I don't want them to
come to my house he said it's okay
nothing will happen we went to my house
went in my room smoked some weed
he was being it to me the whole time
excuse my language and I told him I
wanted to beat him up basically I told
him to stop running his mouth I told
miss disrespectful you're in my house
it's different if you're outside of my
house is it okay with your mother and
you step
father that you smoke in your room
sometimes yes when not when I don't have
a job which was then tell me what
happened with your car I got this called
where he told me using a destroy my car
and bash my face and from then I hung up
the phone and from around the corner
where they were parked I began making my
way to my vehicle and when I started
getting closer i hearing pounding noises
and hitting and everything so I started
jogging and when I came around the
corner I see him just drop kicking
elbowing punching throwing everything
his but whatever he had at my card the
whole side of my car is all dented up as
I see whatever please yes man
go to school mr. Graham no I do not do
you work not at the moment
you don't look well for a young guy you
have really lousy color you know that
you only have two children maybe you're
looking at him through rose-colored
glasses I'm telling that for 22 year old
who has nothing to do but sleep if
that's all he does he looks like hell
I'd watch it more carefully if I were
you
Devon has to fix the car yes ma'am like
I'd like to take a look at it
he lives home with you yes you having
drug tested every once in a while No why
not because I know that he smokes pot
mayority what else smokes he drinks what
else
smokes he drinks what else that's it
that's all that you know yes where's he
get the money to buy pot you don't know
I don't give him any money
I'm just asking you where does he get
the money to buy pot you don't know
there's a lot you don't know
there's too much you don't know judgment
for the plaintiff in the amount of
twenty to sixty one that's all step out
excuse their power we all drank on the
way he drank before he even left my
house I'm just appalled at the things
that he believes he was right in he
smoked weed before we even left my house
he's wasted and he's a mess I think that
Nick is full of it and I believe that he
should get his story straight
they should not be drinking and doing
that nor should they be hanging out you
know being friends any longer I no
longer am friends with Nick I have
enough friendship with him he already
ruined that he's got me fired from at
least two jobs my needs to stay home and
be more mindful came some guy then he
was drunk on his way home he crashed it
I obviously didn't crash my car
otherwise I would have been in a
different situation whole different
scenario he's scared of tone his father
did I crashed it then he crashed it I
learned a lot about somebody son's
friends they blackmailed me they forced
me to sign a contract in front of a
police officer he told me if I don't
sign he would take me to jail that boy
was two different people when we had the
police officer there and when he was
there by himself that's against the law
it was a tough little gangster when he
was there by himself but then when the
police officer was there he was very
nice and pleasant
he clearly bashed my car in and I'm just
glad for the justice that was done
[Music]