I'll tell yo you know shit I'm givin ya
ya play so you can tell you're pushing
and Oh Oh Sophie Tom Hannah do get that
come on akiza you can't ask me that
hi nice to meet you I'm Jennifer yeah I
can you tell me who's mommy you are hi
nice to meet you
oh hi hi that's me - I'm Sophie ball the
other mother but I cannot speak English
well I can speak English a little bit
sorry okay who worries I will try like
Mouse to help understand so we're going
to just talk about how I yeah is doing
exactly and socially this year no
complicated things at all
oh thanks oh you're all welcome so she's
doing really great and she has no
problem understanding the class and then
getting along with friends okay okay if
for example which is an advanced in
English she got a really good score on
her a test that she took a few weeks ago
good good
so she has a really good score is never
section listening in writing speaking
and reading mm-hmm okay okay good do you
have any questions no questions at all
no question regarding her social skills
you know that she got um being a super
hard worker a word from the principal
last Friday you know that right yes just
a happy kid and doing well and she seems
to enjoy the school very much right I
think so too
right okay so any other questions no no
questions
oh great thank you for coming by today
okay thank you bye thank you bye
- watch it yo kuttappan say it is
awkward return I'm looking down huh cool
okay so even joking have a gun into
picture what kind of weirdo but don't
worry it's a somber two-way conversation
ETA drew come on hit okay okay so young
Bonnie solo Sunday ninja on Monica
Chacon epoch on Holly
ha ha Keiko yo I said I secrete a
baguette le Mignot
dr. Han reaction wha the Panama
Portugal's oh it's a tension a signal
something you may have optimized
imitates all peace attention retention
can jump real high it's a check on a
grotto motions anaconda enemy on YouTube
you don't know don't you dare could I go
my hotel and get what you don't go home
or I can kick your Robertson Masha to
look in Chennai oh yeah I'm gonna book a
oh hello nice to meet you I'm Jennifer
may I ask of his mother you are hi hi
I'm Sophie bond Leah's mother nice to
meet you
you know leah is such an adorable little
girl
she's very outgoing and energetic and
academically she's doing really well
oh really well I'm so glad to hear that
honestly Leah's a father and I worry a
little bit about her English because
most of the time we use a Korean at home
no no she doesn't have any problem
chipping away the class she understands
everything but sometimes sometimes she
seems to not understand some words or
expressions but that's that's pretty
normal for every kid no need to worry
about it good that's a relief
but since we know that she might need to
catch up with her
resident class is there a way that we
can work on English together because we
want to help her improve oh well then I
don't suggest that you read the books to
her or have her read books to you aloud
and talk about the story together in
English wow that's a good idea and any
other questions well I was just
wondering how she gets along with other
kids yes she'll laugh mingle with other
kids and always looks happy when she's
around them
oh great actually I was a little bit
worried that some kids like Tia's are
because you know she was a primitive
over the past weeks and looks like a
jack-o-lantern with a list and as we
know sometimes the kids can been Mia
no you shouldn't worry about that she
gets along well with everyone
oh thanks I think we're really lucky to
have you as our teacher I'm very happy
and feel grateful Thanks oh thank you oh
thank you for today are you bananas hey
when today oh I wanted a kiss all monami
or juice up she actually a prio have it
incorporated kale hello are you miss
Jennifer oh yes I am I am Liz Muller
Sophie ball nice to meet you oh yes glad
you make it oh of course
Oh have a seat please oh thanks um I'm
sorry I have it come down here today but
as you know we have some problems with
Leah and want to discuss ways to help
her it's more cooperative with others
oh yes I know yeah we know
street bra warning knows her from you
three times just last week and Leah's
father and I grade that we should help
her yeah we should help her work harder
to be better yes right right and as we
know she often has arguments with others
during lunch and doesn't follow
directions like lining up or avoiding
her turn and it doesn't finish her work
in timely manner yes right right mm-hmm
yes Leah's father and I also grade that
she has some issues with patience
cooperation and time management and we
are willing to cooperate with you to
help her make any necessary changes oh
I'm glad we can help each other a helper
of course the chorus as Leo's parents
which is some want her to understand
that her happiness a related others and
yeah we believe it is in for a lesson to
learn oh great now if you don't mind can
we discuss more details how we can help
sure go ahead I'm all ears
help to find a better way for her