>> Heather: GOOD EVENING, I'M
HEATHER HISCOX AND THIS IS "THE
NATIONAL."
[♪♪♪]
>> I FIND IT DISAPPOINTING.
>> Heather: THE BACKLASH GROWS
AFTER THE GOVERNOR GENERAL
DERIDES JUNK SCIENCE, HOROSCOPES
AND DIVINE INTERVENTION.
>>> YOU HAVE LOTS OF QUESTIONS
FOR BOB MacDONALD ABOUT CLIMATE
CHANGE.
ANSWERS.
>> THIS IS A TICKING TIMEBOMB.
IT REALLY WORRIES ME A LOT.
>> Heather: ABOUT HALF A MILLION
CANADIANS ARE AFFECTED BY
HEPATITIS C.
THERE IS A CARE.
IT DOES NOT REACH MOST.
>>> PLUS...
>> IT IS A ONCE IN A LIFETIME
OPPORTUNITY TO SEE THIS.
>> Heather: THE OLD MASTER THAT
IS EXPECTED TO HIT A NEW HIGH
FOR A PAINTING SOLD AT AUCTION.
>>> THE GOVERNOR GENERAL IS THE
QUEEN'S REPRESENTATIVE IN
CANADA.
THE POSITION STEEPED IN
TRADITION AND CEREMONY AND
REQUIRING PLENTY OF DIPLOMACY.
TONIGHT, JULIE PAYETTE IS UNDER
FIRE FOR WADING INTO TRICKY
TERRITORY DURING A SPEECH THIS
WEEK.
FOR SOME, IT APPEARED SHE WAS
MOCKING PEOPLE WHO BELIEVE IN
GOD.
KATIE SIMPSON REPORTS.
[♪♪♪]
♪♪♪
GOD SAVE THE QUEEN...
>> Reporter: JULIE PAYETTE'S
DEDICATION TO SCIENCE HELPED
PROPEL HER TO HIGH OFFICE.
BUT HER COMMENTS ABOUT THOSE WHO
LOOK TO A HIGHER POWER ARE
CAUSING DIVISION IN CANADA'S
RELIGIOUS COMMUNITIES.
>> WE FIND IT DISAPPOINTING.
AND INSULTING QUITE FRANKLY.
>> Reporter: FRUSTRATION HAS
BEEN GROWING SINCE THE GOVERNOR
GENERAL SPOKE AT A SCIENCE
CONFERENCE ON WEDNESDAY.
PAYETTE USED HER APPEARANCE AND
DENOUNCED CLIMATE CHANGE DENIERS
AND TOOK ON CREATIONISTS.
>> WE ARE STILL DEBATING AND
STILL QUESTIONING WHETHER LIFE
WAS A DIVINE INTERVENTION OR
WHETHER IT WAS COMING OUT OF A
NATURAL PROCESS.
RANDOM PROCESS.
>> Prime Minister Justin
Trudeau: WE ARE A GOVERNMENT
GROUNDED IN SCIENCE.
>> Reporter: THE PRIME MINISTER
DEFENDED PAYETTE.
AND HER FAITH IN SCIENCE.
>> Prime Minister Justin
Trudeau: I APPLAUD THE FIRMNESS
WITH WHICH SHE STANDS IN SUPPORT
OF SCIENCE.
AND THE TRUTH.
>> Reporter: JUSTIN TRUDEAU'S
COMMENTS HAVE TRIGGERED NEW
BACKLASH TODAY.
ON FACEBOOK, CONSERVATIVE LEADER
ANDREW SCHEER WROTE...
TRUDEAU'S OFFICE SAID HE STANDS
BY HIS STATEMENT.
SOME SPIRITUAL LEADERS SUGGEST
THIS DEBATE IS EXPOSING A
DISMISSIVE ATTITUDE IN CANADA.
>> TRYING TO PROMOTE AWARENESS
OF CLIMATE CHANGE, IT IS COUNTER
PRODUCTIVE.
>> Reporter: PAYETTE HAS BEEN ON
THE JOB A MONTH.
HER ROLE IS MOSTLY CEREMONIAL.
SHE REPRESENTS THE QUEEN.
THE HEAD OF THE CHURCH OF
ENGLAND.
KATIE SIMPSON, CBC NEWS, OTTAWA.
>> Heather: CATHERINE McKENNA
CONFRONTED A REPORTER FROM REBEL
MEDIA DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE
TODAY.
THE REPORTER TRIED TO ASK A
QUESTION ABOUT HYDROELECTRIC
POWER.
McKENNA ANSWERED WITH A DEMAND
THE MEDIA ORGANIZATION STOP
REFERRING TO HER AS CLIMATE
BARBIE.
>> CAN I GET A COMMITMENT FROM
YOU, YOU WILL NOT USE THAT
HASHTAG AND THE NAME IN YOUR
ARTICLES?
>> ME PERSONALLY, YES.
IF YOU WANT TO GET INTO IT, YOU
BANNED ONE OF OUR CORRESPONDENCE
FROM GOING TO THE CONFERENCE IN
BONNE.
>> THAT IS NOT TRUE.
I WROTE A LETTER LAST YEAR END
COURAGING YOU TO COME BECAUSE I
THINK YOU CAN ALL LEARN ABOUT
CLIMATE CHANGE HOW IT IS REAL --
IT IS HAVING REAL IMPACT.
>> A LEGITIMATE QUESTION.
>> I WOULD LIKE A COMMITMENT YOU
WILL NOT CALL ME NAMES AND TALK
ABOUT THE COLOUR OF MY HAIR.
YOU WILL NOT MAKE FUN OF ME.
THE REASON I ASK YOU IS I HAVE
TWO DAUGHTERS.
THERE ARE A LOT OF GIRLS THAT
WANT TO GET INTO POLITICS, AND
IT IS COMPLETELY UNACCEPTABLE
THAT YOU DO THIS.
>> Heather: THE EXCHANGE
HAPPENED AFTER A MEETING OF
CANADIAN ENVIRONMENT MINISTERS
IN VANCOUVER.
>>> HIRING PROSPECTS IN BRITISH
COLUMBIA GOT A BIG LIFT TODAY
WITH AMAZON ANNOUNCING PLANS TO
BRING 1,000 NEW JOBS TO THE
PROVINCE.
IT COMES ON THE SAME DAY AS THE
LATEST EMPLOYMENT NUMBERS.
THE CANADIAN ECONOMY ADDED MORE
THAN TWICE THE EXPECTED NUMBER
OF NEW JOBS LAST MONTH.
JACQUELINE HANSEN REPORTS.
>> I THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
BEING PATIENT WITH US.
>> Reporter: A LONG LINE OF JOB
SEEKERS SNAKES THROUGH A MALL,
WAITING HOURS TO APPLY FOR
POSITIONS AT AN AMAZON
FULFILLMENT CENTRE OVER THE
HOLIDAYS.
>> RIGHT NOW, I AM NOT LOOKING.
I AM LOOKING FOR A JOB.
>> Reporter: UNEMPLOYED FOR TWO
MONTHS ALREADY, ANNIE HOPES
TODAY'S WAIT WILL BE WORTH IT.
>> Interview: IT IS SEASONAL.
THEY SAID LATER IT MAY BE
PERMANENT.
I AM HOPING I WILL GET HIRED.
>> Reporter: IF THE TREND
CONTINUES, SHE MAY BE IN LUCK.
THE ECONOMY ADDED 33,000 JOBS IN
OCTOBER DRIVEN BY FULL-TIME
POSITIONS.
IN MARKS 11 MONTHS OF GAINS.
THE UNEMPLOYMENT RATE TICKED UP
BECAUSE MORE PEOPLE ARE LOOKING
FOR WORK.
>> Interview: PART IS THE
RECOVERY FROM THE OIL SHOCK.
AGAIN THE RESOURCE SECTOR IS NO
LONGER A BIG DRAG.
WE ARE STARTING TO SEE THE
MANUFACTURING SECTOR PICK UP.
>> Reporter: WAGES SAW STRONG
GROWTH.
A GOOD SIGN FOR CANADIAN'S
POCKET BOOKS AND THE ECONOMY AS
A WHOLE.
THE RECESSION IN 2009, WE HAD
REALLY, REALLY SLOW WAGE GROWTH.
THERE IS A LITTLE BIT OF WAGE
GROWTH IN THE 2000S BEFORE THE
RECESSION, BUT REALLY FOR THE
PAST, YOU KNOW, 20 YEARS OR SO,
WE HAVE NOT HAD GREAT WAGE
GROWTH.
>> Reporter: CANADA'S ECONOMY
STARTED THE YEAR SO STRONG, THAT
IT HAS BEEN WIDELY EXPECTED TO
SLOW DOWN.
AND IN SOME WAYS, IT ALREADY IS
SLOWING.
THE GDP CONTRACTED IN AUGUST AND
A REPORT TODAY SHOWS EXPORTS
CONTINUE TO FALL.
>> WHAT IS LOOMING, WE HAVE TO
TAKE SOME OF THE NUMBERS WE ARE
GETTING WITH A GRAIN OF SALT
BECAUSE THE NUMBERS AHEAD MAY
NOT BE SO ROSEY.
>> Reporter: AT THE JOB FAIR,
SHE GOT GOOD NEWS.
>> YEAH, THEY CALLED ME FOR THE
NEXT INTERVIEW TOMORROW, 9:30.
I HOPE I WILL GET TO IT.
>> Reporter: AND BE ONE OF THE
CANADIANS TO FIND WORK.
WHILE THE OPPORTUNITIES ARE
THERE.
JACQUELINE HANSEN, CBC NEWS,
TORONTO.
>> Heather: CANADA'S ETHICS
COMMISSIONER HAS CLEARED UP THE
CONFUSION ABOUT THE NUMBER OF
LIBERAL CABINET MINISTERS STILL
HOLDING ASSETS OUTSIDE OF BLIND
TRUST.
MARY DAWSON NOW SAID THAT ASIDE
FROM BILL MORNEAU, THERE ARE
NONE.
DAWSON'S OFFICE SAID FEWER THAN
FIVE LIBERAL CABINET MINISTERS
CURRENTLY HOLD CONTROLLED ASSETS
INDIRECTLY.
THAT LED TO HEATED DEBATE
BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE
OPPOSITION OVER LIBERAL M.P.S
ASSETS.
AND POTENTIAL CONFLICT OF
INTEREST.
MORNEAU HAS COMMITTED TO PUTTING
HIS ASSETS IN A BLIND TRUST.
>>> FOR THE FIRST TIME TODAY,
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT USED THE
MAGNITSKY ACT, THE NEW LEGAL
WEAPON AGAINST CORRUPTION AND
HUMAN RIGHTS ABUSES.
OTTAWA SLAPPED SANCTIONS ON 52
FOREIGN OFFICIALS, INCLUDING 30
RUSSIANS.
MOSCOW PROMISED TO COUNTER WITH
SANCTIONS ON HIGH PROFILE
CANADIANS.
>>> ONTARIO IS PLOWING AHEAD
WITH ITS MARIJUANA RETAIL
STRATEGY.
AHEAD OF LEGALIZATION SET FOR
NEXT CANADA DAY.
TODAY, THE LIQUOR CONTROL BOARD
ANNOUNCED THE CITY'S PRESELECTED
FOR STAND ALONE CANNABIS STORES.
BUT THERE IS GROWING PRESSURE ON
THE TRUDEAU GOVERNMENT TO SLOW
ALL THIS DOWN.
IT IS COMING FROM THE
OPPOSITION, FROM LAW ENFORCEMENT
AND EVEN FROM THE RED CHAMBER.
CATHERINE CULLEN EXPLAINS.
>> WE DON'T THINK THEY CAN MEET
THE DEADLINE FOR LEGALIZING POT.
>> Reporter: JUSTIN TRUDEAU'S
GOVERNMENT HAS MARCHED WITH
DETERMINATION TOWARD POT
LEGALIZATION BY JULY 1ST.
CONCERN FROM PROVINCES.
>> WE NEED AN ADDITIONAL YEAR.
I THINK THERE ARE TOO MANY
UNADDRESSED ISSUES.
>> Reporter: AND POLICE FORCES.
>> Interview: WE HAVE A CHANCE
TO DO IT RIGHT HERE.
WE ARE ASKING FOR A BIT OF TIME
AND THEN WE WILL DO THAT.
>> Reporter: A LEGAL, REGULATED
POT REGIME BY NEXT CANADA DAY
REMAINS THE LIBERAL'S GOAL.
THE POT PLANS COULD BE
CHALLENGED BY AN INCREASINGLY
INDEPENDENT SENATE.
>> Interview: IT IS GOING TO
TAKE SOME TIME TO STUDY THE BILL
IN A DELIBERATE, THOUGHTFUL
MANNER.
>> Reporter: PRATT SAID THERE IS
SERIOUS CONCERN ABOUT
LEGALIZATION IN THE SENATE.
INCLUDING ABOUT POLICING, AND
LETTING PEOPLE GROW MARIJUANA AT
HOME.
MANY THINGS THAT WILL REQUIRE
CAREFUL STUDY AND POTENTIALLY
SUGGESTING CHANGES TO THE BILL.
A PROCESS THAT MAY OR MAY NOT BE
DONE BY JULY.
>> Interview: THE DEADLINE IS A
POLITICAL DEADLINE.
YOU KNOW, IT IS NOT A COURT THAT
IMPOSED THE DEADLINE.
IT IS THE GOVERNMENT THAT SET
THE DEADLINE.
>> Reporter: HE IS NOT ALONE.
>> I DON'T THINK WE SHOULD SET A
TIME LINE FOR LEGISLATION LIKE
THIS EVER.
>> Reporter: VERNE WHITE POINTS
TO AGE OF ACCESS.
>> Interview: THIS IS ABOUT
KEEPING IT AWAY FROM YOUNG
PEOPLE, WE SHOULD TALK ABOUT AN
AGE BEYOND 18 AND 19.
>> I UNDERSTAND THE COMPLEXITY
AND THE WORK THE SENATE HAS TO
DO.
>> Reporter: TO ENCOURAGE THE
SENATE ALONG, BILL BLAIR IS
LEANING ON A MORAL ARGUMENT.
TELLING SENATORS A REGULATED
SYSTEM IS NEEDED TO KEEP YOUNG
PEOPLE AWAY FROM POT.
>> I REMIND THEM THAT THE
URGENCY IS WHAT IS HAPPENING TO
THE KIDS AND THE COMMUNITIES
TODAY,.
>> Reporter: HOW MANY IN THE
INDEPENDENT SENATE WILL ACCEPT
THAT ARGUMENT.
CBC NEWS, OTTAWA.
>> Heather: CANADA IS COMMITTED
TO ELIMINATE HEPATITIS C BY
2030.
EXCEPT NEW DATA RELEASED AT THE
WORLD HEPATITIS SUMMIT IN BRAZIL
THIS WEEK SHOWS THAT WILL NOT
HAPPEN.
THERE IS A CURE FOR HEPATITIS C.
AS VIK ADHOPIA TELLS US, THE
HIGH COST OF TREATMENT IS A
MAJOR BARRIER TO DEFEATING THE
DISEASE.
>> Reporter: WHEN MARSHA WAS
DIAGNOSED, SHE WAS TOLD SHE
WOULD NEED A LIVER TRANSPLANT.
A NEW CLASS OF DRUGS CHANGED
EVERYTHING.
>> Interview: PEOPLE THAT HAVE
HAD HEPATITIS C FOR YEARS FEEL
HOPE.
>> Reporter: HOPE CAME AT A
STEEP PRICE.
MORE THAN $100,000 FOR THE
TREATMENT.
>> Interview: I HAD AN EXCELLENT
DRUG PLAN.
AND THE DRUG PLAN COVERED THE
COST OF THE TREATMENT.
I PAID, I THINK, MAYBE 10, $15
OUT OF POCKET EVERY MONTH.
WHICH IS REALLY NOTHING.
>> Reporter: THE PRICE HAS
FALLEN A BIT.
NOT EVERYONE CAN AFFORD THE NEW
12 WEEK TREATMENT THAT CAN BE AS
HIGH AS $80,000.
IF PATIENTS DO NOT HAVE DRUG
COVERAGE, THE GOVERNMENTS ONLY
PAY FOR THE SICKEST.
MANY GO UNTREATED.
>> WE ARE NOT ON THE ROAD TO
ELIMINATION OF HEPATITIS C.
IT IS NOT ENOUGH.
>> Reporter: MANY COUNTRIES
INCLUDING CANADA AIM TO
ELIMINATE HEPATITIS C BY 2030.
COUNTRIES IN GREEN ARE ON TRACK
AND THOSE IN RED ARE FALLING
BEHIND.
CANADA IS AMONG NATIONS MAKING
PROGRESS BUT WILL MISS THE GOAL
LIKELY.
THE U.K. PHARMACOLOGIST SAID THE
COST OF DRUGS IS HOLDING UP
PROGRESS.
>> THE PEOPLE ARE NOT GETTING
THE TREATMENTS THEY NEED.
THE GOVERNMENTS ARE SAYING THIS
IS TOO EXPENSIVE.
AND THEY ARE NOT TREATING
EVERYBODY.
THERE ARE RESTRICTIONS ON ACCESS
TO TREATMENT.
SOMETHING HAS TO CHANGE.
THE PRICES HAVE TO COME DOWN.
>> Reporter: THE EXPERTS
ESTIMATE THE DRUG SHOULD NOT
COST MORE THAN $60 A PATIENT.
THE PROBLEM MAY NOT BE PRICE
ALONE.
>> Interview: IF THIS WAS AN
INFECTION THAT AFFECTED AN UPPER
MIDDLE CLASS WEALTHY POPULATION,
I DON'T THINK WE WOULD HAVE THE
DISCUSSION.
>> Reporter: THE LIVER
SPECIALIST SAID CANADA SCREENS
FOR THE DISEASE INCONSISTENTLY.
HE SUSPECTS IT IS BECAUSE
HEPATITIS C IS ASSOCIATED OFTEN
WITH SHARING NEEDLES OR UNSAFE
SEX.
BUT BABY BOOMERS ARE AT RISK
BECAUSE OF CONTAINED BLOOD
TRANSFUSIONS.
STILL, HEALTH CANADA HAS
REJECTED CALLS FOR MASS
SCREENING.
>> Interview: THE U.S. HAS
DEVELOPED EXCELLENT PUBLIC
HEALTH POLICY TOWARD HEPATITIS C
ARE ON TARGET FOR ELIMINATING IT
IN THE U.S. BY 2030.
WHICH IS THE W.H.O. GLOBAL
TARGET.
AND IT IS DISAPPOINTING TO SEE
CANADA FALLING SHORT.
>> Reporter: HE SAID UNLESS
THERE IS A NATIONAL STRATEGY,
INFECTIONS WILL SIMPLY CONTINUE.
CBC NEWS, TORONTO.
>> Heather: COMING UP, ASK BOB.
WHAT YOU WANTED TO KNOW ABOUT
CLIMATE CHANGE.
>> THAT IS A HARD QUESTION TO
ANSWER.
>> Heather: IT DID NOT HAVE HIM
STUMPED.
>>> LATER...
THERE GOES THE NEIGHBOURHOOD.
>> OPEN AND PEOPLE PROTESTED
PRETTY STRONGLY.
>> Heather: THE BATTLE AGAINST
GENTRIFYING PARTS OF LOS
ANGELES.
>>> THE MAYOR OF MONTREAL WAS
SUPPOSED TO BE A SHOO-IN FOR
RE-ELECTION THIS SUNDAY.
DENIS CODERRE IS IN FOR A FIGHT.
HIS MAIN RIVAL IS A RELATIVELY
NEW NAME TO POLITICS.
WHO WANTS TO SHAKE THINGS UP.
ALISON NORTHCOTT HAS THE STORY.
>> Reporter: SHE STARTED THE
CAMPAIGN AS THE UNDERDOG.
A ONE TERM CITY COUNCILLOR WITH
LITTLE POLITICAL EXPERIENCE.
NOW, POLLS SUGGEST SHE IS IN A
TIGHT RACE WITH DENIS CODERRE
WHO HAS BEEN MAYOR FOR FOUR
YEARS.
TODAY, SELLING HER MESSAGE ON
THE MONTREAL METRO.
>> FINDING SOLUTIONS FOR PEOPLE
STUCK IN TRAFFIC AND PEOPLE NOT
BEING ABLE TO GET INTO A BUS OR
THE SUBWAY BECAUSE IT IS
OVERCROWDED.
THIS IS MY GOAL.
I HAVE BEEN TRANSPARENT AND
CLEAR ABOUT MY OBJECTIVES.
IF I GET -- IF I AM THE FIRST
WOMAN MAYOR OF THE CITY.
TO ME, EVERYTHING IS POSSIBLE.
>> Reporter: THE KEY PROPOSALS
INCLUDING A PLAN TO BUILD A NEW
METRO LINE HAVE BEEN CALLED
UNREALISTIC.
STILL, SHE SAID HER PLANS AND
LEADERSHIP STYLE RESONATE WITH
VOTERS.
>> Interview: PEOPLE ARE LOOKING
FOR POLITICIANS CONNECTED TO
THEM.
>> Reporter: CODERRE, A FORMER
FEDERAL M.P. IS CAMPAIGNING ON
HIS DECADES OF POLITICAL
EXPERIENCE AND HIS RECORD.
>> Interview: WE HAVE A
TREMENDOUS MOMENTUM.
THE ECONOMY IS GOING WELL.
TO THINK BACK FOUR YEARS AGO
WHETHER WE WILL THE CORRUPTION
AND NOW THAT WE BROUGHT BACK
INTEGRITY.
I THINK THAT AT THE END OF THE
DAY, PEOPLE WILL SEE IF IT IS
NOT BROKE, WHY FIX IT.
>> Reporter: HE WAS ELECTED
FOLLOWING YEARS OF CORRUPTION
SCANDALS AT CITY HALL.
ONE OF THE FIRST MOVES WAS TO
NAME AN INSPECTOR GENERAL TO
MONITOR PUBLIC CONTRACTS IN AN
EFFORT TO CLEAN THINGS UP.
HIS OPPOSITION AT THE ENERGY
EAST PIPELINE AND CANADA POST
PLANS TO END HOME MAIL DELIVERY
WON HIM POINTS WITH SOME.
HE HAS BEEN CRITICIZED FOR BIG
SPENDING ON EVENTS LIKE
MONTREAL'S 375th ANNIVERSARY AND
THE FORMULA E ELECTRIC CAR RACE
LAST SUMMER.
NICKNAMED KID KODAK FOR THE
AFFECTION FOR THE CAMERAS.
HIS BRASH PERSONALITY DOES NOT
SIT WELL WITH EVERYONE.
>> THE PERSONALITY OF CODERRE
COMPARED TO VALERIE PLANTE, IT
IS NOT A MAN I WILL INVITE TO
DINNER.
>> Reporter: MANY SAID HE PUT
MONTREAL ON THE MAP.
>> SHE IS VERY YOUNG.
AND NO EXPERIENCE.
>> Reporter: THE CHOICE IS NOT
UP TO MONTREALERS WHO GO TO THE
POLLS ON SUNDAY.
ALISON NORTHCOTT, CBC NEWS,
MONTREAL.
>> Heather: LONDON IS A CITY ON
EDGE AGAIN.
AFTER MORE ACID ATTACKS.
THE LATEST CARRIED OUT BY A 14
YEARS.
IT HAS BECOME A MAJOR WORRY WITH
GRUESOME CONSEQUENCES.
MARGARET EVANS REPORTS.
>> Reporter: THERE HAVE BEEN TWO
ATTACKS USING CORROSIVE
SUBSTANCES IN LONDON OVER THE
PAST 24 HOURS.
STATISTICS THAT EARNED THE CITY
THE DUBIOUS TITLE OF THE ACID
ATTACK CAPITAL OF THE WORLD.
THAT IS NEARLY 400 ATTACKS SINCE
THE START OF THE YEAR.
A CRIME TREND INCREASINGLY
ASSOCIATED WITH PARTS OF EAST
LONDON AND CARRIED OUT BY YOUNG
MEN OR BOYS.
TRYING TO STEAL MOPEDS OR
SCOOTERS.
TARGETING DELIVERY PEOPLE.
SCOTLAND YARD SAID THEY HAVE
ARRESTED A 14-YEAR-OLD CONNECTED
TO ONE OF LAST NIGHT'S ATTACKS,
ON A MAN DELIVERING PIZZA AFTER
HE PARKED HIS SCOOTER.
>> THE VICTIM WAS BRAVE AND
STARTED TO FIGHT BACK AND WOULD
NOT HAND OVER THE KEY.
>> Reporter: THE LOCAL RESIDENTS
TRIED TO HELP THE MAN.
HIS INJURIES ARE LIFE
THREATENING.
>> Interview: IT IS LIKELY HE
WILL LOSE THE SIGHT OF HIS EYES.
HE INHALED SOME OF THE NOXIOUS
SUBSTANCE THAT WOULD APPEAR TO
CAUSE A NEGATIVE REACTION IN HIS
WINDPIPE.
AND AS A RESULT, HE HAS BEEN PUT
INTO AN INDUCED COMA.
>> Reporter: THE INCREASE IS SO
ALARMING HERE THAT THE BRITISH
GOVERNMENT IS PREPARING TO BAN
THE SALE OF CORROSIVE PRODUCTS
TO ANYONE UNDER THE AGE OF 18.
THEY ARE PLANNING TO TOUGHEN UP
LAWS OF POSSESSION.
SO POSSESSION OF CORROSIVE
SUBSTANCES.
MAKING THEM EQUIVALENT TO THE
LAWS IN PLACE THAT EXIST FOR
CARRYING KNIVES.
MOST PRODUCTS USED IN THE
ATTACKS CAN BE PURCHASED IN THE
LOCAL HARDWARE STORE.
AMMONIA, SULFURIC ACID FOUND IN
CLEANING PRODUCTS.
SOME CRITICS SAID CRIME IS ON
THE RISE.
ONE CONTRIBUTING FACTOR FOR THE
PROBLEM.
>> Heather: THE FORMER U.S.
SOLDIER WHO ABANDONED HIS POST
IN AFGHANISTAN ONLY TO BE
CAPTURED BY THE TALIBAN RECEIVED
A DISHONOURABLE DISCHARGE TODAY.
BOWE BERGDAHL AVOIDED PRISON
TIME FOR DESERTION.
HE WAS HELD BY THE TALIBAN FOR
FIVE YEARS.
HE WAS RELEASED IN 2014 IN A
CONTROVERSIAL EXCHANGE FOR FIVE
DETAINEES IN GUANTANOMO.
THE U.S. PRESIDENT TRUMP TWEETED
THAT THE JUDGMENT TODAY WAS A
COMPLETE DISGRACE.
>>> THE RED CROSS IS APOLOGIZING
AFTER LOSING OVER $5 MILLION OF
EBOLA AID MONEY TO FRAUD.
SALARIES WERE PAID TO
NON-EXISTENT EMPLOYEES.
OVERPRICED SUPPLIES.
AND CASH SIPHONED OFF BY STAFF.
THE ORGANIZATION SAID IT NOW HAS
MORE STRINGENT RULES IN PLACE
AND THERE WILL BE CONSEQUENCES
FOR STAFF INVOLVED.
>>> THE HOLY GRAIL, AN ART WORLD
MIRACLE.
THAT IS HOW AUCTIONEERS DESCRIBE
AN EXTREMELY RARE LEONARDO
DEVINCI MASTERPIECE.
IT IS ABOUT TO GO FOR SALE IN
NEW YORK.
THE PAINTINGS'S PATH TO THE
AUCTION BLOCK TOOK MANY TWISTS
AND TURN.
>> Reporter: IT IS CALLED ONE OF
THE GREATEST ART DISCOVERIES OF
THE 21 CENTURY.
A PIECE THOUGHT LOST TO HISTORY.
ONE OF A HANDFUL OF SURVIVING
WORKS BY ONE OF THE GREAT
MASTERS.
>> WHERE DO I START?
IT IS AN EXTRAORDINARY EVENT TO
BE ABLE TO HANDLE THE HOLY GRAIL
OF THE MASTERS.
>> Reporter: IT IS CALLED
SAVIOUR OF THE WORLD.
EYES THAT HINT AT A GREATER
MYSTERY.
IT HAS THE HALLMARKS OF LEONARDO
DEVINCI'S HAND.
IT IS BELIEVED IT WAS PAINTED
AROUND 1500.
THE TIME HE WORKED ON THE LAST
SUPPER AND THE MONA LISA.
>> HIS MAIN OCCUPATION WAS THE
PAINTINGS.
THE PAINTING HE DID TO
PERFECTION HE DID EVERYTHING
ELSE.
THAT IS WHY THERE ARE SO FEW
WORKS.
>> Reporter: ACCORDING TO
CHRISTIE'S, THIS IS ONE OF JUST
16 PAINTINGS KNOWN TO EXIST.
IT WAS THE LAST ONE IN PRIVATE
HANDS.
THE PAINTING HAS BEEN INCREDIBLE
BACK STORY, IT HAD BEEN LOST FOR
MORE THAN 100 YEARS AND AT ONE
POINT IT WAS SOLD AT AUCTION FOR
45 POUNDS.
BAD RESTORATION JOBS MASKED THE
PAINTING.
IT WAS BOUGHT FOR $10,000 IN
2005.
THE LAYERS WERE PEELED AWAY.
REACHING THE MASTERPIECE
BENEATH.
IT HAS BEEN SOLD TWICE.
THE SUBJECT OF A LAWSUIT.
>> Interview: IT SUBSEQUENT
REMOVAL, THE GENIUS BECAME
APPARENT.
>> Reporter: AFTER 500 YEARS,
THE PIECE IS SHOWING ITS AGE.
BUT IT IS STILL EXPECTED TO
FETCH MORE THAN $100 MILLION.
IT IS ALSO GENERATING A LOT OF
BUZZ.
AS PEOPLE RUSH TO CATCH A
GLIMPSE, HOPING IT IS NOT THE
LAST CHANCE.
>> IT IS BREATHTAKING.
YOU HAVE TO APPRECIATE IT,
HONESTLY AND SEE IT.
>> IT IS A ONCE IN A LIFETIME
OPPORTUNITY TO SEE THIS PIECE.
I MEAN, WHO KNOWS WHERE IT WILL
END UP FROM HERE.
>> Reporter: THE HOPE IS IT WILL
NOT DISAPPEAR AGAIN.
AND THAT WHOMEVER BUYS IT WILL
LOAN IT TO A GALLERY OR MUSEUM.
SO THE WORK WILL REMAIN ON
DISPLAY FOR ALL TO SEE.
STEVEN D'SOUZA, CBC NEWS, NEW
YORK.
>> Heather: STRAIGHT AHEAD, BOB
[ CBC News theme ]
[whoosh]
[dramatic]
By the time it finally dissipated itself,
Hurricane Hazel had screamed and hacked its way
from Haiti to James Bay in a path
of death and destruction 200 miles wide.
Drownings, falling trees, crushed homes
and washed-out bridges accounted for more than 100 deaths.
One third of them in Ontario alone.
So far 30 bodies have been recovered in the Toronto area.
Some of them are, as of yet, unidentified.
Complete casualty figures won't be available for several days,
but latest reports indicate that
the final death count in Ontario may exceed 60.
24-hours after the hurricane and floods had passed
some 300 people were still missing,
countless thousands are homeless.
Camera crews from CBC TelevisionNews worked through the night
to bring you this exclusive
eye-witness account of Hurricane Hazel.
With rainfall reaching almost seven inches in places,
some rivers ran as much as 16 feet above their normal levels.
When dawn breaks, planes take to the air to survey the damage.
The sight that greets them resembles a lake,
it's surface deceivingly quiet.
But the damage doesn't show,
but estimates say farmers will count
their losses in the millions of dollars.
Then the four-lane boulevard that links
Toronto to her western suburbs,
the Humber Bridge, it's totally impassable.
Toronto's prized traffic bottle-neck,
the Humber River Bridge,
was washed out on it's approaches,
although the bridge still held.
It was luckier than many other bridges
in the Greater Toronto Area,
more than a score of them have been washed away,
some of them have completely vanished.
More than 40 highways and main roads are underwater.
All traffic to and from Toronto was banned by provincial police,
pending a survey of the actual damage.
[ CBC News theme ]
>> Heather: THE UNITED STATES
GOVERNMENT RELEASED A
COMPREHENSIVE REPORT ON CLIMATE
CHANGE TODAY.
THE CONCLUSION:
IT IS EXTREMELY LIKELY THAT
HUMANIVITIES HAVE BEEN THE
DOMINANT CAUSE OF GLOBAL WARMING
SINCE THE MID-20th CENTURY.
IT IS A STARK CONTRAST TO THE
TRUMP ADMINISTRATION'S MESSAGING
AND POLICY WITH THE U.S.
OFFICIALS SET TO PUSH FOSSIL
FUELS AT NEXT WEEK'S UNITED
NATIONS CONFERENCE IN BON.
THERE IS A LOT OF NEWS AROUND
CLIMATE CHANGE, YOU HAVE MANY
QUESTIONS ABOUT THE SCIENCE OF
IT.
EARLIER, WE TOOK THOSE QUESTIONS
TO OUR SCIENCE CORESPONDENT BOB
McDONALD.
FOR A SPECIAL CLIMATE CHANGE
EDITION OF ASK BOB.
OUR KNOWLEDGE OF CLIMATE CHANGE
IS STILL IMPERFECT.
IT IS A FIELD SCIENTISTS HAVE
BEEN BUILDING ON FOR DECADES.
THE CBC SCIENCE CORRESPONDENT
HAS BEEN FOLLOWING CLOSELY SINCE
THE 1970s.
>> I AM BOB McDONALD.
THERE IS A NEW ELEMENT INVOLVED.
ONE THAT WE INTRODUCED.
GLOBAL WARMING.
>> IS THERE A CONSENSUS OUT
THERE THAT THE CLIMATE CHANGE IS
REAL?
>> Heather: BRINGING US THE
STORIES.
>> THE EARTH IS GETTING WARMER.
>> Heather: NOW HE IS HERE TO
ANSWER THE QUESTIONS YOU ASKED.
BOB, THANK YOU.
>> MY PLEASURE.
>> Heather: WE ALWAYS APPRECIATE
THE OPPORTUNITY TO PUT YOUR
QUESTIONS TO YOU DIRECTLY.
I WAS SURPRISED AND I HAVE TO
SAY IMPRESSED YOU HAVE BEEN
LOOKING AT THE SCIENCE OF
CLIMATE CHANGE FOR AS LONG AS
YOU HAVE.
>> Interview: JUST ABOUT 40
YEARS.
WHAT IS INTERESTING ABOUT THIS
IS THAT WHEN I STARTED IN THE
'70s, IT WAS A DEBATE IN THE
SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY ABOUT WHICH
WAY THE CLIMATE WOULD GO.
BECAUSE ONE SIDE SAID, YOU KNOW,
WE ARE OVERDUE FOR AN ICE AGE.
WE SHOULD BE GOING INTO ANOTHER
ICE AGE.
YOU FOLLOW THE PATTERN OF UP AND
DOWN.
THE PERIOD OF WARM IS 10,000
YEARS.
IT HAS BEEN 12,000 YEARS SINCE
THE LAST ICE AGE.
IT IS GOING TO GET COLD.
THERE WAS A SENSE, THERE IS THE
STUFF CALLED GREENHOUSE GASES WE
ARE PUTTING INTO THE ATMOSPHERE
AND GLOBAL WARMING, IT WILL GO
THE OTHER WAY.
>> Heather: BOTH SIDES...
>> THEY WERE ALMOST EQUALLY BOTH
SIDE.
IT HAS BEEN INTERESTING TO SEE
HOW IT TURNED OUT SINCE THEN.
ALL THE PREDICTIONS WHO SAID IT
IS GETTING WARMER ARE TRUE.
>> Heather: HOLD ON TO THE
THOUGHT.
I WANT TO ASK FROM THE EARLIEST
DAYS WHEN YOU WERE BEGINNING TO
INVESTIGATE THE SCIENCE.
DID YOU HAVE A SENSE THAT
CLIMATE CHANGE OR SOMETHING
RELATED TO WARMING OR THE
CLIMATE WAS GOING TO BE THE
PRESSING ISSUE OF OUR DAY?
>> Interview: I KNEW IT WOULD BE
A BIG ISSUE.
THAT WAS THE TIME IN THE '70s
WHEN EARTH DAY WAS AROUND.
THE ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION
AGENCY.
RACHEL CARSON PUT OUT SILENT
SPRING.
WE GOT THE PICTURES FROM THE
MOON OF THE EARTH.
THE BLUE MARBLE.
WE WERE REALLY LOOKING INWARDS
ON THE EARTH AS A WHOLE AND
REALIZING THINGS ARE CHANGING
AND WE ARE CAUSING THEM AND WE
HAVE TO LOOK AT THIS.
NOT JUST CLIMATE CHANGE, BUT
POLLUTION, FOOD, OCEANS,
EXTINCTION, ALL KINDS OF STUFF.
>> Heather: WHERE ARE WE NOW
BECAUSE HERE WE HAVE A BRAND NEW
U.S. AMBASSADOR TO CANADA.
WHO JUST THE OTHER DAY, KELLY
CRAFT BELIEVES BOTH SIDES.
THE FIRST QUESTION...
>> THE PERCEPTION OF BOTH SIDES
IS IN THE PUBLIC MIND.
AND THAT'S WHERE THERE APPEARS
TO BE A DEBATE ABOUT WHETHER OR
NOT IT IS REALLY HAPPENING.
IN THE SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY,
THERE IS NO DEBATE.
>> Heather: IT IS CLEAR.
>> Interview: CLEAR.
ON THE PUBLIC SIDE, THERE HAS
BEEN A VERY WELL ORGANIZED AND
WELL FUNDED CAMPAIGN THAT IS
FUNDED BY AN OIL COMPANY TO PUT
DOUBT IN THE PUBLIC MIND.
BY SAYING, YOU KNOW, MAYBE NOT.
MAYBE NOT.
ON THE SCIENTIFIC SIDE, THE
UNITED NATIONS WENT TO THE
SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY IN 1988,
AND THEY ASKED THE SAME
QUESTIONS.
IS CLIMATE CHANGE REAL.
ARE HUMANS AFFECTING IT.
THEY GATHERED TOGETHER THE
INTERGOVERNMENTAL PANEL ON
CLIMATE CHANGE.
THE IPCC.
THEY GATHERED 1300 SCIENTISTS
FROM 50 COUNTRIES.
REPRESENTING EVERY CLIMATE PART
OF THE EARTH.
THE ENTIRE EARTH.
AND THEY ASKED THEM, NOT TO DO
ORIGINAL RESEARCH.
THEY SAID WHY DON'T YOU GATHER
ALL THE RESEARCH YOU CAN FIND
THAT HAS BEEN PUBLISHED.
AND TELL US WHAT YOU SEE.
THEY DID THAT.
THEY GATHERED THIS STUFF
TOGETHER.
THEY PUT THAT OUT FOR SCIENTIFIC
REVIEW.
AND THEN THEY PUT OUT A REPORT.
AND THE MAJORITY, THE
OVERWHELMING MAJORITY SAID YES,
IT IS TRUE.
IT IS GOING UP AND HUMANS ARE
RESPONSIBLE FOR SOME OF IT.
NOW, WHERE THE DEBATE WITHIN
SCIENCE IS, WHAT HAPPENS NOW.
SO YOU HAVE THE OPTIMISTS ARE
SAYING, IF WE DO SOMETHING, IT
WILL GO UP THIS MUCH.
THE PESSIMISTS SAY IF WE DON'T
DO SOMETHING, IT WILL BE BAD.
THE TREND IS UP.
>> Heather: WHY IS WHAT IS
HAPPENING NOW DIFFERENT FROM
WHAT HAS HAPPENED PAST.
>> Interview: AN EXCELLENT
QUESTION.
THE EARTH HAS GONE THROUGH
DRAMATIC CHANGES IN THE PAST.
WHEN THE DINOSAURS WERE HERE,
THE EARTH IS WARMER THAN NOW.
AND WE HAD FIVE ICE AGES.
SO THE EARTH GOTTEN COLD AND
WARM AND COLD AND WARM.
WE ARE IN A WARM PERIOD.
THE EARTH IS GETTING WARM FOR
12,000 YEARS.
WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE?
THE DIFFERENCE IS THAT IN
ADDITION TO ALL THOSE CYCLES
THAT THE EARTH NATURALLY GOES
THROUGH, THE LONG ONES THAT TAKE
THOUSANDS OF YEARS AND SHORT
ONES THAT TAKE DECADES OR YEARS.
THE HUMAN ASPECT, WHAT THE
SCIENTISTS ARE SEEING IS ON TOP
OF THAT.
THAT STUFF IS THE BACKGROUND.
THAT HAS ALWAYS BEEN THERE.
ON TOP OF THAT, THERE IS AN
ACCELERATION.
AND IT IS THE RATE OF CHANGE
THAT THE SCIENTISTS ARE
CONCERNED ABOUT.
WE ARE DOING WITHIN DECADES WHAT
USED TO TAKE THOUSANDS OF YEARS
TO DO.
THE CHANGES IN THE PAST WERE
SLOW.
SO NOW WE ARE PUSHING IT.
OUR FOOT IS ON THE ACCELERATEOR
AND CAUSING CHANGES THAT HAPPEN
QUICKLY.
THIS IS A PROBLEM BECAUSE NATURE
DOES NOT HAVE TIME TO ADAPT TO
THAT.
>> Heather: WE HAD JUST THIS
WEEK FROM THE UNITED NATIONS, I
MEAN WHEN I INTERPRET AS A DIRE
WARNING, THE CONCENTRATION OF
CO2 IN THE ATMOSPHERE INCREASED
AT RECORD SPEEDS LAST YEAR.
IT IS NOW REACHED A LEVEL NOT
SEEN FOR MORE THAN 3 MILLION
YEARS.
>> Interview: THAT'S CORRECT.
THE CHANGE WE ARE SEEING NOW
THAT HAS NOT BEEN THIS WAY IN 3
MILLION YEARS, IT HAPPENED IN
THE LAST 150 YEARS.
THE BEGINNING OF THE INDUSTRIAL
REVOLUTION.
YOU SEE IT ON THE CHARTS.
YOU SEE WHEN THAT CURVE
ACCELERATES WHEN WE BURNED COAL,
AND NATURAL GAS.
THE SOLUTION IS OBVIOUS.
WE HAVE TO STOP PUTTING THE
EMISSIONS IN.
EVEN IF WE STOP TODAY, IT WOULD
CONTINUE UP FOR A WHILE BEFORE
IT SLOWS.
>> Heather: A QUESTION ABOUT THE
POINT...
>> THAT IS A HARD QUESTION TO
ANSWER.
THERE HAVE BEEN A COUPLE OF
MILESTONES THE SCIENTISTS PUT
OUT.
ONE OF THEM IS 400 PARTS PER
MILLION OF CARBON IN THE
ATMOSPHERE.
WE ARE PAST THAT.
WE PAST THAT LAST YEAR.
WE MAY NEVER GO BELOW.
THE OTHER IS THE 2 DEGREE RISE.
THEY ARE SAYING IF WE DON'T GO
BEYOND 402 DEGREES, THE WARMING
WOULD LEVEL OUT.
AND OVER A LONG PERIOD OF TIME,
IT WOULD LEVEL OUT AND MAYBE IT
WOULD START TO COME BACK DOWN
AGAIN.
THAT MEANS STOPPING ALL OF THE
INDUSTRY THAT WE HAVE NOW.
TODAY.
THAT IS NOT GOING TO HAPPEN.
SO THAT MEANS WE WILL GO UP
HIGHER THAN 2.
WE MAY GO TO 4.
AND JUST AS A CONTEXT, GOING UP
4º, THE DIFFERENCE IN AVERAGE
TEMPERATURES BETWEEN THE ICE AGE
AND TODAY WAS 5 DEGREES.
WHEN YOU TALK CLIMATE, PEOPLE
SAY THAT IS NOT MUCH.
2 DEGREES.
IT GOES MORE THAN THAT BETWEEN
YESTERDAY AND TODAY.
DAY AND NIGHT.
WINTER AND SUMMER.
WHAT IS 2 DEGREES.
THAT IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
WEATHER AND CLIMATE.
CLIMATE IS AN AVERAGE.
>> Heather: TOM WILSON, HE IS
READING OUR MIND.
HE WANTS TO KNOW THE DIFFERENCE.
AND HOW ONE AFFECTS THE OTHER.
HE IS SPEAKING INTO THIS.
WHAT IS 2 DEGREES.
>> WEATHER IS WHAT YOU SEE.
CLIMATE IS WHAT HAPPENS.
IT IS AN AVERAGE OF THE WHOLE
EARTH OVER A LONG PERIOD OF
TIME.
SO YOU SAY WHAT IS THE AVERAGE
TEMPERATURE.
AVERAGE SEA RISE AS WELL.
THEY TALK ABOUT THE SEA LEVEL
GOING UP INCHES.
THE TIDES ARE MORE THAN THAT.
IT IS AN AVERAGE OVER A LONG
PERIOD OF TIME.
AND TO MOVE THE AVERAGE
TEMPERATURE OF THE EARTH UP
TAKES A LOT OF WEATHER.
IT TAKES A LOT OF STORMS AND
CIRCULATING THE AIR AROUND AND
SHIFTING CLIMATE ZONES AND THE
WATER.
EVEN SHIFTING THE CONTINENTS.
THAT IS WHY A LITTLE BIT OF
CHANGE IN THE CLIMATE MEANS A
LOT OF CHANGE IN THE WEATHER.
>> Heather: A NUMBER OF VIEWERS
BOB ARE WONDERING ABOUT METHANE.
SPECIFICALLY THE WARMING ARCTIC
AND THE FACT THAT THAT IS
ACCELERATING GLOBAL WARMING
BECAUSE OF METHANE BEING
RELEASED IN THE ARCTIC.
EXPLAIN WHERE THAT GAS COMES
FROM.
AND THE EFFECT IT HAS.
>> THIS IS A TICKING TIMEBOMB.
METHANE IS ANOTHER GREENHOUSE
GAS.
IT HAS THE SAME EFFECT ON THE
ATMOSPHERE THAT CARBON DIOXIDE
HAS, IT IS 20 TIMES MORE POTENT.
>> IT ABSORBS MORE OF THE SUN'S
ENERGY.
>> YES.
IT IS A POTENT GAS.
AND THERE IS MORE METHANE IN THE
ARCTIC ICE RIGHT NOW IN
PERMAFROST.
THIS IS UNDER GROUND.
NOT GLACIER.
THERE IS MORE METHANE THERE THAN
CURRENTLY CARBON IN THE
ATMOSPHERE TODAY THAT IS STORED.
THE REASON YOU GET METHANE OUT
OF THE ARCTIC IS BECAUSE MIXED
IN WITH THE ICE ARE THE DEAD
ANIMALS.
THE MAMMOTHS, THE SHORT FACE
BEAR, CAMELS, THEY ARE ALL
THERE.
ORGANIC MATTER FROZEN.
WHEN THE ICE MELTS, THAT STUFF
ROTS.
THAT IS WHERE YOU GET THE
METHANE.
IT IS FROM ROTTING ORGANIC
MATTER.
THAT WILL ADD TO WHAT WE ARE
ALREADY TALKING ABOUT WITH ALL
THE HUMAN CARBON EMISSIONS.
UNFORTUNATELY IN THE ARCTIC, IT
IS ACCELERATING.
THE ARCTIC IS WARMING FASTER
THAN THE REST OF THE WORLD
BECAUSE IT IS AN OCEAN COVERED
IN ICE.
AND ICE REFLECTS SUNLIGHT BACK
TO SPACE.
IT STAYS COOL.
WHEN THE ICE MELTS, YOU GET DARK
SEAWATER.
SEAWATER ABSORBS HEAT.
SUNLIGHT AND GETS WARM.
THAT IS WHY THE ARCTIC IS
GETTING WARMER AND THAT CAUSES
THE PERMAFROST AND RELEASES THE
METHANE.
IT IS A LOOP.
I WORRY ABOUT THAT ONE A LOT.
>> THERE IS A CONCERN THAT HAS
BEEN AROUND FOR A WHILE.
THE OCEAN CURRENTS, THEY ARE
LIKE LIQUID WEATHER.
THE MIDDLE OF THE EARTH IS WARM
BECAUSE THAT'S WHERE THE SUN IS.
THE EQUATOR IS WARM.
THE TOP OF THE BOTTOM OF THE
EARTH ARE COLD.
HEAT LIKES TO GO TO COLD.
THE WARM WATER WANTS TO GO NORTH
AND SOUTH.
THE GULF STREAM ACROSS NORTH
AMERICA.
IT BRINGS WARM WATER TO THE
NORTH.
WHEN IT GETS TO NORTH, THE COLD
ARCTIC WATER SINKS AND FLOWS
SOUTH AGAIN.
THERE IS A CONVEYOR BELT OF HEAT
AND COLD MOVING BETWEEN THE
NORTH AND THE SOUTH.
YOU NEED A DIFFERENCE IN
TEMPERATURE TO DO THAT.
IF THE ARCTIC IS WARM, THEN
THERE IS NOT AS MUCH DRAW AND
THEY ARE WORRIED THAT THE GULF
STREAM WILL CUT OFF.
IT COULD DISRUPT THE OCEAN
CURRENTS.
THE OCEAN CURRENTS DRIVE THE
WEATHER A LOT.
AND THAT'S WHY THEY CALL IT
CLIMATE CHANGE RATHER THAN JUST
GLOBAL WARMING.
>> MORE OF YOUR QUESTIONS FOR
BOB AND HIS ANSWERS AFTER THE
[theme]
Reporter:
CBC Newsmagazine
Canadian scientists
and their counterparts
on the Soviet side
of the North Pole,
have found out
that the Arctic
ice pack is
slowly melting.
The ocean is warming up,
its coat of ice
is now only about
60 per cent as thick
as it was at the turn
of the century.
Reporter: Polar ice
will melt,
and by the end
of the century,
this will bring floods
to low-lying coastal areas.
Inland, there'll
be drought,
and in other places
an increase in storms.
Some crops could
be devastated.
But looking at the
brighter side of things,
at least our
great-grandchildren
should have
warmer winters.
Reporter: Just a sample
of the broad spectrum
of opinion on the changes
taking place
in our atmosphere.
Interview: Cataclysmic,
not a trivial matter,
and not one to
be taken lightly.
The greenhouse effect
will wreck total havoc
on the natural world.
McDonald: All of them
are burning fossil fuels,
all of them are adding
carbon dioxide
to the atmosphere,
but if I put in
too much carbon dioxide,
in effect,
what I'm doing
is putting a dome
over the entire world.
Temperature
begins to rise,
because it's being trapped -
the greenhouse effect.
We can actually see it
here on the thermometer
just from these-- these
ordinary studio lights.
Reporter: Compounding
the problem has been
the systematic depletion
of the world's forests.
Trees need carbon dioxide
for photosynthesis.
As the number of trees
diminish worldwide,
more carbon dioxide is left .
The start
of global warming
can also mean extreme,
and erratic weather,
and the evidence
has been mounting up.
And knowing
what we know now,
how serious it may get,
I don't want to see us
looking back saying,
"Oh, we could
have done this.
We could have done this,
but now it's too late."
I think
what concerns me
most about
global warming,
I feel like we're just
in a little experiment,
and that we're just
not leaving anything
for the future
generations.
Reporter: A piece of film was
supposed to have been cut
to open this year's
Festival of Festivals,
but the organizers
couldn't find any,
so an old fashioned ribbon
was used instead.
This evening,
the gala premiere belongs
to a Canadian film,
Ticket to Heaven.
A number of limousines
have pulled up
with well-dressed people,
unfortunately, nobody seems
to know who they are.
[upbeat, lively]
Reporter:
Despite the problems,
after the film,
it was party time.
And there was everything
you'd expect at a show-biz
bash.
Stars...booze...
good looking women...
good looking men...
people dancing to the music
of Martha and the Muffins,
and more booze.
Reporter:
It's Warren Beatty night
at the Festival of Festivals,
where the spotlight
shines on everyone.
The ushers at the theatre,
had their hands full.
It was their job
to make sure the fans,
and the stars,
didn't collide.
But when the big,
black Continental
pulled up to the curb,
there was no stopping
the autograph hounds.
I'm very
proud of myself,
from restraining myself,
from attempting to wrestle
him to the ground,
cause that's exactly
what I wanted to do.
Reporter: This was
opening night.
A gala for the
North American premiere
of Joshua Then & Now.
There were klieg lights
and limousines,
but there were also some
charming down-home touches.
The star, James Woods, arrs
who came in from Rhode Island
for the event.
Arsenault: Now the oh-so-cool
set have decreed
Canada's little
festival-that-could, a must.
[mumbles an impression]
That, of course,
is Robin Williams...
Claudia Schiffer...
It's the only film festival
in the world
where you see all
of the most important films.
You see a whole year
come in advance.
Arsenault: As un-Canadian
as it is to gloat,
movie critic, Roger Ebert
says go right ahead.
Yeah, it's okay Canada!
It's okay.
It's a real big,
a real good festival.
[crowd cheering]
[theme]
>> HERE IS A QUESTION.
YOU TALKED ABOUT OCEAN WATER.
SALT WATER.
CANADA OF COURSE A LAND OF LAKES
AND RIVERS.
SO WHAT ARE THE PROJECTED
IMPACTS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON THE
FRESH WATER ECOSYSTEMS OF OUR
COUNTRY.
>> CANADA HAS MORE WATER THAN
ANYONE.
WE HAVE ABOUT 20% OF THE WORLD'S
FRESH WATER IN CANADA.
ASTOUNDING.
IN SOME AREAS AS THE TEMPERATURE
GOES UP, THE RIVERS WILL DRY UP.
THERE IS A GOOD CHANCE IN THE
WEST, THE SOUTH SASKATCHEWAN AND
THINGS LIKE THAT, THEY WILL GET
LESS WATER.
IN TERMS OF THE GREAT LAKES,
WHICH IS WHERE MOST OF OUR
INDUSTRY IS AND WHERE A GOOD
PART OF THE POPULATION IS.
>> 30 MILLION CANADIANS AND
AMERICANS IN THE BASIN.
>> IT CAN GO EITHER WAY.
EITHER WAY.
THE AREA IS PREDICTED TO GET
WARMER.
SO IF YOU HAVE HOTTER SUMMERS,
THAT MEANS MORE EVAPORATION.
SO THE LAKES LOSE WATER JUST
FROM THE HEAT.
IF YOU HAVE SHORTER WINTERS,
THAT MEANS LESS SNOWFALL.
SO IN THE SPRING RUNOFF, THERE
IS NOT AS MUCH SNOW MELT TO
RECHARGE THEM AGAIN.
THAT MEANS THEY CAN GO DOWN.
ON THE OTHER HAND, IT COULD GO
IN THE OPPOSITE DIRECTION.
BECAUSE IF THE STORMS, THE
HURRICANES, THEY COME ACROSS THE
ATLANTIC OCEAN AND HIT THE
UNITED STATES AND ESPECIALLY
THAT COME INTO TEXAS LIKE WE SAW
THIS YEAR, THE STORMS ARE
STRONGER.
WHICH WAS ALSO PREDICTED.
IF THEY ARE STRONGER, THEY WILL
COME INTO CANADA AND BRING MORE
RAIN TO THE GREAT LAKES AREA.
AND ALSO, WE HAVE TO THINK ABOUT
WATER IN TERMS OF THE FREE TRADE
AGREEMENT WITH THE UNITED
STATES.
THE U.S. HAS PLANS TO DRAIN THE
LAKES TO FEED THE HUNGRY
SOUTHWEST, BECAUSE THEY WILL BE
REALLY FEELING DROUGHTS IN THE
DESERT REGIONS.
CAN WE ALLOW THEM TO DO THAT?
HOW DO WE DEAL WITH THAT.
THE GREAT LAKES ARE A JEWEL.
THEY ARE THE LARGEST FRESH WATER
SYSTEM ON THE PLANET.
WE REALLY HAVE TO TAKE CARE OF
THEM.
>> Heather: NANCY MUST HAVE BEEN
WATCHING THE LAST TIME THE TWO
OF US WERE TALKING...
A QUESTION ABOUT SPACE:
>> ROCKETS SPEND 2 MINUTES IN
THE ATMOSPHERE WHEN THEY TAKE
OFF.
AFTER THAT, THEY ARE ABOVE THE
ATMOSPHERE.
THEY ARE NOT LIKE HIGH FLYING
AIRPLANES THAT PUT CARBON
DIOXIDE IN FOR HOURS AT A TIME.
NO.
THEY DON'T AFFECT THE CLIMATE
THAT WAY.
ON THE OTHER HAND, IF IT WASN'T
FOR SPACECRAFT, IF IT WASN'T FOR
THE ROCKETS TO PUT SATELLITES
UP, WE WOULD NOT KNOW ABOUT THE
CLIMATE ISSUES.
IT IS THANKS TO SATELLITES WE
SPOTTED THE OZONE HOLE.
GET THE WEATHER.
IN YOUR BUSINESS, YOU GO TO THE
SATELLITE WEATHER.
IT IS SATELLITES THAT SHOW US
THE SHIFTING OCEAN CURRENTS, EL
NINO ACROSS THE PACIFIC.
THE OSCILLATIONS THAT HAPPEN.
WE DIDN'T KNOW THEY EXISTED
BEFORE WE HAD SATELLITE.
SO, I THINK WE SHOULD BE
THANKING THE SPACE PROGRAM FOR
THE ENVIRONMENTAL AWARENESS
RATHER THAN BE WORRIED ABOUT THE
EFFECT ON THE ATMOSPHERE.
>> Heather: MAYBE NOT AVIATION.
THAT HAS A DISPROPORTIONATE
EFFECT.
PEOPLE ARE TRYING TO FIND
CLEANER WAYS TO GO AROUND THE
WORLD.
>> THE HUMAN BODY IS ONE OF THE
MOST REMARKABLE ADAPTATIONS IN
EVOLUTION HISTORY.
ONE OF THE REASONS HOMOSAPIENS
SURVIVED IS BECAUSE WE ARE
ADAPTABLE.
WE CAN ADAPT TO CLIMATE CHANGE.
ACTUALLY IT WAS PARTLY CLIMATE
CHANGE THAT MADE EXTINCTION.
WE ARE GOOD AT ADAPTING.
I AM NOT WORRIED ABOUT THE HUMAN
BODY.
HOWEVER, WE ARE CAUSING, NOT
JUST THROUGH CLIMATE CHANGE BUT
HABITAT DESTRUCTION AND THE FOOD
AND THE POPULATION, THERE ARE 7
BILLION OF US, WE ARE CAUSING
THE GREATEST EXTINCTION SINCE
THE DINOSAUR.
THE SCALE OF EXTINCTION.
THE ANIMALS ARE GOING EXTINCT AS
THE LAST TIME THE ASTEROID HIT
THE EARTH.
WILL IT AFFECT OUR BODIES, I
WOULD LIKE TO EAT YEAH.
WHAT ABOUT THE FISH IN THE SEA.
WE ARE AFFECTING INSECTS THAT
ARE COMING NORTH AND KILLING OFF
THE CROPS.
WE ARE HAVING TO ADAPT TO THAT
BECAUSE EVER INSECTICIDE
RESISTANCE AND DISEASES AND
ANTIBIOTIC RESISTANCE AND TRYING
TO FIGHT THAT.
WE ARE AFFECTED INDIRECTLY.
NOT DIRECTLY BY THE CLIMATE
CHANGE ITSELF.
IT IS ALL THE OTHER THINGS WE
ARE DOING, WE ARE AT THE TOP OF
THE FOOD CHAIN.
IF WE KNOCK OUT THE BOTTOM, WE
WILL GO WITH IT.
THE BOTTOM OF THE FOOD CHAIN IS
AFFECTED NOW IN A SERIOUS WAY.
>> Heather: GREAT QUESTION.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>>> GETTING TO VERY CLOSE TO THE
END, MY GOODNESS, WE COULD
HAVE -- THERE IS A LOT OF
SCIENCE TO COVER.
WE ALLUDED TO THIS.
IT IS WORTH MENTIONING...
>> THAT IS A GREAT QUESTION.
I LIKE THAT ONE BECAUSE THE
EARTH IS NOT BEING AFFECTED IN
THE SAME WAY IN ALL LOCATIONS.
SOME AREAS ARE GOING TO BE
EXPERIENCING MORE DROUGHTS THAN
OTHER AREAS.
ISLAND COUNTRIES ARE FEELING SEA
LEVEL RISE.
THE OCEAN IS RISING FOR TWO
REASONS, AS IT GETS WARMER,
WHICH IT IS, IT EXPANDS.
ANYTHING THAT GETS HOT IS
BIGGER.
THE OCEAN IS INFLATING ITSELF BY
GETTING WARM.
WE ARE SEEING THE MELTING OF
ANTARCTICA AND GREENLAND.
THE ICE ON THE LAND IS FLOWING
INTO THE SEA AND RISING IT UP.
THEY ARE PREDICTING A METRE OR
TWO METRE OF RISE IN THE NEXT
100 YEARS.
THAT IS A LOT.
ON AVERAGE.
THAT IS AN AVERAGE.
THAT MEANS STORM SURGES WILL BE
BLOWING IN.
WE SAW NEW YORK CITY PART OF IT
INUNDATED YEARS AGO WHEN A STORM
CAME UP THE COAST.
FLOODING.
FLORIDA WILL FEEL IT MORE
BECAUSE IT IS SO LOW.
THEY WILL FEEL THE SEA LEVEL
RISE.
AND THE WARMING DOWN THERE.
AND THE ARCTIC, IT IS WARMING
QUICKER THAN ANYWHERE ON THE
PLANET.
IT IS NOT EVEN.
AND THERE ARE SOME AREAS LIKE
THE MIDDLE OF ANTARCTICA,
BELIEVE IT OR NOT, IS GETTING
COLDER BECAUSE THERE IS A POLAR
VORTEX THERE AND THE AIR GOES
DOWN IN THE MIDDLE AND CAUSES A
COOLING RIDGE.
SOME DENIERS SAY THAT.
THE ANTARCTICA IS GETTING
COLDER, ONLY IN ONE SPOT.
IT IS COMPLICATED.
AND THAT'S WHY WE HAVE TO WATCH
IT.
IT IS NOT AN EASY PICTURE.
EVEN THE WAY THE TEMPERATURE
GOES UP, IT DOES NOT GO UP
EVENTUALLY.
IT WILL GO UP AND LEVEL OFF FOR
A BIT.
EVERYBODY SAID IT IS NOT
WARMING.
THEN IT GOES UP AGAIN.
AND THEN IT LEVELS OFF AND GOES
UP AGAIN.
IT IS A COMPLICATED PICTURE.
THE EARTH HAS ITS CYCLES IT IS
GOING THROUGH.
WE HAVE OUR CYCLES WE ARE GOING
THROUGH.
WE CAN'T STOP WHAT THE EARTH IS
DOING BUT CAN CONTROL WHAT WE
ARE DOING AND TAKE OUR FOOT OFF
THE ACCELERATOR TO GIVE THE
EARTH A CHANCE.
IT CAN HEAL ITSELF IF WE STOP
PUSHING IT.
I BELIEVE WE CAN IF WE TAKE IT
SERIOUSLY AND STOP SAYING THERE
IS A DEBATE ABOUT IT.
THERE IS NO DEBATE.
IT IS REAL.
LET'S GET OFF THE POT AND DO
SOMETHING ABOUT IT.
>> Heather: THAT WOULD BE A
REALLY GREAT CLOSING COMMENT.
WHAT CAN WE DO AS A COUNTRY AND
INDIVIDUALS.
>> I FIND IS THAT THE REAL
CHANGE FOR THE FUTURE TOO, GO TO
CLEAN ENERGY, TO HAVE -- IT IS
HAPPENING AT A COMMUNITY LEVEL.
IT IS HAPPENING AT THE GRASS
ROOTS LEVEL.
IT IS NOT HAPPENING AT THE
FEDERAL LEVEL.
IT TAKES A LONG TIME FOR BIG
GOVERNMENT TO CHANGE THEIR MIND
AND YOU GET A NEW GOVERNMENT.
I FIND THAT INDIVIDUAL TOWNS,
COMMUNITIES, AND EVEN PROVINCES
AND STATES ARE TAKING THE
PROBLEM THEMSELVES TO DO THINGS
LIKE A RIVER CLEANUP DAY OR A
SHORELINE CLEANUP DAY AND PLANT
TREES.
LET'S PUT IN FOR BIKE LANES IN
THE DOWNTOWN COMMUNITIES.
LET GO BACK TO A VILLAGE
LIFE-STYLE WHERE YOU CAN WALK TO
THINGS RATHER THAN JUST DRIVE
EVERYWHERE.
AND FROM A POLITICIANS POINT OF
VIEW GIVE TAX BREAKS TO
BUSINESSES THAT ARE GREEN
ALREADY.
SO THEIR PRICES WILL COME DOWN
AND BE COMPETITIVE.
AND THEN EDUCATE THE PUBLIC TO
SAY THIS IS A GOOD IDEA.
SOLAR PANELS ARE NOT AS
EXPENSIVE AS THEY USED TO BE.
AND MAKE YOUR HOUSE MORE
EFFICIENT WHEN YOU RENOVATE IT.
PUT IN LOW FLUSH TOILETS AND A
HIGH EFFICIENCY FURNACE AND TRY
TO REDUCE THE FOOTPRINT.
EFFICIENCY CAN TAKE US SO FAR.
WE ARE WASTING SO MUCH NOW.
WE CAN GO FAR.
>> Heather: GREEN TECHNOLOGY IS
A GLOBAL INDUSTRY.
WORTH $1 TRILLION.
>> YES.
THERE IS HOPE.
>> Heather: THERE IS HOPE.
SHALL WE LEAVE IT THERE.
>> I LIKE TO BELIEVE THAT.
I THINK HUMANS ARE ADAPTABLE AND
SMART AND CANADA HAS GREAT
INTELLECTUAL CAPITAL AND HAVE
THE RESOURCES AND THE RESEARCH
COMMUNITY HERE THAT CAN LOOK
INTO BUILDING BETTER BATTERIES
FOR CARS AND BETTER WINDOWS AND
BETTER ALTERNATIVE CLEAN ENERGY
AND HOW TO LIVE IN A CLEAN WAY.
IT IS NOT A MATTER OF GOING TO
THE CAVES OR LOSING JOBS.
IT IS MOVING FORWARD.
IT IS EVOLVING INTO THE NEXT
STAGE OF OR TECHNOLOGY.
THE WAY WE WILL LIVE.
>> Heather: THANK YOU FOR
HELPING US LEARN ABOUT THE
SCIENCE FOR THE MANY DECADES AND
TONIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR FANTASTIC
QUESTIONS.
ALWAYS GREAT.
>> ALWAYS GREAT.
the Trans-Mountain pipeline.
Between Jasper and Redpath,
a start is made.
All the latest weapons
employed by engineers in modern
pipeline construction,
converge on the theatres of war.
The enemy, one by one,
toppling to empyrean cries
of "Timber!"
And the steel monsters arrive
to 145 sightings from
Edmonton to Vancouver.
5,000 railway flatcars bring
their loads of pipes
and then to their
individual prearranged spots
in the continuous
chain.
They are linked together by a
complicated process that
ensures 100
per cent accuracy.
The pipe is 24 inches in
diameter and every inch of it
must be
evenly coated.
And then checked
and rechecked.
Then a wrapping is added,
made from
glass, felt,
and asbestos.
As the men observe their
finished product laid to rest.
A continuous tube,
a liquid railway
stretching 718 miles.
The big question, is of course,
whether there is life on Mars?
And the short answer is
that it's not impossible.
No one knows what
Mars really looks like,
but this week, streaming back
from deep space is the best
information in history.Brins
concerning the origin of life.
Whether man is something special
or a special freak.
The search for life on Mars
is still continuing.
Data received from
the Viking Landers
have puzzled NASA scientists
and within the past
two days they've been
able to confirm that
the ice caps of Mars,
are really frozen water.
Not carbon dioxide,
as once believed.
So the chances
of finding life
get better with
each passing day.
Its past was hostile
and torn by meteors,
its present is
cold and barren.
A colony here would seem
a futile fantasy.
But today's dreamers are
scientists and they do
their dreaming
for NASA.
I think the possibility
of Mars as a second home
for mankind is very
important for our future
as a race.
The students are building
a prototype Martian colony
called Marsville.
It's on Earth but they do
understand what it will take
to settle on Mars.
The temperature on Mars is a lot
colder than on Earth.
And these students understand
cooperation is the only
way to get to Mars.
With all the technology they
have now we could
have something go up
really soon.
They've come from all over
the world for this meeting
of the International
Mars Society.
They've got
bumper stickers.
They've got a Martian flag
already picked out.
The one question that always
comes up is this,
"Is it worth the many
billions more to put people
on the surface
of the red planet,
rather than
just machines?"
The Mars fans here admit
the barriers are huge.
But they also say we have
the capability and the money
to get to Mars.
All me need now
is the will to do it.
To find out more we need
to out into space.
And space research,
like politics,
is the art
of the possible.
What we would like to do must be
weighed against what we can do.
[theme]
>> WHEN I SAW IT, THIS IS LIKE
80% INCREASE.
>> Heather: SKY ROCKETING RENT,
AND A LOSS OF CULTURE.
TWO THINGS THAT ARE BEING FEL F
ACUTELY IN A NUMBER OF LOS
ANGELES NEIGHBOURHOODS.
THEY ARE GENTRIFIED.
FOR LONG-TIME RESIDENTS, ALL THE
UPSCALING HAS A DOWNSIDE.
>> Reporter: HOW DID IT GET SO
FAR?
HOW DID IT COME TO THIS?
THE RACIAL FIRESTORM OVER OF ALL
THINGS, A COFFEE SHOP.
>> I DON'T KNOW.
I DON'T KNOW.
>> Reporter: LOOK AROUND, THE
CUSTOMERS ARE ARTISTS AND
HIPSTERS.
THE PLACE HAS BEEN DUBBED WHITE
WAVE BY THE LATINO NEIGHBOURS.
THEY FEAR THE NEIGHBOURHOOD, THE
CENTER OF LATINO CULTURE COULD
MEAN THE BEGINNING OF THE END.
>> OPENED AND PEOPLE PROCESSED
IT STRONGLY FOR A COUPLE OF
WEEKS.
AND THEN AFTER THAT DIED DOWN,
THE WINDOWS WERE VANDALIZED.
>> Reporter: WHY PEOPLE ARE
ANGRY, TO UNDERSTAND, WE NEED TO
VISIT THE GATEWAY, THE PLAZA.
YOU NEED A MARIACHI, YOU COME
HERE.
THERE ARE FEWER AND FEWER
MUSICIANS HERE THESE DAYS.
MANY CAN NO LONGER AFFORD THE
RENT.
>> Interview: THERE IS MINE, A
ONE BEDROOM APARTMENT HERE.
>> Reporter: HE LIVED IN THE
BUILDING FOR 20 YEARS.
THE SIGNS ARE A CALL TO ACTION.
THE RENT STRIKE AFTER A LETTER
FROM THE DEVELOPER WHO BOUGHT
THE BUILDING.
>> Interview: MY GOD WHEN I SAW
THE LETTER, THIS IS HELL BROKE
LOOSE.
THIS IS 80% INCREASE JUST LIKE
THAT.
>> Reporter: WITH PROPERTY AND
RENT PRICES GOING UP, THE PEOPLE
WITH MONEY, MOST OF THEM WHITE,
ARE DRAWN TO UNDESIRABLE
MINORITY NEIGHBOURHOODS WHERE
THE RESIDENTS FEAR THEIR CULTURE
WILL BE ERASED.
ABOUT 15 KILOMETRES AWAY, A
SIMILAR THING IS HAPPENING IN
THE HEART OF AFRICAN-AMERICAN
LOS ANGELES.
HUNDREDS OF ANGRY RESIDENTS ARE
TALKING ABOUT WHAT SEEMS LIKE
GOOD NEWS.
A NEW MALL AND HOUSING
DEVELOPMENT.
LOOK AT THE PROMOTIONAL
BROCHURE, THEY ARE PROOF OF WHO
IS EXPECTED TO ATTRACT.
THEY FEAR IT WILL KILL THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN BUSINESS.
THE MALL DEVELOPER IS BLACK.
>> THEY WILL CHANGE THE FLAVOUR
AND TENOR AND THE NEIGHBOURHOOD
AND THE DIVERSITY WILL SLOWLY
TURN INTO ESSENTIALLY A WHITE
COMMUNITY.
>> Reporter: THAT IS THE
CONUNDRUM.
THE HISTORIC MINORITY
COMMUNITIES WANT DEVELOPMENT,
BUT THAT IS THE THING THAT WILL
ATTRACT OUTSIDERS.
EXPERTS SAID EVEN MEASURES LIKE
RENT CONTROL WILL DO LITTLE TO
CHANGE THAT.
>> THE FLOOD OF CAPITAL IS
COMING IN THE WAY TOWARD THESE
NEIGHBOURHOODS.
>> THE STORM IS COMING.
YOU ARE GOING TO BE -- NEW
APARTMENTS AND NEW HOUSES.
>> Reporter: HE PRACTICES THE
SPEECH FOR THE OTHER TENANTS.
FIRST THE MARIACHIS WILL
DISAPPEAR.
>> ONE, TWO THREE, YOU WILL BE
GONE.
>> Reporter: CBC NEWS, LOS
ANGELES.
>> Heather: WHEN WE COME BACK, A
QUICK RECAP OF SOME OF THE TOP
STORIES.
FIRST, LET'S CHECK THE BUSINESS
NUMBERS.
THE TSX EDGED UP SLIGHTLY.
THE DOLLAR INCREASED 3/10th OF A
CENT.
>>> IN NEW YORK, THE DOW GAINED
NEARLY 23 POINTS.
THE PRICE OF OIL ROSE 1.10.
and play with your
own little world.
There are other
worlds out there.
Lots of them.
And you can't just ignore them
or brush them aside.
You see, the world you know
is really made up of
lots of other worlds.
And all of them have
their own problems,
which in fact,
become your problems.
And worlds aren't simply
made up of problems,
good things happen,
exciting things.
And they all affect you.
The thing is,
to understand what's happening,
And to understand,
you have to have a complete
and comprehensive
view of matters.
And where to get
this information?
It's easy.
The National News.
Nightly.
OnCBC Television.
So welcome other worlds
into your life.
It's almost fun.
The National News.
Reporter:
Five nights a week
in the national news room of
CBC Television,
the stories come in from
all parts of the world,to bd
for use on
The National.
[clicking and clacking of
typewriters]
The facts are checked
and the backgrounds gathered.
[rotary phones being dialled]
On the spot reports
are collected,
then the films and the tapes
are evaluated and edited,
readied for
the air.
CBC'scorrespondents
in all corners of the world
report and interpret
the news.
[dramatic]
Wherever things
are happening,
you'll get
the complete information,
right here on
CBC Television.
I'm Warren Batis.
Those are just some
of the things
that go into
The National.
Join me.
[dramatic]
[jovial]
From here,
each day at one o'clock,
Canada is given
the exact time.
60 Canadian radio stations
relay the signal tothe nation.
[silence]
TheCBC
brings you
theDominion Observatory
Officialtime signal.
The beginning
of the long dash,
which follows
ten seconds of silence,
will indicate exactly
one o'clock
Eastern daylight time.
[short beep]
[long beep]
One o'clock,
Eastern daylight time.
>> BEFORE WE GO, ANOTHER LOOK AT
OUR TOP STORIES.
THE GOVERNOR GENERAL PAYETTE IS
BEING CRITICIZED FOR COMMENTS AT
A SCIENCE CONFERENCE.
SHE RAISED THE ISSUE OF
CREATEISM IN A WAY THAT SOME SAY
IS DIVISIVE.
>>> CANADA'S LABOUR MARKET HAS
EXPANDED FOR AN 11th STRAIGHT
MONTH.
THE ECONOMY ADDED 35,000 NEW
JOBS IN OCTOBER.
MORE THAN TWICE AS MANY AS
ANALYSTS EXPECTED.
>>> THAT IS THE NATIONAL.
FOR NEWS AT ANY HOUR, YOU CAN GO
TO CBC NEWS.CA.
I'M HEATHER HISCOX.
THANK YOU FOR JOINING US.